<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Learn Mem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Learn. Mem</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">learnmem</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Learning &#x00026; Memory</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1072-0502</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1549-5485</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">27918277</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">5110990</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1101/lm.042044.116</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ZhangLM042044</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Brief Communication</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Computational model of a positive BDNF feedback loop in hippocampal neurons following inhibitory avoidance training</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">Model of a BDNF feedback loop</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Model of a BDNF feedback loop</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Yili</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Alberini</surname><given-names>Cristina M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>Douglas A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>John H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurobiology and Anatomy, McGovern Medical School, Houston, Texas 77030, USA</aff><aff id="af2"><label>2</label>Center for Neural Science, New York University, New York, New York 10003, USA</aff><author-notes><corresp>Corresponding author: <email>John.H.Byrne@uth.tmc.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><month>12</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>23</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>714</fpage><lpage>722</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>29</day><month>2</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>23</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/site/misc/terms.xhtml">&#x000a9; 2016 Zhang et al.; Published by Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press</ext-link></copyright-statement><copyright-year>2016</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This article is distributed exclusively by Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press for the first 12 months after the full-issue publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://learnmem.cshlp.org/site/misc/terms.xhtml">http://learnmem.cshlp.org/site/misc/terms.xhtml</ext-link>). After 12 months, it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International), as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="ZhangLM042044.pdf"/><abstract><p>Inhibitory avoidance (IA) training in rodents initiates a molecular cascade within hippocampal neurons. This cascade contributes to the transition of short- to long-term memory (i.e., consolidation). Here, a differential equation-based model was developed to describe a positive feedback loop within this molecular cascade. The feedback loop begins with an IA-induced release of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF), which in turn leads to rapid phosphorylation of the cAMP response element-binding protein (pCREB), and a subsequent increase in the level of the &#x003b2; isoform of the CCAAT/enhancer binding protein (C/EBP&#x003b2;). Increased levels of C/EBP&#x003b2; lead to increased <italic>bdnf</italic> expression. Simulations predicted that an empirically observed delay in the BDNF-pCREB-C/EBP&#x003b2; feedback loop has a profound effect on the dynamics of consolidation. The model also predicted that at least two independent self-sustaining signaling pathways downstream from the BDNF-pCREB-C/EBP&#x003b2; feedback loop contribute to consolidation. Currently, the nature of these downstream pathways is unknown.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="funding-1"><funding-source>NIH <named-content content-type="funder-id">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100000002</named-content></funding-source><award-id>MH065635</award-id><award-id>NS073974</award-id></award-group></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The transformation of short-term memory into long-term memory (LTM) is known as consolidation and can require days to complete. During consolidation, memories pass through several distinct phases. The molecular processes that underlie these distinct phases of consolidation are not well understood.</p><p>Inhibitory avoidance (IA) conditioning is an attractive system to examine mechanisms of consolidation (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>,<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C45" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C6" ref-type="bibr">Bekinschtein et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C37" ref-type="bibr">Radulovic and Tronson 2010</xref>). IA is usually acquired in a single training trial, thus providing a well-defined time point for the beginning of consolidation. The present study focuses on the IA protocol described by <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. (2014)</xref>. Briefly, the IA training and testing chamber is divided into a safe compartment and a shock compartment. The animal is placed in the safe compartment and allowed to spontaneously enter the shock compartment (i.e., step-through), where it is subjected to a foot shock. During subsequent testing, memory of this aversive stimulus is measured by an increased latency for spontaneous entry into the shock compartment. Several brain structures are involved in step-through IA (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C3" ref-type="bibr">Baldi and Bucherelli 2015</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C20" ref-type="bibr">Izquierdo et al. 2016</xref>), including the hippocampus (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C24" ref-type="bibr">Kornisiuk et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C22" ref-type="bibr">Khakpai et al. 2016</xref>).</p><p>The consolidation of IA memory is believed to begin with the extracellular release of BDNF, which then acts through the tropomyosin-related kinase B (TrkB) receptor on the plasma membrane to initiate activation of kinases, other intracellular signaling events, and gene expression (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C31" ref-type="bibr">Minichiello 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C34" ref-type="bibr">Panja and Bramham 2014</xref>). Recently, <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. (2014)</xref> delineated a BDNF-CREB-C/EBP&#x003b2;-positive feedback loop in rat hippocampus that contributes to consolidation. In the positive feedback loop, BDNF is released during training, leading to a rapid increase in CREB phosphorylation and a subsequent increase in <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; expression. The resultant increase in C/EBP&#x003b2; contributes to a delayed increase in <italic>bdnf</italic> expression (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C10" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C27" ref-type="bibr">Martinowich et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C16" ref-type="bibr">Guan et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). Anti-BDNF antibody, given before IA training, blocks the increase in pCREB levels at 30 min and 20 h post-training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2012</xref>), demonstrating that increased BDNF levels, in turn, can increase CREB phosphorylation. These reciprocal interactions complete the positive feedback loop. Previous studies found that BDNF activates multiple feedback processes that regulate cellular activities (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C12" ref-type="bibr">Cheng et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C48" ref-type="bibr">Vaynman et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C26" ref-type="bibr">Maharana et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C51" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C47" ref-type="bibr">Tuvikene et al. 2016</xref>). The mechanism by which BDNF selectively phosphorylates CREB to activate the BDNF-CREB-C/EBP&#x003b2; feedback loop after IA training is unclear. However, the existence of this feedback loop and its importance for consolidation of IA memory has been verified by experiments in <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. (2014)</xref>, as follows: (1) Hippocampal injection of an anti-BDNF antibody inhibits the phosphorylation of CREB by IA; (2) Knockdown of <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; expression by an antisense oligonucleotide blocks induction of <italic>bdnf</italic> exon IV mRNA by IA; (3) Knockdown of C/EBP&#x003b2; expression also impairs IA memory consolidation, and this impairment is rescued by hippocampal injection of BDNF; and (4) Hippocampal injection of an anti-BDNF antibody before training blocks the up-regulation of <italic>bdnf</italic> exon IV expression post-training. The feedback loop appears to be terminated by increased binding of transcriptional repressors to the <italic>bdnf</italic> promoter &#x0223c;48 h after IA conditioning (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>Here, a mathematical model of the major components of the BDNF feedback loop was developed. Simulations examined the extent to which the loop contributes to the dynamic properties of sensitivity of memory (quantified as a synaptic weight increase) to protein synthesis inhibition and to other disruptions, such as are often studied empirically (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C39" ref-type="bibr">Santini et al. 2014</xref>), during memory formation and persistence. Ordinary differential equations were used to describe the dynamics of signaling pathways that regulate BDNF, CREB, and C/EBP&#x003b2;. To fit empirical observations, two independent self-sustaining signaling pathways, regulated by pCREB and C/EBP&#x003b2;, were hypothesized to contribute to LTM formation and persistence. Simulations suggested that the delayed initiation of the BDNF-positive feedback loop may play a substantial role in the dynamics of time windows for disruption of memory by protein synthesis inhibition and other treatments. The dynamics of the putative biochemical elements that determine the delays in initiation, and in termination, of the BDNF feedback loop were also delineated.</p><p>The molecular network that we model is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F1">Figure 1</xref>A. This network embodies and simplifies the essential elements of the above BDNF feedback loop and as such it is a first step in formulating a quantitative model of mechanisms involved in IA conditioning. More detailed future models will need to include other BNDF feedback loops (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C48" ref-type="bibr">Vaynman et al. 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C26" ref-type="bibr">Maharana et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C51" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C47" ref-type="bibr">Tuvikene et al. 2016</xref>), BDNF-dependent activation of translation via activation of phosphatidylinositol-3-kinase and mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) kinase, as well as BDNF's contribution to dendritic protein synthesis and the latter's contribution to LTP/LTD (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C17" ref-type="bibr">Hou and Klann 2004</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C21" ref-type="bibr">Jain and Bhalla 2009</xref>).</p><fig id="ZHANGLM042044F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Simulating signaling pathways essential to consolidation of IA LTM. (<italic>A</italic>) Schematic model of the positive BDNF feedback loop that contributes to memory consolidation. The structure of this molecular pathway is based on <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. (2014)</xref>. Details and equations are given in the main text. Empirical results (black circles) indicate that BDNF protein (<italic>C</italic>) and pCREB (<italic>D</italic>) increase for at least 20 h after training but BDNF mRNA (<italic>B</italic>) and C/EBP&#x003b2; protein (<italic>E</italic>) do not significantly increase until 6 h after training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>), with all species returning to basal levels 48 h after training. Simulated time courses are qualitatively similar to the empirical data.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZhangLM042044f01"/></fig><p>Standard values for all model parameters are given in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1101/lm.042044.116/-/DC1">Supplemental Table S1</ext-link>. The differential equations of the model are also collected therein. However, the elements of these equations are also set forth here. The synthesis and degradation of BDNF is described by the following differential equation:
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M1"><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="0.4em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">BDNF</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">stim</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">fB</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">trans</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ANI</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dBDNF</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">BDNF</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">BDNF</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dB</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
where <italic>stim</italic> represents a stimulus that simulates the initial activation of the BDNF pathway. A single strong stimulus was simulated, such as occurs in one-trial IA training. <italic>Stim</italic> is 0 except for an increase to 30 &#x000b5;M/sec, for 1 min, to simulate training. BDNF is released by the initial stimulus and, subsequently, produced by the BDNF feedback loop. In simulations, [<italic>BDNF</italic>] increases abruptly and transiently after stimulus; this increase does not represent new BDNF synthesis, but rather activity-induced vesicular release of pre-existing BDNF (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C41" ref-type="bibr">Slipczuk et al. 2009</xref>). <italic>Bdnf</italic> represents <italic>bdnf</italic> mRNA, with the dynamics described below. <italic>ANI</italic> (anisomycin, a commonly used protein synthesis inhibitor) represents the effect of protein synthesis inhibition. <italic>ANI</italic> remains at 0 in the absence of inhibition and increases to 0.8 for 6 h to simulate inhibition. A similar strength of inhibition of the protein synthesis rate (&#x0223c;80%, for &#x0223c;6 h) is commonly reported empirically (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C29" ref-type="bibr">Milekic et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>Previous empirical studies indicate that total CREB remains at its basal level for 20 h after IA training in rat hippocampus (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). Therefore, the model keeps total [CREB], denoted by <italic>CREB</italic><sub><italic>total</italic></sub>, fixed. The differential equation describing CREB activation by phosphorylation and the conservation relation for fixed total CREB are therefore as follows, with [<italic>CREB</italic>] denoting non-phosphorylated CREB:
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M2"><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="0.4em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basalp</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">creb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">phos</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">creb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">BDNF</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">BDNF</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">BDNF</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dphos</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">creb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M3"><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CREB</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">total</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:math></disp-formula>
This minimal model does not explicitly include biochemical processes that mediate CREB phosphorylation in response to BDNF elevation. Empirically, these processes are not well characterized. BDNF acts through TrkB receptors to activate MAP kinase signaling cascades, including ERK1/2 isoforms of MAPK, and this MAPK activation is important for induction of <italic>bdnf</italic> exon IV (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C47" ref-type="bibr">Tuvikene et al. 2016</xref>). These authors also found that the AP-1 transcription factor is necessary for induction of other exons of BDNF, but not exon IV. However, earlier work demonstrated that CREB activation is necessary for BDNF induction (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C43" ref-type="bibr">Tao et al. 1998</xref>) and <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. (2014)</xref> show that active CREB specifically induces exon IV expression, with exon IV being the most abundant transcript in the hippocampus. Thus, this model assigns pCREB an essential role. MAPK does not appear to phosphorylate CREB directly. Instead, MAPK phosphorylates and activates kinases such as ribosomal S6 kinase or mitogen- and stress-activated kinase, which in turn can phosphorylate CREB (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C13" ref-type="bibr">De Cesare et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C1" ref-type="bibr">Arthur et al. 2004</xref>). The activation of these downstream kinases in response to BDNF has not yet been well characterized.</p><p>Subsequently, synthesis of the transcription factor C/EBP&#x003b2; is up-regulated by active CREB. Empirically, CREB and C/EBP&#x003b2; are essential for memory consolidation after IA training. pCREB significantly increases 30 min after IA training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>), whereas both <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; mRNA and C/EBP&#x003b2; protein do not increase until more than 6 h after training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>; C Alberini, unpublished observations). Experiments have not yet determined the extent to which the increase of the C/EBP&#x003b2; protein after IA training is a consequence of increased pCREB. However, the expression of <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; is regulated by a cAMP response element after contextual learning (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C19" ref-type="bibr">Impey et al. 1998</xref>), and thus presumably by pCREB. Therefore, the model assumes that an increase in pCREB leads to increased expression of C/EBP&#x003b2; after stimulus. The mechanism underlying the delay in increase in C/EBP&#x003b2; mRNA and protein is not known. The model assumes that phosphorylated CREB binds to the promoter of C/EBP&#x003b2; immediately after training. However, the effect of CREB to activate transcription is blocked by repressors that are also bound to the promoter of C/EBP&#x003b2; (e.g., Sin3a discussed in <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>), until the repressors are removed &#x0223c;6 h after training. In the model, the effect of pCREB on C/EBP&#x003b2; expression is simply reflected by a function <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>act_cebp</italic></sub> (see Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M5">5</xref>). To simulate the observed delay in increase of the C/EBP&#x003b2; protein (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>), <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>act_cebp</italic></sub> remains at a constant basal synthesis rate <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>f_cebp_basal</italic></sub> for 6 h after stimulus, after which time it is regulated by <italic>pCREB</italic>. A 6 h delay is selected, because C/EBP&#x003b2; is still near the basal level at 6 h after training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>). In the model, starting at 6 h, <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>act_cebp</italic></sub> is regulated by <italic>pCREB</italic> so that the C/EBP&#x003b2; protein (variable [<italic>CEBP</italic>], Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M4">4</xref>) starts to increase. By 9 h post-stimulus, [<italic>CEBP</italic>] is elevated to a level close to empirical observation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F1">Fig. 1</xref>E) consistent with data (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>).</p><p>It is hypothesized that the &#x0223c;6 h delay in <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; induction is due to the time taken for repressors to unbind from the <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; promoter after a stimulus. Because the delay is only applied once, with the regulation of C/EBP&#x003b2; by pCREB beginning at 6 h post-stimulus instead of at 0 h, the differential equation describing the dynamics of C/EBP&#x003b2; synthesis and degradation is an ordinary differential equation, which is as follows:
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M4"><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="0.4em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basal</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cebp</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cebp</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo movablelimits="true">max</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ANI</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cebp</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cebp</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
with the delay incorporated in the definition of <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>act_cebp</italic></sub>,
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M5"><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="0.4em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cebp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">post</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">stimulus</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cebp</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cebp</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>6</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">post</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">stimulus</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">cebp</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basal</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
Here CREB and C/EBP&#x003b2; activate transcription as dimers (homodimers or heterodimers) (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C49" ref-type="bibr">Wu et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C35" ref-type="bibr">Parkin et al. 2002</xref>). Therefore, for simplicity, Hill functions with coefficients of 2 were used to describe the effect of pCREB on <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; expression and the effect of C/EBP&#x003b2; on <italic>bdnf</italic> expression. In Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M4">4</xref>, <italic>CEBP</italic><sub>max</sub> denotes the maximum amount of C/EBP&#x003b2; that can be produced within 48 h, and was used to keep the simulation results within a biologically reasonable concentration boundary.</p><p>The transcription of <italic>bdnf</italic> is regulated by two activators, pCREB and C/EBP&#x003b2;, and three repressors, Sin3a, MeCP2, and HDAC2 (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). The mechanisms underlying the changes in binding of Sin3a, MeCP2, and HDAC2 to the <italic>bdnf</italic> exon <italic>IV</italic> promoter are unclear. The dynamics of Sin3a, MeCP2, and HDAC2 protein levels after training are also not well characterized. Therefore, differential equations were not developed to simulate dynamics of binding of these repressors. Instead, a step function is used to approximate the termination of <italic>bdnf</italic> transcription (Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M7">7</xref>). The activation of <italic>bdnf</italic> transcription by C/EBP&#x003b2; is reflected by <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>act_bdnf</italic></sub> in Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M7">7</xref>. The increase in C/EBP activity increases <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>act_bdnf</italic></sub> and thus induces the expression of <italic>bdnf</italic> until 18 h post-stimulus, at which time it is assumed that a complex involving the above repressors begins to interfere with the binding of C/EBP&#x003b2; to <italic>bdnf</italic> so that <italic>bdnf</italic> returns to its basal level &#x0223c;48 h after training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>), terminating the feedback loop. Thus, 18 h after stimulus <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>act_bdnf</italic></sub> decreases to a constant basal synthesis rate <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>f_bdnf_basal</italic></sub> to reflect this repression. The resulting differential equation describing the synthesis and degradation of <italic>bdnf</italic> mRNA is
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M6"><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">minb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">degb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">db</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula>
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M7"><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="0.4em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>18</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">post</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">stimulus</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>18</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">h</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">post</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">stimulus</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mspace width="0.4em"/><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basal</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
The feedback loop is terminated by 48 h after IA training. BDNF, C/EBP&#x003b2;, and pCREB all return to basal levels. However, IA memory persists for at least 9 d (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). This finding indicates that one or more downstream pathways induced by the BDNF-positive feedback loop are self-sustaining for at least 9 d, remaining activated even after the BDNF loop is turned off at &#x0223c;48 h post-IA training. Injection of a protein synthesis inhibitor or anti-BDNF antibody 24 h after IA training does not impair memory at day 3, but impairs memory at day 8 (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). If one pathway was responsible for memory both at days 3 and 8, it would be difficult to explain why protein synthesis inhibition at 24 h, lasting &#x0223c;6 h, fails to impair this pathway, and memory, at day 3, but does impair memory at day 8. Hence, it is more likely that at least two independent downstream pathways are self-sustaining for some time, enhancing transcription or translation required to sustain synaptic potentiation for 9 d or longer. The model assumes that one such downstream pathway is activated by both pCREB and C/EBP&#x003b2; immediately after IA training and that the activity of this pathway persists for &#x0223c;2 d (Downstream Pathway 1 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F1">Fig. 1</xref>A; the activity of this pathway is denoted by <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>pCREB*CEBP</italic></sub> in Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M8">8</xref>). Another such pathway is activated by C/EBP&#x003b2; alone (Downstream Pathway 2 in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F1">Fig. 1</xref>A; the activity of this pathway is denoted by <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>CEBP</italic></sub> in Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M9">9</xref>). Because of the delayed activation of C/EBP&#x003b2; expression, the second pathway is slowly activated hours after IA training. The activity of this pathway lasts for at least 9 d. Thus these pathways prolong the effects of the BDNF feedback loop, so that the length of time for which the synaptic weight stays elevated and IA memory persists is up to at least 9 d, in agreement with empirical data (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). The differential equation describing the activation of the first downstream pathway by pCREB and C/EBP&#x003b2; is
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M8"><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="0.4em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCREB</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">aPcreb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCREB</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basal</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">down</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CREB</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mspace width="2em"/><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basal</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">down</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>pCRE</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCRE</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCRE</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">B</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ANI</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo fence="false">{</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basalpath</mml:mi><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ANI</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dPcreb</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCRE</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi>B</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo fence="false">}</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
and that describing the activation of the second pathway by C/EBP&#x003b2; is
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M9"><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mtable columnalign="right left" rowspacing=".5em" columnspacing="0.4em"><mml:mtr><mml:mtd><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:mtd><mml:mtd><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">aCEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basal</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">down</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ANI</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr><mml:mtr><mml:mtd/><mml:mtd><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">basalpath</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ANI</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dcebp</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mtd></mml:mtr></mml:mtable></mml:math></disp-formula>
Both pathways contribute to the elevation of synaptic weight, denoted as <italic>W</italic>. The differential equation describing the dynamics of <italic>W</italic> is therefore
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M10"><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dt</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">aw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">pCREB</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">ANI</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">dw</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mstyle></mml:math></disp-formula>
To selectively couple the increased gene expression driven by the BDNF-positive feedback loop to increases in the weight of specific synapses that were activated during IA training, as opposed to a general up-scaling of all synaptic weights, it is also necessary to postulate a process similar to synaptic tagging, which data suggest allowing only recently activated synapses to capture plasticity-related proteins synthesized in response to increased activity (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C38" ref-type="bibr">Redondo and Morris 2011</xref>). Because the present study is interested in modeling transcriptional regulation and associated processes, the dynamics of synaptic tagging are not included in the model.</p><p>For this model, the topology of the BDNF feedback loop as diagrammed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F1">Figure 1</xref>A is based on substantial empirical data (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). However, extant empirical data do not suffice to provide strong constraints on model parameter values. In accordance with data, the model is constrained only to qualitatively simulate the characteristic dynamics of BDNF, <italic>bdnf</italic>, pCREB, and C/EBP&#x003b2; after IA training, as well as the effects of protein synthesis inhibitors and oligodeoxynucleotides (ODNs) on IA memory.</p><p>The dynamic elements to be simulated include the following:
<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>BDNF increases due to release immediately after training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C41" ref-type="bibr">Slipczuk et al. 2009</xref>), but BDNF returns to basal level within 1 h (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C14" ref-type="bibr">Finsterwald et al. 2015</xref>). BDNF increases again &#x0223c;20 h after training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p>pCREB increases immediately after training and remains elevated for at least 20 h (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p></list-item><list-item><p><italic>bdnf</italic> and C/EBP&#x003b2; do not increase until 6 h after training, and then remain elevated for at least 20 h, returning to basal levels &#x0223c;48 h after training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p></list-item></list>LTM is assumed to be formed (consolidated) if <italic>W</italic> remains at least 100% higher than its unstimulated (basal) value for more than 2 d. LTM is further considered to be persistent if <italic>W</italic> remains at least 100% higher than its unstimulated value for more than 7 d.</p><p>Parameter sensitivity analysis was performed to test the robustness of the model to parameter variations (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1101/lm.042044.116/-/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). Each individual parameter was varied within the range of &#x000b1;90% of its standard value. For each parameter, 60 evenly spaced values were simulated. Forty-eight hours of time courses of BDNF, <italic>bdnf</italic>, pCREB, and C/EBP&#x003b2; after IA training were simulated to investigate how parameter variations affect the qualitative match between simulation and empirical data (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1101/lm.042044.116/-/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>). Synaptic weight <italic>W</italic> was also simulated, for 9 d post-training, to quantify sensitivity.</p><p>Fourth-order Runge-Kutta integration was used for integration of differential equations, with a time step of 3 sec. The model was programmed in XPP-Auto version 6.1 (<uri xlink:href="www.math.pitt.edu/~bard/xpp/xpp.html">www.math.pitt.edu/~bard/xpp/xpp.html</uri>). The XPP-Auto code will be provided as requested. The model will also be submitted to the ModelDB database (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C28" ref-type="bibr">McDougal et al. 2015</xref>).</p><p>In <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. (2014)</xref>, <italic>bdnf</italic> exon IV mRNA was measured at 40 min and at 6, 12, 20, and 48 h after IA training with quantitative real-time PCR. A delayed increase occurred 12 and 20 h after training, with a return to basal level at 48 h. C/EBP&#x003b2; protein was significantly increased at 12 h after IA training, BDNF was significantly increased at 20 h, and pCREB remained elevated for 20 h after IA training, returning to basal level at 48 h. BDNF appears to be rapidly released during IA training or neuronal activity (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C23" ref-type="bibr">Kojima et al. 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C41" ref-type="bibr">Slipczuk et al. 2009</xref>). Therefore, to simulate IA training, an immediate brief increase (for 1 min) in the parameter <italic>stim</italic> generated an initial large, rapid rise in [BDNF]. Simulated time courses of <italic>bdnf</italic> mRNA, BDNF, pCREB, and C/EBP&#x003b2; qualitatively agreed with the empirical observations discussed above (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F1">Fig. 1</xref>B&#x02013;E), although only a single empirical data point is available for BDNF.</p><p>Dynamics of BDNF, pCREB, and C/EBP&#x003b2; are illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F1">Figure 1</xref>B&#x02013;E. The initial increase in BDNF is due to BDNF release induced by stimulus, and results in rapid CREB phosphorylation. A delayed increase in C/EBP&#x003b2; expression is induced by this first phase of CREB phosphorylation. This increase in C/EBP&#x003b2; leads, in turn, to a surge of <italic>bdnf</italic> mRNA. By 12 h after stimulus, this increase in <italic>bdnf</italic> mRNA results in increased levels of BDNF, a second phase of increased phosphorylation of CREB, and thus a second phase of increased synthesis of C/EBP&#x003b2;.</p><p>Three examples of parameter sensitivity analyses are illustrated in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1101/lm.042044.116/-/DC1">Supplemental Figure S2</ext-link>. These three examples were selected to illustrate the range of responses (from highly sensitive, column A of <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1101/lm.042044.116/-/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2</ext-link>, to insensitive, column C). For column A, when compared with the control simulation with standard values of parameters (black curves), altering <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>a_bdnf</italic></sub> by a moderate degree (18%) could substantially change the time courses of pCREB and C/EBP&#x003b2; post-stimulus. For column B, similar alterations of <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>minb</italic></sub> had modest effects, and for column C, altering <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>basalp_creb</italic></sub> did not have significant effects. More generally, these sensitivity analyses suggested that parameters directly related to the interactions among <italic>bdnf</italic> mRNA, BDNF, pCREB, and C/EBP&#x003b2; (e.g., <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>a_bdnf</italic></sub> in <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1101/lm.042044.116/-/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S2A</ext-link>, <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>trans</italic></sub>, <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>p_BDNF</italic></sub>) have the greatest impact on the dynamics of feedback loops after stimuli and that moderate variations in these parameters could significantly enhance the response of <italic>W</italic> to stimulus. Thus, this class of parameters might suggest pharmaceutical targets for enhancing memory. The model proved to be relatively insensitive to changes in the remaining parameters, indicating that the qualitative match between simulation and empirical data was generally robust to moderate parameter variations.</p><p>With standard parameter values, the increase in synaptic weight (variable <italic>W</italic>, Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M10">10</xref>) from days 2 to 9 after IA training was &#x0003e;200% above the basal value of <italic>W</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>A). The inhibition of this increase by several treatments shown by <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. (2014)</xref> to impair IA memory was simulated (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>B). For these simulations, from the day 2 to 9 time points, if <italic>W</italic> was increased by &#x0003c;100% relative to its basal level, either the formation of memory (from 2 to 4 d) or its persistence (from 7 to 9 d) was considered to be impaired (that is, impairment corresponds to an approximately twofold decrement in the normal increase of <italic>W</italic>). The corresponding empirical measure of memory impairment is a significant decrease in the average time taken to enter a compartment 2&#x02013;9 d after a shock has been applied (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p><fig id="ZHANGLM042044F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Simulations of the temporal profile of the protein synthesis, BDNF, and <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; expression. (<italic>A</italic>) Simulated time courses of synaptic weight <italic>W</italic> and of the activities of downstream pathways 1 and 2. LTM is considered to be persistent if <italic>W</italic> remains at least twofold higher than its basal value (dashed line) for 7 d. Increases in <italic>W</italic> were impaired by anisomycin (PSI) (<italic>B1</italic>), anti-BDNF antibody (<italic>B2</italic>), and ODN (<italic>B3</italic>). (<italic>C</italic>) Simulation of effects on <italic>W</italic> as a result of blocking the synthesis of various components in the model at 15 min (blue curves) or 24 h (red curves) after stimulus. (<italic>C1</italic>) Blocking synthesis of all proteins. (<italic>C2</italic>) Blocking the synthesis of only BDNF. (<italic>C3</italic>) Blocking only the synthesis of C/EBP&#x003b2;. (<italic>C4</italic>) Blocking only the synthesis of <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>pCREB*CEBP</italic></sub>. (<italic>C5</italic>) Blocking only the synthesis of <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>cebp</italic></sub>. (<italic>C6</italic>) Blocking only the synthesis of <italic>W</italic> itself.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZhangLM042044f02"/></fig><p>Injection of anisomycin in the rat dorsal hippocampus blocks &#x0003e;80% of protein synthesis for &#x0223c;6 h (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C29" ref-type="bibr">Milekic et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). To simulate this effect (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>B1), the synthesis rates of BDNF and C/EBP&#x003b2; were reduced by 80% for 6 h. Protein synthesis inhibition was initiated at different times after the initial stimulus. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Figure 2</xref>B1 illustrates that if inhibition was simulated at 15 min prior to stimulus (shown by red arrow and circles), or immediately after (green arrow and diamonds), and lasting for &#x0223c;6 h, <italic>W</italic> was increased by &#x0003c;100% relative to its basal level at days 2 and 7. This simulation shows impairment of both memory formation (2 d) and memory persistence (7 d). However, if inhibition was simulated at 24 h after stimulus in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Figure 2</xref>B1 (purple arrow and triangles), <italic>W</italic> increased by more than 100% relative to its basal level at day 3, but failed to do so at day 8. This simulation shows impairment of only memory persistence, at 8 d. If inhibition occurred 48 h after stimulus (blue arrow and squares), <italic>W</italic> was increased by more than 100% relative to its basal level at days 4 and 9, which indicates that memory formation and persistence were intact. These results are qualitatively consistent with data (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>In the model, BDNF initiates the positive feedback loop by phosphorylating CREB. No empirical data delineate the strength and duration of the reduction in CREB phosphorylation due to an anti-BDNF antibody. Hence, the effect of anti-BDNF antibody was assumed to have similar strength and duration as protein synthesis inhibition. The phosphorylation rate of CREB was reduced by 80% for 6 h. If the simulated effect of anti-BDNF antibody began 15 min prior to the IA stimulus (red arrow and circles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>B2), <italic>W</italic> was increased by &#x0003c;100% relative to its basal level at days 2 and 7, consistent with impaired memory formation. However, if anti-BDNF antibody was added immediately after (within in 15 min) (green arrow and diamonds in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>B2) or 24 h after stimulation (purple arrow and triangles), <italic>W</italic> was increased by more than 100% relative to its basal level from 2 to 9 d. These treatments failed to impair memory formation and persistence. Similarly, memory at days 4 and 9 was unimpaired if anti-BDNF antibody was added 48 h after stimulation (blue arrow and squares). Most of these simulation results are consistent with empirical findings, except that, empirically, anti-BDNF antibody injected immediately after or 24 h after training does impair IA memory at days 8 and 9 in <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. (2014)</xref>. This discrepancy may be due to an incomplete description in the model of the actions of BDNF. In the model, anti-BDNF antibody reduces <italic>W</italic> by blocking the phosphorylation of CREB only. Empirically, BDNF is likely to affect a number of additional biochemical targets, such as substrates of ERK MAPK or of mTOR, that are important for IA memory.</p><p>Injection of <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; antisense ODN in rat hippocampus 24 h after training impairs memory 2 d post-training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>). In contrast, anisomycin injected 24 h after training fails to impair memory at day 3. This discrepancy indicates that at 24 h post-training, anti-<italic>c/ebp</italic> ODN may more efficiently reduce the expression of C/EBP&#x003b2; than does anisomycin at the given dose. With the model, if the simulated expression rate of C/EBP&#x003b2; was reduced by 95% for 24 h, starting either 5 h (red arrow and circles in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>B3) or 24 h (purple arrow and diamonds) after stimulus, <italic>W</italic> was increased by &#x0003c;100% relative to its basal level at days 2 and 7, thus memory was considered impaired. Similarly, to simulate the effect of anti-<italic>bdnf</italic> ODN, the expression rate of BDNF was reduced by 95% for 24 h. In a separate simulation, if anti-<italic>bdnf</italic> ODN was added 6 h after stimulus (green arrow and squares in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>B3), <italic>W</italic> was also increased by &#x0003c;100% relative to its basal level at days 2 and 7. These results are consistent with empirical findings of memory impairment (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). Hence, the model can simulate a variety of effects of protein synthesis inhibition and ODN injection on memory formation and persistence.</p><p>In the above simulations, protein synthesis inhibition was implemented by reducing the synthesis of BDNF, C/EBP&#x003b2; <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>pCREB*CEBP</italic></sub>, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>CEBP</italic></sub>, and <italic>W</italic> by 80% for 6 h (i.e., increasing <italic>ANI</italic> in Equations <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M1">1</xref>, 4, and 8&#x02013;10 to 0.8 for 6 h). To investigate the individual contribution of each of these components to the stimulus-induced increase in <italic>W</italic>, simulations were repeated but with inhibition restricted to individual components (i.e., by selectively increasing <italic>ANI</italic> in the corresponding differential equation). Simulation of protein synthesis inhibition beginning 15 min after stimulation primarily reduced <italic>W</italic> through its effects on BDNF and C/EBP&#x003b2; (blue curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>C2, C3). Selective inhibition of <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>pCREB*CEBP</italic></sub>, <italic>P</italic><sub><italic>CEBP</italic></sub> or <italic>W</italic> had only small effects (blue curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>C4&#x02013;C6), most likely due to the relatively long half-lives of these components. For inhibition of protein synthesis beginning 24 h after stimulation, reduction of <italic>W</italic> was still predominately due to BDNF and C/EBP&#x003b2; (red curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>C1&#x02013;C6). Note that an accelerated decrease in <italic>W</italic> was observed, lasting for &#x0223c;6 h, in each case with protein synthesis inhibition of <italic>W</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F2">Fig. 2</xref>C1, C6). This effect occurs because <italic>W</italic> itself depends directly on protein synthesis (Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M10">10</xref>).</p><p>To further develop a temporal profile of sensitivity of memory to protein synthesis inhibition or ODN injection as a function of the time at which application initiates, the simulations were repeated with the time that inhibition began varying from 0 to 50 h post-stimulus. The degree to which <italic>W</italic> at day 2 or day 7 after stimulus is reduced by treatments was used to represent the degree of sensitivity of memory to protein synthesis inhibition. Specifically, the threshold value of synaptic weight required to maintain memory at either day 2 or day 7 was denoted by <italic>W</italic><sub>reference</sub>. As above, this threshold was taken to be fixed at a 100% increase of <italic>W</italic> above its basal value. Impairment at either day 2 or day 7 corresponds to a decrement in <italic>W</italic> below <italic>W</italic><sub>reference</sub>. For this model, then, the sensitivity of memory to protein synthesis inhibition or ODN treatment increases with this impairment. Thus the following equation was used to calculate sensitivity at either day 2 or day 7 post-stimulus:
<disp-formula id="ZHANGLM042044M11"><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">sensitivity</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>100</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02217;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">reference</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>W</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">reference</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
For either day, plots of the variation of this sensitivity versus the time at which protein synthesis inhibition or ODN treatment began were generated. Both impairment and sensitivity were considered to be zero if the right-hand side of Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M11">11</xref> was negative. The resulting plot of sensitivity to protein synthesis inhibition versus the time at which inhibition began is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Figure 3</xref>A3. The sensitivity of memory formation (at 2 d, blue curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A3), or persistence (at 7 d, red curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A3) to inhibition displayed a non-monotonic change with the time at which inhibition began. The peaks of sensitivity curves occurred when inhibition initiated at 6 h after stimulus, at the time that C/EBP&#x003b2; expression was induced and positive feedback was initiated.</p><fig id="ZHANGLM042044F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>The relationship of the sensitivities of memory formation (2 d) and persistence (7 d) to protein synthesis inhibition (PSI) (<italic>A</italic>) or anti-c/ebp oligodeoxynucleotide (ODN) (<italic>B</italic>) versus the time at which inhibition or ODN application began. With increasing delay in the initiation of C/EBP&#x003b2; expression, from 0 to 9 h (<italic>A1&#x02013;A4</italic>), the difference between the sensitivity of memory formation (blue curves) and memory persistence (red curves) to inhibition progressively increases. Similarly, with increasing delay in the initiation of C/EBP&#x003b2; expression, the difference between the sensitivity of memory formation (blue curves) and memory persistence (red curves) to anti-<italic>c/ebp</italic> ODN progressively increases (<italic>B1</italic>&#x02013;<italic>B4</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ZhangLM042044f03"/></fig><p>To investigate the effect on sensitivity of varying the 6 h delay between stimulus-induced pCREB elevation and C/EBP&#x003b2; expression, these simulations were repeated, with the delay (Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M5">5</xref>) varying from 0 to 9 h. When no delay was present (i.e., C/EBP&#x003b2; expression increased immediately after stimulus), the sensitivity of memory formation at day 2 (blue curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A1), or of persistence at day 7 (red curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A1) to protein synthesis inhibition displayed a monotonic dependence on the time at which inhibition began. Sensitivity dropped to zero within 1 h after stimulus. When a 3 h delay was present, the sensitivity of memory formation (blue curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A2), or persistence (red curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A2) to protein synthesis inhibition displayed a nonmonotonic dependence on the time of inhibition. The sensitivity of memory at day 2 dropped to zero within 10 h after stimulus, whereas it took longer for the sensitivity of memory persistence to drop to zero. With increasing delay in the initiation of C/EBP&#x003b2; expression and the feedback loop, the sensitivity to protein synthesis inhibition also increased, and displayed a strong nonmonotonic dependence on the time of initiation of inhibition. The difference in the time required for the sensitivity of memory at day 2, versus that at day 7, to drop to zero also increased (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A2&#x02013;A4). When a 9 h delay was present, the sensitivity of memory at day 2 (blue curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A4), and at day 7 (red curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A4) to protein synthesis inhibition remained elevated for as long as 48 h after stimulation. This prolonged elevation in sensitivity with the 9 h delay is due to a slower stimulus-induced increase in <italic>W</italic> with this long delay. For this case, <italic>W</italic> could be reduced to below <italic>W</italic><sub>reference</sub> by protein synthesis inhibition initiated as late as 48 h post-stimulus.</p><p>When a 6 h or less delay in the initiation of the feedback was present, all the sensitivities dropped to zero by 48 h (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A). These results indicated that time windows of sensitivity were dependent on the initiation and termination of the BDNF feedback loop, which is consistent with the previous results that BDNF and C/EBP&#x003b2; were the main contributors to the effects of protein synthesis inhibition. Note in the case for the 9 h delay in the initiation of the feedback, the sensitivity of memory at day 2 (48 h) had a delayed peak if inhibition of protein synthesis was initiated around 42 h after stimulus (blue curve in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A4). This peak occurs because the variable <italic>W</italic> itself depends directly on protein synthesis (Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M10">10</xref>).</p><p>The corresponding plots of sensitivity to anti-<italic>c/ebp</italic> ODN versus the time at which ODN treatment began are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Figure 3</xref>B1&#x02013;4. Similar to the effects of protein synthesis inhibition, the sensitivity to anti-<italic>c/ebp</italic> ODN increased, at both days 2 and 7 when the delay in the initiation of C/EBP&#x003b2; expression and positive feedback was increased. However, unlike the sensitivity to protein synthesis inhibition, the sensitivity of memory at day 2 (blue curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>B1&#x02013;4) or at day 7 (red curves in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>B1&#x02013;4) to anti-<italic>c/ebp</italic> ODN never appeared to display a nonmonotonic dependence on the time of ODN application. This lack of nonmonotonic dependence may be due to the long duration of the ODN effect (24 h), such that even a prolonged delay (9 h) in the initiation of the feedback will not affect the efficacy of ODN in suppressing the expression of <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2;; whereas for the case of protein synthesis inhibition that lasts &#x0223c;6 h, the model might be insensitive to inhibition if the inhibition occurs before the BDNF feedback loop is initiated.</p><p>In the current study, we found that for successful simulation of the empirical observations, it was necessary to assume that at least two independent self-sustaining signaling pathways, downstream from pCREB and C/EBP&#x003b2;, play substantial roles in LTM formation and persistence. These two independent pathways might occur in different synaptic sites of the same neurons, or different neurons in the circuit responsible for memory formation and persistence. This assumption needs to be validated empirically.</p><p>Empirical studies support the existence of time windows of sensitivity of consolidation to protein synthesis inhibition, or to inhibition of kinases or of BDNF signaling, during &#x0223c;24 h post-training, for some common learning protocols, although the parameters of these windows vary between studies (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C15" ref-type="bibr">Grecksch and Matthies 1980</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C9" ref-type="bibr">Bourtchouladze et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C46" ref-type="bibr">Tiunova et al. 1998</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C18" ref-type="bibr">Igaz et al. 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C5" ref-type="bibr">Bekinschtein et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C41" ref-type="bibr">Slipczuk et al. 2009</xref>). Here, it is hypothesized that the observed delay of &#x0223c;6 h between IA training and C/EBP&#x003b2; induction (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>) may help to shape these time windows. This delay leads to a nonmonotonic dependence of sensitivity to protein synthesis inhibition on the time of inhibitor application and implies that memory formation may be less sensitive to inhibition begun at early times before up-regulation of C/EBP&#x003b2; synthesis occurs. Indeed, in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Figure 3</xref>A3, with a 6 h delay, there is a peak, or time window, of sensitivity of both 2 and 7 d memory to protein synthesis inhibition, centered around 6 h post-stimulus (the 2 d window is narrower). Although not clearly evident in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Figure 3</xref>, inhibition that started immediately before training and lasting &#x0223c;6 h blocks memory formation in simulations, as it does empirically (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>The simulation results illustrate that the windows of sensitivity of memory formation and persistence to protein synthesis inhibition, as well as to ODN application, move to earlier times rapidly as the delay in initiation decreases (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Therefore, if in a given system memory consolidation depends on a positive feedback loop with a little delay of activation, then there may be a significant early window of decreased sensitivity to protein synthesis inhibition or to ODN administration (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ZHANGLM042044F3">Fig. 3</xref>A1, B1). An advance in initiation of a positive feedback loop, and therefore of maximal sensitivity to inhibition, might result from a stronger stimulus intensity.</p><p>The transcription of <italic>bdnf</italic> is regulated by three repressors, Sin3a, MeCP2, and HDAC2 (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). In the model, a delay of 6 h was used in the onset of pCREB's regulation of the expression of <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; to take into account the observation that <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; mRNA remained at basal level for at least 6 h after IA training despite pCREB itself being significantly increased 30 min after training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C44" ref-type="bibr">Taubenfeld et al. 2001a</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). What might be the biochemical mechanism underlying this &#x0223c;6 h delay? Considering that increased binding of repressors to the promoter of <italic>bdnf</italic> at 48 h may act as a brake to terminate the BDNF feedback loop (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>), it is hypothesized that increased binding of Sin3a, or other repressors, to the <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; promoter during the first few hours after training acts as another brake to delay the initiation of the positive feedback loop. The time required to reduce binding of these repressors and allow <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2; induction could generate the observed delay of &#x0223c;6 h between IA training and C/EBP&#x003b2; increase. However, no empirical studies have yet been performed to investigate this hypothesis. Further empirical studies are needed to examine protein levels of MeCP2, HDAC2, and Sin3a and changes in binding to the <italic>bdnf</italic> promoter during IA, and the extent to which any changes are dependent on BDNF, CREB, or neuronal activity.</p><p>The simulated time courses of BDNF mRNA and protein, pCREB, and C/EBP&#x003b2; are qualitatively similar to empirical time courses following IA training. However, the empirical data are sparse and additional data will be necessary before it is possible to make more thorough quantitative comparisons between data and the model. Data also indicate that activity of the NMDA receptor and of CaM kinase II are necessary for <italic>bdnf</italic> induction (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C48" ref-type="bibr">Vaynman et al. 2003</xref>) and that, reciprocally, elevated BDNF leads to induction of CaM kinase II expression (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C11" ref-type="bibr">Chen et al. 2012</xref>). However, data have not determined whether they are actual components of the BDNF-positive feedback loop or, instead, permissive factors required for operation of the loop.</p><p>In this model, the effect of protein synthesis inhibition lasts &#x0223c;6 h. However, inhibition in vivo might last longer, depending upon dosage, brain region, or other parameters. It will be important to extend the model to simulate the effects of varying protein synthesis inhibition duration on memory formation and persistence.</p><p>Rapamycin added prior to, but not immediately after, IA training blocks memory at 2 and 7 d post-training (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). Hence rapamycin-sensitive protein synthesis appears to be necessary for the early phase of memory induction via a C/EBP&#x003b2;-independent pathway, which is not simulated in the current model. In addition, the model is simplified by focusing on the C/EBP&#x003b2; expression induced by BDNF up to 48 h after training. Additional biochemical cascades activated by BDNF and contributing to memory consolidation are reviewed in <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C34" ref-type="bibr">Panja and Bramham (2014)</xref>. In view of these additional cascades, as well as other processes (e.g., dendritic spine remodeling, <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C8" ref-type="bibr">Bosch et al. 2014</xref>), it seems unlikely the operation of the BDNF feedback loop modeled here is itself sufficient for consolidation of IA memory or induction of genes such as <italic>c/ebp</italic>&#x003b2;. Experiments, however, do suggest that the feedback loop is necessary (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>Models have suggested that positive feedback loops might sustain bistable switches important for memory persistence and consolidation (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C7" ref-type="bibr">Bhalla and Iyengar 1999</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C30" ref-type="bibr">Miller et al. 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C36" ref-type="bibr">Pettigrew et al. 2005</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C40" ref-type="bibr">Shema et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C25" ref-type="bibr">Liu et al. 2008</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C32" ref-type="bibr">Ogasawara and Kawato 2009</xref>, <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C33" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C50" ref-type="bibr">Zhang et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C2" ref-type="bibr">Aslam and Shouval 2012</xref>; <xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C42" ref-type="bibr">Smolen et al. 2012</xref>). In the model presented here, three positive feedback loops were implemented, two of which are hypothetical signaling pathways downstream from pCREB and C/EBP. The role of these hypothetical pathways is limited. They contribute to LTM formation and persistence only by prolonging the effects of the BDNF feedback loop on synaptic weight. For standard parameter values, these two pathways were not bistable because their activities eventually returned to basal levels &#x0223c;7 d after training. If parameters were adjusted to generate bistability in these pathways, then <italic>W</italic> would have lower and upper stable steady states, and the temporary application of inhibitors would only have two lasting outcomes: able to or not able to reduce <italic>W</italic> from an upper (strong) steady state to a lower steady state. The third positive feedback loop is the BDNF feedback loop. Empirical data suggest that the repressors Sin3a, MeCP2, and HDAC2 are involved in terminating operation of this feedback loop (<xref rid="ZHANGLM042044C4" ref-type="bibr">Bambah-Mukku et al. 2014</xref>). To identify the role of this repression in the model, the response to a stimulus was simulated with <italic>F</italic><sub><italic>act_bdnf</italic></sub> in Equation <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="ZHANGLM042044M7">7</xref> dependent on C/EBP throughout the simulation:
<disp-formula><mml:math id="UM1"><mml:msub><mml:mi>F</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">act</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>K</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo>_</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">bdnf</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">CEBP</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac></mml:mrow></mml:mstyle></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></disp-formula>
The simulation results indicated that, in the absence of repressors, the BDNF-positive feedback loop does, with standard parameter values, sustain a bistable switch. One minute of stimulation with an amplitude no lower than 20 &#x000b5;M/sec switched pCREB1 and C/EBP from basal levels to an upper steady state (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1101/lm.042044.116/-/DC1">Supplemental Fig. S1</ext-link>). An amplitude of 20 &#x000b5;M/sec, near the switch threshold, generated slow switching dynamics, yielding a state transition after &#x0223c;8 d, with C/EBP transiting to the upper state (orange time course). These results suggest an additional mechanistic possibility for generating bistability in biochemical cascades that sustain memory, which may be terminated by transcription or translation repressors.</p>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
<title>Supplementary Material</title>
<supplementary-material id="PMC_1" content-type="local-data">
<caption>
<title>Supplemental Material</title>
</caption>
<media mimetype="text" mime-subtype="html" xlink:href="supp_23_12_714__index.html"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="ps"
xlink:href="supp_23.12.714_Supplemental_Figure1.eps"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_23.12.714_Supplemental_Table1.docx"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="ps"
xlink:href="supp_23.12.714_Supplemental_Figure2.eps"/>
<media xlink:role="associated-file" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword"
xlink:href="supp_23.12.714_Supplemental_Legends.docx"/>
</supplementary-material>
</sec>
</body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>This study was supported by NIH grants MH065635 (to C.M.A.) and NS073974 (to J.H.B.).</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><p>[Supplemental material is available for this article.]</p></fn><fn><p>Article is online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.learnmem.org/cgi/doi/10.1101/lm.042044.116">http://www.learnmem.org/cgi/doi/10.1101/lm.042044.116</ext-link>.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fong</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dwyer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Davare</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reese</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obrietan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Impey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <year>2004</year>
<article-title>Mitogen- and stress-activated protein kinase 1 mediates cAMP response element-binding protein phosphorylation and activation by neurotrophins</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>4324</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4332</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aslam</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shouval</surname><given-names>HZ</given-names></name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Regulation of cytoplasmic polyadenylation can generate a bistable switch</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>12</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22335938</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Baldi</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bucherelli</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>Brain sites involved in fear memory reconsolidation and extinction of rodents</article-title>. <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>
<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>160</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>190</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25887284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bambah-Mukku</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Travaglia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pollonini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberini</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>A positive autoregulatory BDNF feedback loop via C/EBP&#x003b2; mediates hippocampal memory consolidation</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>12547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12559</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25209292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bekinschtein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cammarota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Igaz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bevilaqua</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <year>2007</year>
<article-title>Persistence of long-term memory storage requires a late protein synthesis- and BDNF-dependent phase in the hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>53</volume>: <fpage>261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>277</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17224407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bekinschtein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slipczuk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dorman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cammarota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Persistence of long-term memory storage: new insights into its molecular signatures in the hippocampus and related structures</article-title>. <source>Neurotox Res</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>385</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20151243</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Iyengar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <year>1999</year>
<article-title>Emergent properties of networks of biological signaling pathways</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>283</volume>: <fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>387</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9888852</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castro</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saneyoshi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsuno</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sur</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayashi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Structural and molecular remodeling of dendritic spine substructures during long-term potentiation</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>82</volume>: <fpage>444</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24742465</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bourtchouladze</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abel</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lapidus</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kandel</surname><given-names>ER</given-names></name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>Different training procedures recruit either one or two critical periods for contextual memory consolidation, each of which requires protein synthesis and PKA</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>365</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>374</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10454361</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>West</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Griffith</surname><given-names>EC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jaenisch</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <year>2003</year>
<article-title>Derepression of BDNF transcription involves calcium-dependent phosphorylation of MeCP2</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>302</volume>: <fpage>885</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>889</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14593183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>DY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bambah-Mukku</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pollonini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberini</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Glucocorticoid receptors recruit the CaMKII&#x003b1;-BDNF-CREB pathways to mediate memory consolidation</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1707</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1714</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23160045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mattson</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>. <year>2003</year>
<article-title>Nitric oxide acts in a positive feedback loop with BDNF to regulate neural progenitor cell proliferation and differentiation in the mammalian brain</article-title>. <source>Dev Biol</source>
<volume>258</volume>: <fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>333</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12798291</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>De Cesare</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacquot</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanauer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>Rsk-2 activity is necessary for epidermal growth factor-induced phosphorylation of CREB protein and transcription of <italic>c-fos</italic> gene</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci</source>
<volume>95</volume>: <fpage>12202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>12207</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9770464</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Finsterwald</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steinmetz</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Travaglia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberini</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>From memory impairment to posttraumatic stress disorder-like phenotypes: the critical role of an unpredictable second traumatic experience</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>15903</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15915</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26631471</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grecksch</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matthies</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <year>1980</year>
<article-title>Two sensitive periods for the amnesic effect of anisomycin</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>665</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7393961</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guan</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haggarty</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giacometti</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dannenberg</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Joseph</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nieland</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mazitschek</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>HDAC2 negatively regulates memory formation and synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>459</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19424149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <year>2004</year>
<article-title>Activation of the phosphoinositide-3-kinase &#x02013; Akt &#x02013; mammalian target of rapamycin signaling pathway is required for metabotropic glutamate receptor-dependent long-term depression</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>6352</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6361</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Igaz</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vianna</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Two time periods of hippocampal mRNA synthesis are required for memory consolidation of fear-motivated learning</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>6781</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6789</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12151558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Impey</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Obrietan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Donahue</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wade</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>Stimulation of cAMP response element (CRE)-mediated transcription during contextual learning</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
<volume>1</volume>: <fpage>595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>601</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10196567</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Furini</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Myskiw</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name>. <year>2016</year>
<article-title>Fear memory</article-title>. <source>Physiol Rev</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>695</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>750</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26983799</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>US</given-names></name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Signaling logic of activity-triggered dendritic protein synthesis: an mTOR gate but not a feedback switch</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000287</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19242559</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Khakpai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nasehi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zarrindast</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>. <year>2016</year>
<article-title>The role of NMDA receptors of the medial septum and dorsal hippocampus on memory acquisition</article-title>. <source>Pharmacol Biochem Behav</source>
<volume>143</volume>: <fpage>18</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>25</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26780596</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kojima</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Takei</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Numakawa</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ishikawa</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Matsumoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katoh-Semba</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hatanaka</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <year>2001</year>
<article-title>Biological characterization and optical imaging of brain derived neurotrophic factor-green fluorescent protein suggest an activity-dependent local release of brain-derived neurotrophic factor in neurites of cultured hippocampal neurons</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci Res</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>10</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11276045</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kornisiuk</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Snitcofsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blanco</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harvey</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jerusalinsky</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Memory impairment in rats by hippocampal administration of serine protease subtilisin</article-title>. <source>Behav Brain Res</source>
<volume>219</volume>: <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>67</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21185873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>RY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fioravante</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>cAMP response element-binding protein 1 feedback loop is necessary for consolidation of long-term synaptic facilitation in <italic>Aplysia</italic></article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>28</volume>: <fpage>1970</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1976</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18287513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maharana</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Feedback mechanism in depolarization-induced sustained activation of extracellular signal-regulated kinase in the hippocampus</article-title>. <source>Sci Rep</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>1103</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23346360</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Martinowich</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hattori</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fouse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>YE</given-names></name>. <year>2003</year>
<article-title>DNA methylation-related chromatin remodeling in activity-dependent BDNF gene regulation</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>302</volume>: <fpage>890</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>893</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14593184</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>McDougal</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morse</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hines</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>ModelView for ModelDB: online presentation of model structure</article-title>. <source>Neuroinformatics</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>459</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>470</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25896640</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Milekic</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Castellini</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberini</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <year>2006</year>
<article-title>Persistent disruption of an established morphine conditioned place preference</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>26</volume>: <fpage>3010</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3020</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16540579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhabotinsky</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lisman</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>XJ</given-names></name>. <year>2005</year>
<article-title>The stability of a stochastic CaMKII switch: dependence on the number of enzyme molecules and protein turnover</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>
<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>e107</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15819604</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Minichiello</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>TrkB signaling pathways in LTP and learning</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>850</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>860</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19927149</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Bistable switches for synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Sci Signal</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>pe7</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19193606</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogasawara</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawato</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>The protein kinase M&#x003b6; network as a bistable switch to store neuronal memory</article-title>. <source>BMC Syst Biol</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>181</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21194445</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Panja</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bramham</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>BDNF mechanisms in late LTP formation: synthesis and breakdown</article-title>. <source>Neuropharmacology</source>
<volume>76</volume>: <fpage>664</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>676</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23831365</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parkin</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baer</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Copeland</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>PF</given-names></name>. <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Regulation of CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein (C/EBP) activator proteins by heterodimerization with C/EBP (Ig/EBP)</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>277</volume>: <fpage>23563</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23572</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11980905</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pettigrew</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <year>2005</year>
<article-title>Dynamic properties of regulatory motifs associated with induction of three temporal domains of memory in <italic>Aplysia</italic></article-title>. <source>J Comput Neurosci</source>
<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>163</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>181</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15714268</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Radulovic</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tronson</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Molecular specificity of multiple hippocampal processes governing fear extinction</article-title>. <source>Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20458884</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Redondo</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Making memories last: the synaptic tagging and capture hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>30</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21170072</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Santini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huynh</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klann</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Mechanisms of translation control underlying long-lasting synaptic plasticity and the consolidation of long-term memory</article-title>. <source>Prog Mol Biol Transl Sci</source>
<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>131</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>167</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24484700</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shema</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sacktor</surname><given-names>TC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dudai</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>. <year>2007</year>
<article-title>Rapid erasure of long-term memory associations in the cortex by an inhibitor of PKM&#x003b6;</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>317</volume>: <fpage>951</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>953</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17702943</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Slipczuk</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bekinschtein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Katche</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cammarota</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Izquierdo</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Medina</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>BDNF activates mTOR to regulate GluR1 expression required for memory formation</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e6007</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19547753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Molecular constraints on synaptic tagging and maintenance of long-term potentiation: a predictive model</article-title>. <source>PLoS Comput Biol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002620</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22876169</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tao</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Finkbeiner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shaywitz</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Greenberg</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx regulates BDNF transcription by a CREB family transcription factor-dependent mechanism</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>
<volume>20</volume>: <fpage>709</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>726</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9581763</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taubenfeld</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Milekic</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberini</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <year>2001a</year>
<article-title>The consolidation of new but not reactivated memory requires hippocampal C/EBP&#x003b2;</article-title>. <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>813</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>818</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11477427</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Taubenfeld</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wiig</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dolan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pollonini</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alberini</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <year>2001b</year>
<article-title>Fornix-dependent induction of hippocampal CCAAT enhancer-binding protein &#x003b2; and &#x003b4; co-localizes with phosphorylated cAMP response element-binding protein and accompanies long-term memory consolidation</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11150323</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tiunova</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anokhin</surname><given-names>KV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>Two critical periods of protein and glycoprotein synthesis in memory consolidation for visual categorization learning in chicks</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>
<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>401</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>410</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10701879</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tuvikene</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pruunsild</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Orav</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Esvald</surname><given-names>EE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Timmusk</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>. <year>2016</year>
<article-title>AP-1 transcription factors mediate BDNF positive feedback loop in cortical neurons</article-title>. <source>J Neurosci</source>
<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>1290</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1305</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26818516</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vaynman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ying</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gomez-Pinilla</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <year>2003</year>
<article-title>Interplay between brain-derived neurotrophic factor and signal transduction modulators in the regulation of the effects of exercise on synaptic plasticity</article-title>. <source>Neuroscience</source>
<volume>122</volume>: <fpage>647</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>657</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14622908</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McMurray</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>cAMP response element-binding protein monomers cooperatively assemble to form dimers on DNA</article-title>. <source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>273</volume>: <fpage>20820</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20827</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9694827</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smolen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Baxter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>The sensitivity of memory consolidation and reconsolidation to inhibitors of protein synthesis and kinases: computational analysis</article-title>. <source>Learn Mem</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>428</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>439</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20736337</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ZHANGLM042044C51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Du</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jian</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Positive feedback loop of autocrine BDNF from microglia causes prolonged microglia activation</article-title>. <source>Cell Physiol Biochem</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>715</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>723</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25171395</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>