<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Gen Physiol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Gen. Physiol</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Journal of General Physiology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0022-1295</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-7748</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">10436003</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2230643</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">7962</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Allosteric Voltage Gating of Potassium Channels I</article-title><subtitle>Mslo Ionic Currents in the Absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup></subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Horrigan</surname><given-names>Frank T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>Jianmin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="b">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>Richard W.</given-names></name><address><addr-line>Department of Molecular and Cellular Physiology, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, CA 94305.</addr-line><fax>Fax: 650-725-4463;</fax></address><email>raldrich@leland.stanford.edu</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a">a</xref></contrib><aff id="a">
<label>a</label>From the Department of Molecular and Cellular Physiology, Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Stanford University School of Medicine, Stanford, California 94305</aff><aff id="b">
<label>b</label>Department of Biomedical Engineering, Case Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio 44106</aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>1</day><month>8</month><year>1999</year></pub-date><volume>114</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>277</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>3</month><year>1999</year></date><date date-type="rev-request"><day>1</day><month>6</month><year>1999</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>6</month><year>1999</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 1999 The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-statement><copyright-year>1999</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Rockefeller University Press</copyright-holder><license license-type="openaccess"><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike&#x02013;No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publication date (see <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rupress.org/terms">http://www.rupress.org/terms</ext-link>). After six months it is available under a Creative Commons License (Attribution&#x02013;Noncommercial&#x02013;Share Alike 4.0 Unported license, as described at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Activation of large conductance Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels is controlled by both cytoplasmic Ca<sup>2+</sup> and membrane potential. To study the mechanism of voltage-dependent gating, we examined mSlo Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> currents in excised macropatches from <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes in the virtual absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (&#x0003c;1 nM). In response to a voltage step, I<sub>K</sub> activates with an exponential time course, following a brief delay. The delay suggests that rapid transitions precede channel opening. The later exponential time course suggests that activation also involves a slower rate-limiting step. However, the time constant of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation [&#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)] exhibits a complex voltage dependence that is inconsistent with models that contain a single rate limiting step. &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) increases weakly with voltage from &#x02212;500 to &#x02212;20 mV, with an equivalent charge (<italic>z</italic>) of only 0.14 <italic>e</italic>, and displays a stronger voltage dependence from +30 to +140 mV (<italic>z</italic> = 0.49 <italic>e</italic>), which then decreases from +180 to +240 mV (<italic>z</italic> = &#x02212;0.29 <italic>e</italic>). Similarly, the steady state G<sub>K</sub>&#x02013;V relationship exhibits a maximum voltage dependence (<italic>z</italic> = 2 <italic>e</italic>) from 0 to +100 mV, and is weakly voltage dependent (<italic>z</italic> &#x02245; 0.4 <italic>e</italic>) at more negative voltages, where <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>&#x02013;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>. These results can be understood in terms of a gating scheme where a central transition between a closed and an open conformation is allosterically regulated by the state of four independent and identical voltage sensors. In the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, this allosteric mechanism results in a gating scheme with five closed (C) and five open (O) states, where the majority of the channel's voltage dependence results from rapid C&#x02013;C and O&#x02013;O transitions, whereas the C&#x02013;O transitions are rate limiting and weakly voltage dependent. These conclusions not only provide a framework for interpreting studies of large conductance Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channel voltage gating, but also have important implications for understanding the mechanism of Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>calcium</kwd><kwd>K<sub>Ca</sub> channel</kwd><kwd>large conductance Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channel</kwd><kwd>ion channel gating</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Large conductance Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> (BK)<sup>1</sup> channels are sensitive to both membrane voltage and intracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="GormanandThomas1980">Gorman and Thomas 1980</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Marty1981">Marty 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Pallottaetal1981">Pallotta et al. 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Barrettetal1982">Barrett et al. 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Latorreetal1982">Latorre et al. 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="MethfesselandBoheim1982">Methfessel and Boheim 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="MoczydlowskiandLatorre1983">Moczydlowski and Latorre 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="DiChiaraandReinhart1995">DiChiara and Reinhart 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). The response of BK channels to Ca<sup>2+</sup> is key to their physiological role in a variety of cell types and has been studied extensively (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="LewisandHudspeth1983">Lewis and Hudspeth 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="MaglebyandPallotta1983a">Magleby and Pallotta 1983a</xref>,<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MaglebyandPallotta1983b">Magleby and Pallotta 1983b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="PetersenandMaruyama1984">Petersen and Maruyama 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Storm1987">Storm 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Lancasteretal1991">Lancaster et al. 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="McManusandMagleby1991">McManus and Magleby 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="BraydenandNelson1992">Brayden and Nelson 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="BielefeldtandJackson1993">Bielefeldt and Jackson 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="CrestandGola1993">Crest and Gola 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Robitailleetal1993">Robitaille et al. 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Nelsonetal1995">Nelson et al. 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Yazejianetal1997">Yazejian et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="MarrionandTavalin1998">Marrion and Tavalin 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="SafronovandVogel1998">Safronov and Vogel 1998</xref>). Attempts to identify Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding sites have also provided a focus for structure&#x02013;function studies (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Weietal1994">Wei et al. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="SchreiberandSalkoff1997">Schreiber and Salkoff 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Schreiberetal1999">Schreiber et al. 1999</xref>). In comparison, the voltage-dependent activation of BK channels has received less attention. Yet BK channels respond rapidly to voltage changes (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HudspethandLewis1988">Hudspeth and Lewis 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>), suggesting that this process might contribute to the physiological function of BK channels. More importantly, interactions between Ca<sup>2+</sup>- and voltage-dependent activation (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>) imply that understanding BK channel Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity depends on also understanding the mechanism of voltage-dependent gating.</p><p>Voltage-dependent activation of BK channels occurs on a millisecond time scale, similar to many purely voltage-gated K<sup>+</sup> (K<sub>v</sub>) channels. However, during an action potential, changes in voltage and voltage-dependent Ca<sup>2+</sup> entry through Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels contribute to BK channel activity such that the direct effect of voltage is difficult to assess. Using a spike-like voltage clamp, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="CrestandGola1993">Crest and Gola 1993</xref> examined the time course of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and K currents during Ca<sup>2+</sup> action potentials in molluscan neurons and concluded that BK channel voltage dependence is important for closing channels rapidly following action potentials and for terminating repetitive firing in response to sustained depolarization. The properties of mammalian BK channel activation studied under constant [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> suggest they could participate in similar processes. The voltage sensitivity of BK channel activation is weak in comparison with that of K<sub>v</sub> channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>), but open probability (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>) can increase from &#x0223c;10 to 90% of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>omax</sub> in response to a 70-mV voltage change centered around the half-activation voltage (V<sub>h</sub>) (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Barrettetal1982">Barrett et al. 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). Calcium alters the kinetics of voltage-dependent activation and shifts V<sub>h</sub> to more negative voltages (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Barrettetal1982">Barrett et al. 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). Thus the change in <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> evoked by a given voltage stimulus can be &#x0201c;tuned&#x0201d; by [Ca<sup>2+</sup>].</p><p>Most studies of BK channel gating have been performed in the presence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Barrettetal1982">Barrett et al. 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Latorreetal1982">Latorre et al. 1982</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="MoczydlowskiandLatorre1983">Moczydlowski and Latorre 1983</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="McManusandMagleby1991">McManus and Magleby 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="RothbergandMagleby1998">Rothberg and Magleby 1998</xref>), leaving open the possibility that the mechanism of voltage sensitivity reflects, to some extent, voltage-dependent changes in the affinity of Ca<sup>2+</sup> for its binding site rather than a direct effect of voltage on channel conformation (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MoczydlowskiandLatorre1983">Moczydlowski and Latorre 1983</xref>). Recent studies, however, involving several cloned homologues of the <italic>slo</italic> family of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels demonstrate that BK channels can be activated by membrane depolarization in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Meeraetal1996">Meera et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>), and that gating currents can be detected under these conditions (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Stefanietal1997">Stefani et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>). These and other results indicate that BK channel voltage sensitivity reflects the action of an intrinsic voltage sensor (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Stefanietal1997">Stefani et al. 1997</xref>). Indeed, the amino acid sequence of <italic>slo</italic> BK channels contains a &#x0201c;core&#x0201d; domain that has many features in common with that of K<sub>v</sub> channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Weietal1994">Wei et al. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Diazetal1998">Diaz et al. 1998</xref>). These include a p-region, homologous to the pore-forming region of K<sub>v</sub> channels, surrounded by six putative transmembrane segments including a charged S4 domain. The S4 domain forms part of the voltage sensor of <italic>Shaker</italic> and other voltage-gated channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="YangandHorn1995">Yang and Horn 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="AggarwalandMacKinnon1996">Aggarwal and MacKinnon 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Larssonetal1996">Larsson et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Mannuzzuetal1996">Mannuzzu et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Seohetal1996">Seoh et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Yangetal1996">Yang et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Yusafetal1996">Yusaf et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Baoetal1999">Bao et al. 1999</xref>), and S4 mutations alter the voltage dependence of BK channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Diazetal1998">Diaz et al. 1998</xref>; Cui, J., and R.W. Aldrich, manuscript in preparation). Thus, it is likely that structural and mechanistic similarities exist between BK and K<sub>v</sub> channels.</p><p>In the present study, we examine the response of mSlo Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels to voltage in the virtual absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (&#x0003c;1 nM, see <sc>methods</sc>) to help understand the mechanism of voltage-dependent gating. The behavior of mSlo in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> must reflect transitions between only a subset of the states that are available in the presence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Thus, the 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> condition should provide a limiting example of mSlo voltage-gating behavior that must be accounted for by any complete model of mSlo gating. The ability of BK channels to open in a voltage-dependent manner in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> suggests that channel activation is fundamentally a voltage-dependent process that is modulated by Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Meeraetal1996">Meera et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>). If so, the voltage-dependent activation pathway must be central to the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent response, and delineation of this pathway in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> will be a prerequisite to the establishment of a detailed Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent gating scheme or the interpretation of BK channel structure&#x02013;function studies that seek to distinguish Ca<sup>2+</sup>- and voltage-dependent conformational changes.</p><p>Many of the effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and voltage on the kinetic and steady state properties of macroscopic mSlo I<sub>K</sub> can be reproduced by a gating scheme (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>) based on the allosteric model of <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Monodetal1965">Monod et al. 1965</xref>. According to this voltage-dependent Monod-Wyman-Changeux (MWC) scheme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref>), mSlo channels activate by undergoing a rate limiting, voltage-dependent transition between a closed (C) and an open (O) conformation and Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding alters the kinetic and equilibrium properties of this transition. Because mSlo channels are composed of four identical subunits (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Shenetal1994">Shen et al. 1994</xref>), the model assumes that each channel contains four identical Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites. This results in a scheme with 10 states representing different Ca<sup>2+</sup>-bound versions of the closed and open conformation.</p><p>A key feature of this model is that the C to O conformational change is allosteric in that it not only opens the channel pore, but also alters the Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding sites, causing their affinities for Ca<sup>2+</sup> to increase. This allosteric linkage between channel opening and Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding, represented by a factor, C, in the model, accounts for the ability of Ca<sup>2+</sup> to affect open probability. Another important feature of the model is that the transition from C to O is represented by a single step and is therefore assumed to be concerted in the sense that Ca<sup>2+</sup>-binding sites in all four subunits change simultaneously upon channel opening. Because the C&#x02013;O transition is voltage dependent, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref> also implicitly assumes that voltage sensors, presumably present in each subunit, move in a concerted manner during channel activation.</p><p>Although <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref> reproduces many features of mSlo activation, it is likely to be an oversimplification, particularly with regards to the mechanism of voltage-dependent gating. A basic prediction of this model is that activation can be described by a simple two-state process in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding, indicated by the highlighted C&#x02013;O transition in the above diagram. Although a two-state mechanism can account for the basic features of activation, deviations from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref>&#x02013;like behavior are observed in the presence and absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> that suggest BK channel voltage gating is more complicated (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>). These deviations include a brief delay in voltage-dependent activation (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Stefanietal1997">Stefani et al. 1997</xref>), and a conductance&#x02013;voltage relationship (G&#x02013;V) that is best fit by a Boltzmann function raised to a power greater than one (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). The shape of the G&#x02013;V also changes slightly with [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub>, an effect that is not predicted by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>; Cui, J., and R.W. Aldrich, manuscript in preparation). Similarly, the voltage dependence of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation kinetics deviates from the prediction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref> at extreme voltages (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>). Finally, a rapid component of gating charge movement is observed that precedes channel opening (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Stefanietal1997">Stefani et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>), whereas <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref> requires that channel opening and voltage-sensor movement occur simultaneously.</p><p>In the present study, we examine in detail several aspects of mSlo behavior in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> that deviate from the predictions of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref>. The results can be explained by relaxing the assumption that channel opening involves a single concerted voltage-dependent transition. Instead, we suggest that mSlo voltage sensors can move independently and that channel opening and voltage-sensor movement represent distinct events that are allosterically coupled. The resulting model of voltage-dependent gating differs from many common schemes in that the channel can open while any number (or none) of the four voltage sensors are activated. This allosteric mechanism defines a 10-state voltage-gating scheme with multiple open and closed states arranged in parallel, analogous to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref>. Similar schemes have been proposed to describe the gating of other voltage-dependent channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MarksandJones1992">Marks and Jones 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="N0x1e510b0N0x1e3fc30">R&#x000ed;os et al. 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="McCormacketal1994">McCormack et al. 1994</xref>).</p><p>The proposed model has important implications for the interpretation and analysis of BK channel structure-function studies because complicated relationships will exist between elementary molecular events such as voltage-sensor movement or channel opening, which give rise to the apparently simple macroscopic features of I<sub>K.</sub> In addition, the complexity of the voltage-gating scheme greatly increases the minimum number of states that are required to describe BK channel gating in the presence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. Finally, the demonstration that mSlo gating is a multistate process in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> raises fundamental questions concerning the identity of the step or steps in the activation pathway that are affected by Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>methods</title><sec><title>Channel Expression</title><p>Experiments were performed with the mbr5 clone of the mouse homologue of the Slo gene (mSlo), kindly provided by Dr. Larry Salkoff (Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, MO). The clone was modified to facilitate mutagenesis and was propagated and cRNA transcribed as previously described (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997b">Cox et al. 1997b</xref>). <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes were injected with &#x0223c;0.5&#x02013;5 ng of cRNA (50 nl, 0.01&#x02013;0.1 ng/nl) 3&#x02013;7 d before recording.</p></sec><sec><title>Electrophysiology</title><p>Currents were recorded using the patch clamp technique in the inside out configuration (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Hamilletal1981">Hamill et al. 1981</xref>). Upon excision, patches were transferred into a separate chamber and washed with at least 20 vol of internal solution. Internal solutions contained (mM): 104 KMeSO<sub>3</sub>, 6 KCl, and 20 HEPES, and 40 &#x003bc;M (+)-18-crown-6-tetracarboxylic acid (18C6TA) was added to chelate contaminant Ba<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Diazetal1996">Diaz et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Neyton1996">Neyton 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997b">Cox et al. 1997b</xref>). In addition &#x0201c;0 Ca<sup>2+</sup>&#x0201d; solutions contained 2 mM EGTA, reducing free Ca<sup>2+</sup> to an estimated 0.8 nM based on the presence of &#x0223c;10 &#x003bc;M contaminant Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997b">Cox et al. 1997b</xref>). 4.5 &#x003bc;M Ca<sup>2+</sup> solutions were buffered with 1 mM HEDTA and free Ca<sup>2+</sup> was measured with a Ca<sup>2+</sup> electrode (Orion Research, Inc.). The external (pipette) solution contained (mM): 108 KMeSO<sub>3</sub>, 2 KCl, 2 MgCl<sub>2</sub>, and 20 HEPES. pH was adjusted to 7.2. Experiments were carried out at 5&#x000b0; or 20&#x000b0;C (&#x000b1; &#x0223c;1&#x000b0;C) as indicated.</p><p>Electrodes were made from thick-walled 1010 glass (World Precision Instruments, Inc.) or borosilicate glass (VWR Micropipettes). Their tips were coated with wax (KERR Sticky Wax) and fire polished before use. Pipette access resistance measured in the bath solution (0.5&#x02013;1.5 M&#x003a9;) was used as an estimate of series resistance (R<sub>s</sub>) to correct the pipette voltage (V<sub>p</sub>) at which I<sub>K</sub> was recorded. The corrected pipette voltage, V<sub>m</sub>, was used in determining membrane conductance (G<sub>K</sub>) from tail current measurements and in plotting the voltage dependence of G<sub>K</sub> or the time constant of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation [&#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)]. Series resistance error was &#x0003c;15 mV for all data presented and &#x0003c;10 mV for &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) measurements.</p><p>Data were acquired with an Axopatch 200-B amplifier that was modified to provide an increased voltage range (Axon Instruments) and set in patch mode. Currents were filtered at 100 kHz with the Axopatch's internal four-pole bessel filter and subsequently by an eight-pole bessel filter (Frequency Devices, Inc.). Macroscopic currents were filtered at 30&#x02013;50 kHz and sampled at 100 kHz with a 16 bit A/D converter (ITC-16; Instrutech Corp.). A P/&#x02212;4 protocol was used for leak subtraction (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="ArmstrongandBezanilla1974">Armstrong and Bezanilla 1974</xref>) from a holding potential of &#x02212;80 mV. To increase the signal to noise ratio, the response to four to eight pulses were typically averaged at each pulse voltage. A Macintosh-based computer system was used in combination with Pulse Control acquisition software (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HerringtonandBookman1995">Herrington and Bookman 1995</xref>) and Igor Pro for graphing and data analysis (Wavemetrics Inc.). A Levenberg-Marquardt algorithm was used to perform nonlinear least-squares fits.</p></sec><sec><title>Simulations</title><p>Simulations were performed using a fifth order Runga-Kutta algorithm with adaptive step size (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Pressetal1992">Press et al. 1992</xref>) implemented in Igor Pro (Wavemetrics Inc.).</p></sec><sec><title>Filter and Instrumentation Delay</title><p>The effect of filtering on I<sub>K</sub> activation kinetics was tested by convolving simulated traces that closely match the data with the impulse response of an eight-pole bessel filter. The impulse response was determined as the derivative of the step response, measured for a 2-kHz filter and scaled along the time axis to correspond to a particular corner frequency. Simulations were calculated at 1-&#x003bc;s intervals and were filtered at 100 kHz, and then at 30 kHz to correspond to the experimental arrangement. This procedure introduced a delay of 22 &#x003bc;s, accounting for the majority the instrumentation delay (25 &#x003bc;s), but had no detectable effect on the shape of the simulated traces. Therefore, simulations were left unfiltered and data were corrected for filtering by shifting I<sub>K</sub> traces along the time axis by &#x02212;25 &#x003bc;s. Instrumentation delay was estimated by measuring the time between a voltage step command to the patch clamp and the peak of the capacitive transient (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SigworthandZhou1992">Sigworth and Zhou 1992</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Single Channel Analysis</title><p>Single channel events were observed in patches containing hundreds of channels at voltages where open probability is low (&#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>). Currents were typically filtered at 20 kHz, yielding a dead-time of &#x0223c;10 &#x003bc;s, and were sampled at 50&#x02013;100 kHz. At voltages where the closed level was clearly defined, total open probability (<italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub>) was determined from steady state recordings of 5&#x02013;45-s duration. All-points amplitude histograms were compiled and the probability (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>k</sub>) of occupying each open level (k) was evaluated using a 1/2 amplitude criterion. <italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub> was then determined as: <disp-formula><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}nP_{{\mathrm{o}}}={{\sum_{{\mathrm{k}}}}}{\mathrm{k}}P_{{\mathrm{k}}}{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>
<italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub> was also evaluated by fitting <italic>P</italic>
<sub>k</sub> with a Poisson distribution: <disp-formula><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}P_{{\mathrm{k}}}=\frac{ \left \left(nP_{{\mathrm{o}}}\right) \right ^{{\mathrm{k}}}}{{\mathrm{k}}!}e^{-nP_{{\mathrm{o}}}}{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>In all cases <italic>P</italic>
<sub>k</sub> was well fit by a Poisson distribution and the values of <italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub> obtained by the two methods differed by &#x0003c;5%. This is consistent with the idea that I<sub>K</sub> represents the activity of a large population of channels with low <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> rather than a subpopulation with higher <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>. Normalized open probability (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>P</italic>
<sub>omax</sub> = <italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>nP</italic>
<sub>omax</sub>) was determined by combining <italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub> measurements with an estimate of <italic>nP</italic>
<sub>omax</sub> obtained from the macroscopic G<sub>K</sub>&#x02013;V relationship in the same patch (<italic>nP</italic>
<sub>omax</sub> = G<sub>Kmax</sub>/g<sub>K</sub>, where g<sub>K</sub> is the single channel conductance). Patches that were used to measure single channel activity at negative voltages often produced currents that were too large to measure (&#x0003e;20 nA) at voltages that activate mSlo channels maximally. In these cases, G<sub>max</sub> was estimated by fitting the macroscopic G<sub>K</sub>-V with a Boltzmann function ({1 + exp[&#x02212;z<italic>e</italic>(V &#x02212; V<sub>h</sub>)/kT]}<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) raised to the 3.2 power as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. C</xref>.</p><p>For voltages &#x0003e;60 mV from the reversal potential (0 mV), single channel amplitudes were large enough that false opening events due to noise were not detected using 20 kHz filtering. The prevalence of false events was assessed by evaluating the number of current transients from the closed level that exceed the 1/2 amplitude criterion in a direction opposite that of the channel opening. <italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub> was determined after digitally filtering current records until such false events were not observed at +20 or &#x02212;20 mV. This procedure yielded a corner frequency of &#x0223c;5 kHz. For V &#x0003e; +60 mV, no difference in <italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub> was observed with 5 or 20 kHz filtering. However, for V &#x0003c; &#x02212;60 mV, a decrease in <italic>nP</italic>
<sub>o</sub> was observed at 5 kHz, reflecting the brevity of open times at these voltages. The largest decreases (&#x0223c;30%) were observed at the most negative voltages (approximately &#x02212;120 mV). Thus, <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> may be underestimated, but this effect is small when compared with patch-to-patch variation in <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> observed at these voltages (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6E</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. F</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Shifts in Voltage-dependent Parameters</title><p>Patch-to-patch variations in half-activation voltage and other voltage-dependent parameters are observed for mSlo (V<sub>h</sub> = 190 &#x000b1; 10 mV; SD, <italic>n</italic> = 20 in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup>) and hSlo (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Stefanietal1997">Stefani et al. 1997</xref>), possibly due to differences in redox state of the channel (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="DiChiaraandReinhart1997">DiChiara and Reinhart 1997</xref>). Such shifts do not appreciably alter the shape of the G<sub>K</sub>-V or other voltage-dependent relationships, but make comparisons of data between different experiments difficult and alter the shape of averaged voltage-dependent relationships relative to those observed in individual experiments. To compensate for this effect, V<sub>h</sub> was determined for each patch and compared with the average for all experiments (&#x02329;V<sub>h</sub>&#x0232a;) at the same [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]. Data from individual experiments were then shifted along the voltage axis by &#x00394;V<sub>h</sub> = (&#x02329;V<sub>h</sub>&#x0232a; &#x02212; V<sub>h</sub>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>results</title><sec><title>Delay in I<sub>K</sub> Activation</title><p>In the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>, mSlo Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels open in response to membrane depolarization exhibiting a steady state half-activation voltage of approximately +190 mV (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> A<sub>1</sub> shows mSlo I<sub>K</sub> evoked in response to a 20-ms pulse to +160 mV from a holding potential of &#x02212;80 mV in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> (20&#x000b0;C). The time course of activation and deactivation are well fit by exponential functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> A<sub>1</sub>, dashed lines). Similar exponential kinetics are observed over a wide range of voltage and [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>), suggesting a two-state model with a single voltage-dependent transition between a closed and an open state. However, the exponential activation of I<sub>K</sub> is preceded by a brief delay in the presence or absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Stefanietal1997">Stefani et al. 1997</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> A<sub>2</sub> shows the initial time course of I<sub>K</sub> activation on an expanded time scale. There is a delay of &#x0223c;100 &#x003bc;s before the current begins to increase, and at least 300 &#x003bc;s is required to achieve an exponential time course (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> A<sub>2</sub>, dashed line). Although this delay is brief compared with the subsequent relaxation of I<sub>K</sub>, it is inconsistent with a two-state gating scheme and suggests that mSlo channels undergo one or more transitions among closed states before opening. To better study these rapid transitions, we examined I<sub>K</sub> activation at a reduced temperature. A family of I<sub>K</sub> evoked by membrane depolarization at 5&#x000b0;C still exhibits activation kinetics that are well fit by single exponential functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> B<sub>1</sub>). The activation is slowed relative to 20&#x000b0;C, and the delay is similarly prolonged (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> B<sub>2</sub>). I<sub>K</sub> begins to increase after 250 &#x003bc;s and attains an exponential time course after 1 ms. A control trace evoked in response to a voltage pulse to &#x02212;180 mV is also shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> B<sub>2</sub>; the capacitive transient decays within 30 &#x003bc;s, showing that voltage clamp speed and filter properties contribute little to the delay.</p><p>The delay in I<sub>K</sub> in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> indicates that the voltage-dependent activation of mSlo cannot be described by a two-state model. This conclusion is inconsistent with the predictions of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref>, where channel opening involves a single concerted step. However, mSlo is a homotetramer and activation is likely to involve the participation of multiple subunits. Unless these subunits move in a strictly concerted manner, channel activation must be described by a multistate scheme that reflects conformational changes in individual subunits. The most extreme deviation from the behavior of a concerted model should occur when subunits act independently (i.e., noncooperatively). Shown below is an example of a completely noncooperative model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S2">Fig. 2</xref>). This scheme corresponds to that used by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="HodgkinandHuxley1952">Hodgkin and Huxley 1952</xref> to describe the activation of voltage-dependent K<sup>+</sup> channels in squid axon. It assumes that channel opening requires all four identical subunits to undergo independent transitions between a resting (R) and an activated (A) conformation.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S2">Fig. 2</xref> can be reduced to a five-state kinetic scheme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S3">Fig. 3</xref>), where subscripts (0&#x02013;4) indicate the number of activated subunits in each closed (C) or open (O) state.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S3">Fig. 3</xref> predicts a delay, but it cannot reproduce the kinetics of mSlo activation. The Hodgkin-Huxley model produces an activation time course that is highly sigmoidal because the delay and subsequent activation of I<sub>K</sub> are both determined by a single process (subunit activation) and therefore occur on a similar time scale. When <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S3">Fig. 3</xref> is fit to the brief delay in mSlo I<sub>K</sub>, it predicts an activation time course that is too rapid (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>2</sub>).</p><p>The relationship between the delay and subsequent relaxation of I<sub>K</sub> can be defined precisely for models like <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S2">Fig. 2</xref>, which require <italic>n</italic> independent subunits to be activated before channels are open (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HodgkinandHuxley1952">Hodgkin and Huxley 1952</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="ColeandMoore1960">Cole and Moore 1960</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="ColquhounandHawkes1977">Colquhoun and Hawkes 1977</xref>). For such models, the time-dependent occupancy of the open state is: <disp-formula id="FD1"><label>1</label><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O}} \left \left(t\right) \right = \left \left[{\mathrm{A}} \left \left(t\right) \right \right] \right ^{n}{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> where A(<italic>t</italic>) represents the probability that a subunit is activated: <disp-formula id="FD2"><label>2</label><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{A}} \left \left(t\right) \right ={\mathrm{A}}_{{\mathrm{{\infty}}}} \left \left(1-e^{-{t}/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}\right) \right \end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> and &#x003c4; = 1/(&#x003b1; + &#x003b2;) is the time constant of subunit activation, with A<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> = &#x003b1;/(&#x003b1; + &#x003b2;) representing the steady state activation. The time course of I<sub>K</sub> activation is determined by combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD1"/> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2"/> and expanding in a binomial series: <disp-formula id="FD3"><label>3</label><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{K}}}={\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{{\infty}}}} \left \left(1-e^{-{t}/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}\right) \right ^{n}={\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{{\infty}}}}{{\sum^{n}_{k=0}}}\frac{ \left \left(-1\right) \right ^{k}n!}{k! \left \left(n-k\right) \right }e^{-{kt}/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> where I<sub>&#x0221e;</sub> is proportional to A<sub>&#x0221e;</sub>
<italic><sup>n</sup></italic> and represents the steady state amplitude of I<sub>K</sub>. The delay duration (&#x00394;<italic>t</italic>) is defined by fitting the slowest component of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation after the delay (I<sub>slow</sub>) with a single exponential function: <disp-formula id="FD4"><label>4</label><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{slow}}}={\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{{\infty}}}} \left \left(1-e^{{ \left \left({\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t-t\right) \right }/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}\right) \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>This function intersects the time axis at <italic>t</italic> = &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>. I<sub>slow</sub> can be determined from the first two terms of the series in <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3"/>: <disp-formula id="FD5"><label>5</label><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{slow}}}={\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{{\infty}}}} \left \left(1-ne^{{-t}/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}\right) \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4"/> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD5"/>: <disp-formula id="FD6"><label>6</label><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t={\mathrm{ln}} \left \left(n\right) \right {\mathrm{{\tau}.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>For a Hodgkin-Huxley model (<italic>n</italic> = 4), &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> = 1.39 &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) represents the slow time constant of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation. In contrast, the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> A indicate &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> = 0.12 &#x003b3;(I<sub>K</sub>).</p><p>The rapid attainment of an exponential time course in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> A suggests that the transitions responsible for the delay equilibrate within 1 ms and that a much slower process limits activation during the subsequent 30 ms. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S2">Fig. 2</xref> can reproduce such behavior only when subunits interact in a highly negatively cooperative manner such that one transition becomes rate limiting while others equilibrate rapidly. An alternative model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S4">Fig. 4</xref>) can account for I<sub>K</sub> kinetics with the assumption that subunits undergo rapid independent transitions, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S2">Fig. 2</xref>, but that channel opening involves an additional conformational change that is slow and rate limiting (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="LedwellandAldrich1999">Ledwell and Aldrich 1999</xref>).</p><p>If channel opening can only occur when all four subunits are activated, this model reduces to a six-state kinetic scheme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> assumes that subunits undergo independent conformational changes when the channel is closed. However, the overall activation scheme is cooperative because the final transition from C to O depends on the state of all four subunits, which requires that they interact (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="WymanandGill1990">Wyman and Gill 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Sigworth1994">Sigworth 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Zagottaetal1994a">Zagotta et al. 1994a</xref>).</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> provides a reasonable fit to both the brief delay and exponential activation time course of I<sub>K</sub> at +180 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> A). To test this model in more detail, we analyzed the delay kinetics. Models like <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, which require <italic>n</italic> independent subunits to be activated before channels can open, predict I<sub>K</sub> kinetics more complex than predicted by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD3"/>. However, the rate of I<sub>K</sub> activation (I<sub>K</sub>&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>d</italic>I<sub>K</sub>/<italic>dt</italic>) during the delay can be approximated by the expression: <disp-formula id="FD7"><label>7</label><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{I^{\prime}}}_{{\mathrm{K}}} \left \left(t\right) \right ={\mathrm{I^{\prime}}}_{{\mathrm{Kmax}}} \left \left[1-e^{-{t}/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}\right] \right ^{n}{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> provided two conditions are satisfied. First, subunit activation must be much faster than the C&#x02013;O transition. The relative kinetics of the delay and I<sub>K</sub> relaxation suggest this is the case for mSlo. Second, few channels must occupy the open state. This is satisfied during the delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation because I<sub>K</sub> achieves an exponential time course when <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>, estimated from G<sub>K</sub>/G<sub>Kmax</sub>, is &#x0003c;0.05. Given these assumptions, the time-dependent occupancy of the last closed state (C<sub>L</sub>) is determined primarily by transitions among closed states and can be approximated: <disp-formula id="FD8"><label>8</label><tex-math id="M10">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}} \left \left(t\right) \right = \left \left[{\mathrm{A}} \left \left(t\right) \right \right] \right ^{n}{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>The rate of change in occupancy of the open state (O&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) = <italic>d</italic>O/<italic>dt</italic>) is then: <disp-formula id="FD9"><label>9</label><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right ={\mathrm{{\delta}C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}} \left \left(t\right) \right -{\mathrm{{\gamma}O}} \left \left(t\right) \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>When few channels are open, such that &#x003b3;O &#x0003c;&#x0003c; &#x003b4;C<sub>L</sub>, this expression simplifies to: <disp-formula id="FD10"><label>10</label><tex-math id="M12">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right ={\mathrm{{\delta}C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}} \left \left(t\right) \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>The expression for I&#x02032;<sub>K</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7"/>) is then determined by combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2"/>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD8"/>, and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10"/>.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> A<sub>2</sub> shows the initial time course of I<sub>K</sub> at +180 mV; the time derivative of this record is plotted on linear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> B<sub>1</sub>) and log&#x02013;log (B<sub>2</sub>) scales. The time course of I&#x02032;<sub>K</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) is sigmoidal, and can be approximated by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> or by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD7"/> with <italic>n</italic> = 4 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, B<sub>1</sub> and B<sub>2</sub>). However, the log&#x02013;log plot reveals that I&#x02032;<sub>K</sub> is best fit when <italic>n</italic> is reduced to 2.9 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> B<sub>2</sub>). This deviation from the prediction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> is small, but significant, and suggests that a more complicated model may be necessary to explain our results. One way to fit the data is by modifying <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> to include direct cooperative interactions between subunits. For example, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref> assumes that the forward and backward rate constants for subunit activation are increased by a factor X for each subunit that is in the activated state.</p><p>The equilibrium properties of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref> are identical, but <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref> can fit I&#x02032;<sub>K</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) with X = 3 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> B<sub>2</sub>). Similar results are obtained if only the forward rate is effected by subunit activation, thereby altering the equilibrium constants (X = 3.5, data not shown). However, our most favored model, discussed later, can account for these results without abandoning the idea that subunits undergo independent transitions.</p><p>Several experimental factors might contribute to a deviation between I<sub>K</sub> kinetics and the prediction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>. The membrane charging time constant for an excised patch is expected to be very fast (&#x003c4; = C<sub>m</sub>R<sub>s</sub> &#x02264; 1 &#x003bc;s, see <sc>methods</sc>) and should not affect I<sub>K</sub> kinetics. The relaxation of the capacitive transient in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> B<sub>2</sub> (control) is mainly limited by the filtering of the current signal. To test whether filtering affects I<sub>K</sub> kinetics, simulated traces in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> were convolved with the impulse responses of 100- and 30-kHz eight-pole bessel filters to reproduce experimental conditions (see <sc>methods</sc>). The filtered and unfiltered traces were indistinguishable after compensating for a 22-&#x003bc;s filter delay (data not shown). Thus, I<sub>K</sub> kinetics are not modified by filtering and appear to represent a genuine property of the channel.</p><p>It is conceivable that <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> could give rise to the observed delay kinetics if channels were distributed in states other than C<sub>0</sub> at the start of the voltage pulse. This possibility was ruled out by examining the effect of initial conditions on the delay. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> A shows the time course of I<sub>K</sub> evoked at +180 mV after a 1-ms prepulse to voltages between &#x02212;80 and +120 mV. Prepulses to voltages &#x0003e;0 mV produced a progressive decrease in the delay, resulting in a shift of I<sub>K</sub> along the time axis analogous to that reported by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="ColeandMoore1960">Cole and Moore 1960</xref> for K<sup>+</sup> current in squid axon. A similar effect was reported for hSlo channels by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Stefanietal1997">Stefani et al. 1997</xref>. This Cole-Moore shift indicates that the initial distribution of channels among closed states is voltage dependent. However, prepulses to &#x02212;80 or 0 mV had no detectable effect on the delay, suggesting that the closed state distribution does not change at voltages &#x0003c;0 mV. This result supports the assumption that channels mainly occupy the ground state (C<sub>0</sub>) at &#x02212;80 mV.</p></sec><sec><title>Voltage Dependence of the Delay in I<sub>K</sub> Activation</title><p>Although the delay kinetics deviate from the prediction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, they are consistent with the idea that multiple closed-state transitions precede channel opening. In addition, the dependence of the delay on prepulse voltage implies that closed-state transitions are voltage dependent. To help characterize the voltage dependence of these early transitions, we measured the delay duration (&#x00394;<italic>t</italic>) during pulses to different voltages. &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> was determined by fitting I<sub>K</sub> with exponential functions (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4"/>), as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> B. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> C plots &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> on a log scale versus pulse voltage for two different experiments. The average &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship is plotted in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> D (mean &#x000b1; SEM, <italic>n</italic> = 6). The delay is maximal at approximately +155 mV and exhibits a bell-shaped voltage dependence.</p><p>The two &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationships in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> C are similar in shape but differ in magnitude by &#x0223c;25%, possibly reflecting variations in temperature (T = 5 &#x000b1; 1&#x000b0;C) (&#x00394;<italic>t</italic> has a Q<sub>10</sub> of 2.3 based on comparison of the delay at 20&#x000b0;C in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> B (210 &#x003bc;s) to the mean delay measured at 5&#x000b0;C (725 &#x003bc;s) at +160 mV). To compensate for patch-to-patch variation in the magnitude of &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>, the average &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> D was determined after first normalizing the component &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V's to the mean &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> at +180&#x02013;195 mV. The ability of the average and individual relationships to be fit by the same functions (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. D</xref>, solid lines), discussed below, argues that the average accurately captures the shape of the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V.</p><p>In general, the relationship between the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> and the kinetics of closed-state transitions will not be as simple as described for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S2">Fig. 2</xref> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD6"/>). The time course of I<sub>K</sub>, and therefore the delay duration, may be influenced by transitions between closed and open states and by O&#x02013;O transitions if multiple open states exist. Previous studies of <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channels have taken the approach of measuring delay duration at high voltages to estimate the kinetics of closed-state transitions (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Zagottaetal1994b">Zagotta et al. 1994b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="SchoppaandSigworth1998a">Schoppa and Sigworth 1998a</xref>). At sufficiently positive voltages, the backward rate constant from open to closed is assumed to be small such that the occupancy of the open state reflects only the rate of leaving the closed state. In other words, the time course of I<sub>K</sub> approximates the cumulative distribution of latencies to first opening, and &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> is highly dependent upon closed-state transition kinetics.</p><p>In this study, &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> was measured over a range of voltages where backward rate constants from open to closed may not be negligible. However, the initial time course of I&#x02032;<sub>K</sub>(<italic>t</italic>) during the delay should be determined mainly by the rate of leaving the closed state when <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is small (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10"/>). Thus, the initial time course of I<sub>K</sub> and the delay duration will be determined by closed-state transition kinetics provided I<sub>K</sub> achieves an exponential time course while <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is small. This condition appears to be satisfied at all voltages where &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> was measured for mSlo (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> B<sub>1</sub> and 3 B). Therefore, the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship should provide information about the voltage dependence of closed state transitions. Such an argument cannot be made in the case of <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channels because the time course of activation has pronounced sigmoidicity such that <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is not small when I<sub>K</sub> achieves an exponential time course.</p><p>The precise relationship between closed-state transition kinetics and &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> is model dependent. For some models, including <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> will be proportional to the time constant of voltage sensor movement &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub> (provided I<sub>K</sub> achieves an exponential time course when <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is small and transitions among closed states are fast relative to channel opening); in which case, the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship can be used to determine the voltage dependence of the R&#x02013;A transition (see <xref ref-type="app" rid="APPAppendix"/>).</p><p>Consistent with the prediction that &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> reflects the voltage dependence of &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>, the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relations can be fit by functions of the form &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> = 1/(a + b), where a=a<sub>o</sub>*<italic>e</italic>
<sup><italic>z</italic><sub>a</sub><italic>e</italic><italic>k</italic><italic>T</italic></sup>, b=b<sub>o</sub>*<italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;<italic>z</italic><sub>b</sub><italic>e</italic><italic>k</italic><italic>T</italic></sup>(<italic>z</italic>
<sub>a</sub> = <italic>z</italic>
<sub>b</sub> = 0.28 <italic>e</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. D</xref>, solid lines). The bell-shaped voltage dependence is consistent with a process governed by a single transition with voltage-dependent forward and backward rate constants. If &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> is proportional to &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>[v] then <italic>z</italic>
<sub>a</sub> = <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> and <italic>z</italic>
<sub>b</sub> = <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>, and the fit to the average &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> D implies that the transition from R to A involves a total charge movement (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> = <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> + <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>) of 0.56 <italic>e</italic> with a half-activation voltage (V<sub>h</sub>) of +153 mV, corresponding to the peak of the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V. Simulations of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> using these parameters can reproduce the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> D, dashed line). Although our final model is more complicated than <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, we show later that it can reproduce the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship using similar parameters for the voltage-sensor transition (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> = 0.55 <italic>e</italic>, V<sub>h</sub> = +145 mV). Moreover, gating current measurements in the companion article produce similar results (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> = 0.55 <italic>e</italic>, V<sub>h</sub> = +155 mV) (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>). Thus measurements of I<sub>K</sub> delay appear to provide a reasonable method for characterizing mSlo voltage-sensor movement.</p></sec><sec><title>The Voltage Dependence of I<sub>K</sub> Relaxation</title><p>The predominantly exponential time course of I<sub>K</sub> suggests that mSlo activation is dominated by a single rate-limiting step. To study the properties of this transition, we examined the voltage dependence of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation kinetics. The time constant of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation, measured after the delay, changes with voltage, suggesting that the rate-limiting step may be voltage dependent (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>). But mSlo gating is a multistate process with rapid, voltage-dependent transitions among closed states. While the kinetics of closed-state transitions are too fast to limit the exponential relaxation of I<sub>K</sub>, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) may be influenced by the equilibrium distribution of closed states. Therefore, the voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) may reflect a voltage dependence of the closed-state equilibria in addition to the rate-limiting step. For example, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> predicts: <disp-formula id="FD11"><label>11</label><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{{\tau}}} \left \left({\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{K}}}\right) \right =\frac{1}{{\mathrm{{\delta}}}P{\mathrm{C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}}+{\mathrm{{\gamma}}}}{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> where <italic>P</italic>C<sub>L</sub> represents the conditional probability that a closed channel occupies the last closed state [i.e., <italic>P</italic>(C<sub>4</sub>|C) for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>]. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11"/> is valid for any scheme with a single open state and a single closed&#x02013;open transition, provided the C&#x02013;O transition is rate limiting and the preceding C&#x02013;C transitions are equilibrated. Although <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11"/> contains a voltage-dependent contribution from closed-state equilibria (<italic>P</italic>C<sub>L</sub>), at extreme voltages, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) depends only on the rate-limiting step. For example, at negative voltages where <italic>P</italic>C<sub>L</sub> is small, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = 1/&#x003b3;, at positive voltages where <italic>P</italic>C<sub>L</sub> = 1 and &#x003b4; &#x0003e;&#x0003e; &#x003b3;, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = 1/&#x003b4;. Even if <italic>P</italic>C<sub>L</sub> fails to achieve limiting values of 0 or 1, the voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) at extreme voltages should reflect only the voltage dependence of &#x003b4; or &#x003b3;, provided <italic>P</italic>C<sub>L</sub> is relatively constant.</p><p>The voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) was examined in an experiment illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>. I<sub>K</sub> was activated by stepping from a holding potential of &#x02212;80 mV to voltages between +100 and +240 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> A). I<sub>K</sub> tail currents were recorded at more negative voltages, following a 50-ms depolarization to +120 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, B&#x02013;D). In all cases, the time course of I<sub>K</sub> was well fit by an exponential function after a brief delay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, solid lines). &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) is plotted from +30 to +240 mV in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> A and exhibits a bell-shaped voltage dependence that can be fit by a two-state model (solid curve) (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). This behavior also appears consistent with the prediction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> because &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) increases exponentially with voltage from +30 to +110 mV and decreases exponentially from +180 to +240 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> A, dashed lines) as if &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) is determined by single voltage-dependent rate constants at these voltages. However, our analysis of the delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation suggests that the voltage range in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> A is insufficient to observe the limiting voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>). The Cole-Moore shift (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> A) indicates that closed-state equilibria change from +40 to +120 mV, and the weak voltage dependence of the delay (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> C) suggests that these equilibria continue to change over a large voltage range.</p><p>To test the limiting behavior of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>), tail currents were measured at very negative voltages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. D</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> B plots &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) for the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> down to &#x02212;360 mV and, in other experiments, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) was measured at voltages as low as &#x02212;500 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> C). Tail currents were always well fit by exponential functions, but the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship at negative voltages departs from that observed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> A. For V &#x0003c; +30 mV, the slope of the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship decreases and achieves an exponential voltage dependence of only e-fold per 170 mV (0.14 <italic>e</italic> equivalent charge) from &#x02212;360 to &#x02212;40 mV. Fits to &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> B define three regions of exponential voltage dependence, characterized by mean equivalent charges of +0.143 <italic>e</italic> &#x000b1; 0.003, +0.49 <italic>e</italic> &#x000b1; 0.02, and &#x02212;0.29 <italic>e</italic> &#x000b1; 0.02 (mean &#x000b1; SEM, <italic>n</italic> = 5) over voltage ranges of &#x02212;500 to &#x02212;20 mV, +30 to +140 mV, and +180 to +280 mV, respectively.</p><p>A similar voltage dependence is observed at 20&#x000b0; and 5&#x000b0;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> C). The individual plots were normalized to the average time constants measured at &#x02212;80 mV for 5&#x000b0;C (0.95 &#x000b1; 0.04 ms, <italic>n</italic> = 6) or 20&#x000b0;C (0.172 &#x000b1; 0.015 ms, <italic>n</italic> = 6). The increase in temperature speeds I<sub>K</sub> relaxation 5.5-fold at all voltages (Q<sub>10</sub> = 3.1) such that the shape of the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V is essentially unchanged. This also demonstrates that measurements of the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship at negative voltages at 5&#x000b0;C are not limited by our ability to resolve fast tail currents. Nor is the limiting voltage dependence affected by series resistance error because tail current amplitudes saturate at voltages less than &#x02212;150 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> D). In this experiment, the tail current amplitude was &#x0003c;5 nA at even the most negative voltages, the electrode resistance was 1 M&#x003a9;, and the series resistance error was &#x0223c;5 mV or less and constant from &#x02212;150 to &#x02212;360 mV.</p><p>The &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship at negative voltages is likely to represent the limiting behavior of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) since no deviation from exponential voltage dependence was observed down to &#x02212;500 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> C). Unfortunately, the voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) could not be tested at very positive voltages. Recordings of I<sub>K</sub> at extreme negative voltages were possible because tail currents decayed rapidly and the time spent at these voltages could therefore be minimized (e.g., 0.5 ms at &#x02212;500 mV). Measuring the slower time course of I<sub>K</sub> activation required longer voltage pulses (&#x02265;10 ms, 5&#x000b0;C), which tends to compromise patch stability above +300 mV. Shorter pulses can be used at 20&#x000b0;C because activation is faster, but higher temperatures also tended to reduce patch stability and thereby offset the benefit of reduced pulse duration.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> predicts that &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) should achieve a limiting exponential voltage dependence, but the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship is inconsistent with this model. According to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = 1/&#x003b3; at negative voltages, and the exponential relationship defined by &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V between &#x02212;360 and &#x02212;40 mV in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> B (&#x003c4;<sub>Lim(</sub>&#x02212;<sub>)</sub>) should represent 1/&#x003b3;. However, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> also requires that &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) satisfy the inequality &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) &#x02264; 1/&#x003b3; at all voltages because (&#x003b4; <italic>P</italic>C<sub>L</sub> + &#x003b3;) &#x02265; &#x003b3; (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD11"/>). The data clearly do not meet this condition because &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) measured from +10 to +230 mV is up to fivefold greater than &#x003c4;<sub>Lim(</sub>&#x02212;<sub>)</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> B).</p><p>The complex voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) could be accounted for by a sequential gating scheme that, unlike <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, contains multiple rate-limiting transitions. In general, the relaxation of any system of <italic>n</italic> states will be multiexponential with <italic>n</italic> &#x02212; 1 characteristic time constants. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, all but one of these time constants is fast and relaxes during the delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation. The remaining slow time constant, reflecting the C&#x02013;O transition, dominates the time course of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation, and the voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) exhibits two regions of exponential voltage dependence associated with the forward and backward rate constants for this transition. If additional transitions in the activation pathway were slow, then they could also limit the time course of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation over some voltage range, possibly contributing additional regions of exponential voltage dependence to the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship.</p><p>A sequential scheme containing multiple rate limiting transitions cannot be ruled out based on the data presented thus far. However such a model is difficult to reconcile with the observation that I<sub>K</sub> relaxes with a predominantly single exponential time course at all voltages. The problem can be illustrated by attempting to fit the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V with a general sequential scheme containing a single open state (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S7">Fig. 7</xref>).</p><p>We will restrict our analysis to voltages less than +100 mV where steady state open probability is small (&#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>), and consider the case where channels begin in the open state (i.e., tail currents). For <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S7">Fig. 7</xref>, as for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) is determined at negative voltages by the rate of leaving O [&#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = &#x003c4;<sub>Lim(</sub>&#x02212;<sub>)</sub> = 1/&#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>]. Under what conditions will I<sub>K</sub> relax with &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) &#x0003e; 1/&#x003b2;<sub>n</sub>, as observed at more positive voltages? First, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) can differ from 1/&#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic> only when &#x003b1;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic> &#x0003e; 0. Moreover, &#x003b1;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic> must be large compared with &#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic> for I<sub>K</sub> to relax with an exponential time course. To see this, consider the relaxation of I<sub>K</sub> at +100 mV where &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) is approximately fourfold greater than &#x003c4;<sub>Lim(</sub>&#x02212;<sub>)</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> B). If I<sub>K</sub> is described by a single exponential function with &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = 4&#x003c4;<sub>Lim(</sub>&#x02212;<sub>)</sub> = 4/&#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>, then: <disp-formula id="FD12"><label>12</label><tex-math id="M14">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right = \left \left(\frac{-{\mathrm{{\beta}}}_{n}}{4}\right) \right {\mathrm{O}} \left \left(t\right) \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>When O(0) = 1, the initial rate of I<sub>K</sub> decay is given by O&#x02032;(0) = &#x02212;&#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>/4, but the general scheme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S7">Fig. 7</xref>) predicts a much faster initial decay O&#x02032;(0) = &#x02212;&#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>, as required by the expression: <disp-formula id="FD13"><label>13</label><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right ={\mathrm{{\alpha}}}_{n}{\mathrm{C}}_{n} \left \left(t\right) \right -{\mathrm{{\beta}}}_{n}{\mathrm{O}} \left \left(t\right) \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Hence there must exist a fast component of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation that is not evident in the data.</p><p>If the amplitude of the fast component is small, then, after it decays, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13"/> should be approximated by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12"/>. Equating <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD12"/> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD13"/> gives: <disp-formula id="FD14"><label>14</label><tex-math id="M16">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{{\alpha}}}_{n}=0.75\;{\mathrm{{\beta}}}_{n} \left \left[\frac{{\mathrm{O}} \left \left(t\right) \right }{{\mathrm{C}}_{n} \left \left(t\right) \right }\right] \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>If O(<italic>t</italic>) is still large after the fast component has decayed, then [O(<italic>t</italic>)/C<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>(<italic>t</italic>)] will be large, implying &#x003b1;<sub>n</sub> &#x0003e;&#x0003e; &#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>, and the final equilibrium constant for the C&#x02013;O transition will be large (&#x003b1;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>/&#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic> &#x0003e;&#x0003e; 1) even when <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is small (&#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>), which suggests that some other forward rate constant in the activation scheme is small at +100 mV. If &#x003b1;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic> &#x02212; <sub>1</sub> is very small when V &#x0003c; +100 mV, then <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S7">Fig. 7</xref> can be approximated by a three-state model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S8">Fig. 8</xref>), which can be solved exactly and is characterized by two time constants: &#x003c4;<sub>slow</sub> and &#x003c4;<sub>fast</sub>.</p><p>The dashed line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> C shows that this scheme can fit the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship at 5&#x000b0;C (for V &#x02264; +100 mV). Using the parameters in the figure legend, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) is equal to &#x003c4;<sub>slow</sub>, and &#x003c4;<sub>fast</sub> will be at least 4.5&#x000d7; smaller than &#x003c4;<sub>slow</sub>. Such a fast component would be observable if its amplitude were significant, but the amplitude of the fast component was adjusted to &#x0003c;20% of the total by requiring &#x003b1;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>/&#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic> to be large (&#x003b1;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>/&#x003b2;<italic><sub>n</sub></italic>= 2.1 at +100 mV). Thus the fast component can be made small, giving the appearance of a monoexponential decay.</p><p>That is, a general sequential scheme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S7">Fig. 7</xref>), whose final C to O transition is not rate limiting, can reproduce important features of the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship while maintaining a predominantly exponential relaxation time course. We can not exclude that a minor fast component of tail current relaxation exists. Furthermore, the requirement that the final C&#x02013;O transition is faster than some closed-state transitions is not in conflict with the observation of a brief delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SchoppaandSigworth1998a">Schoppa and Sigworth 1998a</xref>). However, mSlo gating currents described in the companion article (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>) activate without a detectable rising phase and decay rapidly compared with &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>), supporting the idea that the initial closed-state transitions are fast and voltage dependent. Furthermore, a large fraction of gating charge moves at voltages where the steady state <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is small, implying that intermediate closed states are occupied under these conditions. Thus, to account for both exponential I<sub>K</sub> kinetics and a low <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> at +100 mV, the general sequential scheme would require that an intermediate closed-state transition is slow. Such a model is difficult to describe in terms of only two molecular events: channel opening and subunit activation. However an alternative scheme, presented below, can be described in these simple molecular terms while accounting for the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship and generating exponential kinetics.</p></sec><sec><title>An Allosteric Model of Voltage-dependent Gating</title><p>Although the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship is inconsistent with <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, the data can be explained in terms of the conformational events outlined in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S4">Fig. 4</xref>. If mSlo channels can open even when one or more subunits are in the R conformation, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S4">Fig. 4</xref> can be represented by a 10-state gating scheme with 5 open and 5 closed states (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>), where each horizontal transition (C&#x02013;C or O&#x02013;O) represents a subunit conformational change, and vertical transitions represent channel opening.</p><p>As before, subscripts (0&#x02013;4) denote the number of activated subunits in each open and closed state. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> predicts that channels can open even if no subunits are activated (C<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>0</sub>). However, such an event should be rare because subunit activation is assumed to increase the probability of channel opening. This interaction is represented by a factor D. The equilibrium constants for the C&#x02013;O transitions increase D-fold for each subunit that is activated. As will be shown later, this requirement favors the possibility that channels will pass through several closed states before opening in response to a voltage step, consistent with the presence of a delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation. In addition, if the C&#x02013;O transitions are slow and rate limiting, while C&#x02013;C and O&#x02013;O transitions equilibrate rapidly, this model can account for I<sub>K</sub> kinetics that are essentially exponential after the delay at all voltages. At the same time, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> can reproduce the complex voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) because it contains multiple rate-limiting C&#x02013;O transitions that dominate I<sub>K</sub> relaxation over different voltage ranges. Both the individual and average &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationships in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. C</xref>, are well (solid curves) fit by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>. The observation that a change in temperature has little effect on the shape of the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> C) is also consistent with the idea that a single type of conformational change (C&#x02013;O transition) limits I<sub>K</sub> relaxation at all voltages.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> describes only the response of mSlo channels to voltage and contains no Ca<sup>2+</sup>-bound states; however, it clearly resembles <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref>, used earlier to describe the interaction of Ca<sup>2+</sup> with mSlo channels. Indeed these two models are strictly analogous. Like <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>), <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> assumes that channels undergo a central rate-limiting conformational change from closed to open, and this transition is allosterically regulated. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S1">Fig. 1</xref>, interaction of Ca<sup>2+</sup> with binding sites on each of the four subunits enhances channel opening. In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>, voltage-dependent conformational changes in each subunit influence channel opening.</p><p>An important prediction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> is that the limiting behavior of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) should reflect the voltage dependence of C&#x02013;O transitions. According to the model, horizontal transitions equilibrate rapidly and open channels tend to occupy the left-most state (O<sub>0</sub>) at negative voltages such that the time constant of I<sub>K</sub> deactivation is determined by the rate constant (&#x003b3;<sub>0</sub>) associated with the O<sub>0</sub> to C<sub>0</sub> transition [&#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = 1/&#x003b3;<sub>0</sub>]. The &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship measured at limiting negative voltages therefore determines the value of &#x003b3;<sub>0</sub> used in the model and implies that channel closing is weakly voltage dependent (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b3;0</sub> = 0.138 &#x000b1; 0.003 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>n</italic> = 11). For simplicity, we also assume for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> that all O to C transitions have the same voltage dependence.</p><p>The forward transitions from C to O also appear to be weakly voltage dependent. The rate constant from C<sub>4</sub> to O<sub>4</sub> can be determined by measuring the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship at limiting positive voltages, where &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = 1/&#x003b4;<sub>4</sub>. Simulations of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> suggest that this limiting behavior will be observed at voltages greater than +300 mV, which cannot be attained under our experimental conditions. Nonetheless, the voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V measured from +180 to +280 mV (<italic>z</italic> = 0.29 &#x000b1; 0.02 <italic>e</italic>) places an upper limit on the charge associated with channel opening (see <sc>discussion</sc>). We assign a charge <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub> = 0.26 <italic>e</italic> to the forward C&#x02013;O transitions in the model, giving a total charge of <italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub> = 0.40 <italic>e</italic> for the C&#x02013;O equilibrium (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub> = <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub>+ <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b3;</sub>). This value of <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub> provided reasonable fits to the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationships (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>), and the resultant value of <italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub> is also consistent with the voltage dependence of steady state open probability discussed later.</p><p>If the C&#x02013;O transitions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> are weakly voltage dependent, then the horizontal transitions involving subunit activation must account for the bulk of the channel's voltage sensitivity. To account for the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship, the Cole-Moore effect, and the voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>, we have assigned a charge <italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> = 0.55 <italic>e</italic> and half activation voltage V<sub>h</sub>(J) = +145 mV to the equilibrium constant for subunit activation: <disp-formula><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{J}}=e^{ \left \left({\mathrm{V}}-{\mathrm{V}}_{{\mathrm{h}}}\right) \right \frac{ez_{{\mathrm{J}}}}{kT}}{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Thus, a total charge of 4<italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> = 2.2 <italic>e</italic> should be associated with the horizontal transitions, and <italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub> = 0.4 <italic>e</italic>, or 15% of the estimated total charge (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>T</sub> = <italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub> + 4<italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> = 2.6 <italic>e</italic>), is associated with channel opening.</p><p>From a mechanistic standpoint, the assignment of most of the charge to the horizontal transitions in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> implies that subunit activation involves movement of the channel's intrinsic voltage sensor. Thus <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> not only divides mSlo activation into fast and slow transitions, but also separates voltage-sensor movement from channel opening. In other words, the model suggests that voltage-sensor activation and channel opening represent distinct conformational events that are allosterically coupled.</p></sec><sec><title>The Voltage Dependence of Steady State Activation</title><p>The conductance&#x02013;voltage (G<sub>K</sub>&#x02013;V) relationship was measured in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> (at 20&#x000b0;C) using both macroscopic and single channel currents to examine steady state activation over a wide range of voltage and open probability (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> A shows a family of macroscopic I<sub>K</sub> evoked in response to 20-ms pulses to different voltages. Steady state conductance (G<sub>K</sub>) was determined from tail current amplitudes, normalized to maximal conductance (G<sub>max</sub>), and plotted against voltage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. C</xref>). Data from many individual experiments are plotted (&#x025cb;). To compensate for patch-to-patch variation in half-activation voltage, individual plots were shifted along the voltage axis to align them with the mean V<sub>h</sub> (190 &#x000b1; 2.3 mV; SEM, <italic>n</italic> = 20) (see <sc>methods</sc>). These shifted data were then combined in 15-mV bins to determine the average G&#x02013;V (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. C</xref>, &#x02022;).</p><p>The predictions of sequential <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> and the allosteric <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> are superimposed on the data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> B (dashed lines) and are essentially indistinguishable from each other over this voltage range. The G&#x02013;V can also be well fit by a Boltzmann function that is raised to a power of 3.2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. C</xref>, solid line) (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). Many sequential models like <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> predict a G&#x02013;V relationship that can be approximated by a Boltzmann function raised to power &#x0003e;1 (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="WymanandGill1990">Wyman and Gill 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Zagottaetal1994b">Zagotta et al. 1994b</xref>). Such Boltzmann-like functions achieve a maximal limiting voltage dependence at negative voltages. The semi-log plot in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> C demonstrates that the data are consistent with a such a relationship over a large range of open probability, and appear to achieve a limiting logarithmic slope of e-fold per 12.6 mV (<italic>z</italic> = 2 <italic>e)</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> C, dashed line). However, while this slope does indicate the maximum voltage dependence of the mSlo G&#x02013;V, it does not represent the limiting voltage dependence. Measurements of channel activity at more negative voltages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> D) reveal a marked decrease in the voltage dependence of steady state activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> E), which deviates from a Boltzmann-like G&#x02013;V relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F) and provides evidence for the presence of multiple open states.</p><p>The data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> D were recorded at +80 and &#x02212;80 mV from a macropatch containing several hundred mSlo channels. At these voltages, where <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is small (&#x0003c;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>), single channel openings are observed. Allpoint amplitude histograms like those in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> D were constructed by recording such events for 5&#x02013;45 s and were used to evaluate total open probability at each voltage (V &#x02264; +80 mV) (see <sc>methods</sc>). These data were then normalized based on macroscopic currents recorded in the same patch to determine normalized open probability (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>P</italic>
<sub>omax</sub>), which is plotted against voltage in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> E.</p><p>The normalized <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> E were obtained from several experiments in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> or 4.5 &#x003bc;M Ca<sup>2+</sup>. <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>P</italic>
<sub>omax</sub> at +80 mV in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> are comparable with those measured from macroscopic currents at the same voltage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> C). Similarly, the voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> from +20 to +80 mV is comparable with the maximal slope of the macroscopic G&#x02013;V, indicated by a dashed line in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> E. However, a decrease in the slope of the <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship is observed at more negative voltages both in the presence and absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>. That is, <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> at negative voltages is greater than predicted from the Boltzmann-like fit to the macroscopic G&#x02013;V. This deviation cannot be due to a failure to detect brief openings, since missed events should be more prominent at negative voltages and lead to an underestimate of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>. Furthermore, the shape of the normalized <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship is similar in the presence or absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> despite the fact that Ca<sup>2+</sup> increases the mean open time (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MaglebyandPallotta1983b">Magleby and Pallotta 1983b</xref>).</p><p>The normalized <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships obtained from many experiments in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> are plotted on a semi-log scale in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F for voltages from &#x02212;120 to +300 mV. Filled symbols indicate averages (mean &#x000b1; SEM, 15-mV bin width) while open symbols represent data from individual experiments. The data from single channel activity (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>P</italic>
<sub>omax</sub> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>) are continuous with the macroscopic data and are weakly voltage dependent at negative voltages where <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>P</italic>
<sub>omax</sub> = 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>&#x02013;10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>. The prediction of sequential <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> is superimposed on the plot (dashed line), the data deviates from this Boltzmann-like relationship for <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>P</italic>
<sub>omax</sub> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>. The allosteric model, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> provides an excellent fit (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F, solid line) over the entire voltage range using the same parameters that describe the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>.</p><p>The decrease in voltage dependence of steady state activation observed at low <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> could be caused by a small subpopulation of malformed mSlo channels or endogenous channels that fail to close in a normal voltage-dependent manner. However, several lines of evidence argue that the weak voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> represents the behavior of normal mSlo channels. First, the normalized <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships recorded from different experiments are similar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> E) and are therefore unlikely to represent a variable mixture of channel types. Second, the large amplitude of single channel events measured at negative voltages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> D) clearly identify them as mSlo channel currents. Third, <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitive even at potentials where the voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is weak (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> E). Fourth, the relative probability of observing multichannel openings was well described by a Poisson distribution (data not shown), consistent with the presence of a large uniform population of channels with low <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>, rather than a small subpopulation of malformed channels with high <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>. Finally, although the number of events collected were insufficient to analyze the single channel kinetics in detail, open times observed at &#x02212;80 mV in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> were very brief (95% were &#x0003c;160 &#x003bc;s, measured with a 50% amplitude criterion), consistent with the observation that macroscopic I<sub>K</sub> deactivation is very fast at the same voltage [mean &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = 172 &#x003bc;s at 20&#x000b0;C].</p><p>The complex voltage dependence of steady state activation provides support for the conclusions that mSlo voltage gating involves multiple open states and that the C&#x02013;O transitions are weakly voltage dependent. The limiting voltage dependence of mSlo indicates that a weakly voltage-dependent pathway exists between the resting closed state and an open state even though channel opening at more positive voltages proceeds through one or more voltage-dependent routes. Thus the &#x0201c;limiting slope&#x0201d; of the G&#x02013;V relationship cannot be used as an estimate of total gating charge for BK channels. This behavior can be explained by models like <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>, where multiple voltage-dependent pathways exist between closed and open states. According to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>: <disp-formula id="FD15"><label>15</label><tex-math id="M18">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}P_{{\mathrm{o}}}=\frac{1}{1+\displaystyle\frac{ \left \left(1+J\right) \right ^{4}}{{\mathit{L}} \left \left(1+{\mathit{DJ}}\right) \right ^{4}}}{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>At negative voltages, where <italic>J</italic> is small (<italic>J</italic> &#x0003c;&#x0003c; 1/<italic>D</italic>), this reduces to <disp-formula id="FD16"><label>16</label><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}P_{{\mathrm{o}}}=\frac{{\mathit{L}}}{1+{\mathit{L}}}{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> if <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is also small (L &#x0003c;&#x0003c; 1): <disp-formula id="FD17"><label>17</label><tex-math id="M20">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}P_{{\mathrm{o}}}={\mathit{L}}{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Thus, at negative voltages, <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is determined by the C<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>0</sub> equilibrium constant (<italic>L</italic>). That <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is weakly voltage dependent is consistent with the notion that C&#x02013;O transitions are weakly voltage dependent. The fit of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> to the average data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F suggests that this limiting behavior of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> was obtained, and the value of <italic>L</italic> used in the model (2*10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>) is constrained by <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> at negative voltages. However, the limiting voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> was not measured over a large enough voltage range to directly determine the voltage dependence of <italic>L</italic>. Therefore <italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub> was adjusted to provide a reasonable fit to the overall shape of the <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V and &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationships, as well as the limiting behavior of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>.</p></sec><sec><title>Reproducing &#x0201c;Sequential&#x0201d; Behavior with the Allosteric Gating Scheme</title><p>At negative voltages, both the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V and <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relations are weakly voltage dependent, consistent with the hypothesis that mSlo channels can open and close in a manner that does not involve voltage-sensor movement. We also have described features of mSlo behavior that can be described by a more conventional sequential gating scheme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>) (e.g., the kinetics and voltage dependence of the delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation) and the ability of the macroscopic G&#x02013;V to be approximated by a Boltzmann function raised to a power greater than one over a large range of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>. The allosteric model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>) also can account for these latter results.</p><p>The <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship predicted by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F, Scheme IIb) is almost indistinguishable from that predicted by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> for <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> &#x0003e; 10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>. To reproduce this behavior, the allosteric factor (<italic>D</italic>) in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> must be large. If <italic>D</italic> is large, channel opening at positive voltages most likely will occur only after all four voltage sensors have been activated, and the allosteric model then behaves much like a sequential scheme. The value of <italic>D</italic> (17) used in the model was also constrained by the overall shape of the <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship. At very negative voltages, <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is determined by the C<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>o</sub> equilibrium constant <italic>L</italic>; at positive voltages, the C<sub>4</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>4</sub> equilibrium constant (<italic>LD</italic>
<sup>4</sup>) becomes more important. Thus, the value of <italic>D</italic> is critical in determining the relative magnitude of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> at negative and positive voltages. The half-activation voltage of the G&#x02013;V [V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>)] also depends upon <italic>D</italic>, as well as the equilibrium constants <italic>L</italic> and <italic>J</italic>. <italic>L</italic> is fixed by the limiting value of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> at negative voltages, <italic>J</italic> is constrained by the voltage dependence of the delay in I<sub>K</sub> (see below), and there is little freedom to adjust <italic>D</italic> without producing unacceptable changes in V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>).</p><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref> show that <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> can fit the kinetics of I<sub>K</sub> activation, using the same parameters that reproduce the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V and <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships. These fits were critical in constraining the model parameters associated with the horizontal transitions, corresponding to voltage-sensor activation.</p><p>The results presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> show that mSlo I<sub>K</sub> activates with a brief delay and that these kinetics can be approximated by a sequential model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>) that contains fast voltage-dependent transitions followed by a rate-limiting opening step. However the time course of I&#x02032;<sub>K</sub> was not precisely reproduced by the sequential scheme unless voltage sensors were assumed to interact in a cooperative manner (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref>). The allosteric model can account for these kinetics while assuming voltage sensors act independently. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> shows that <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> reproduces the time course and delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>, A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>2</sub>) as well as I&#x02032;<sub>K</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> B) at +180 mV, and the Cole-Moore shift (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> C).</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>, the delay duration (&#x00394;<italic>t</italic>) is influenced by the time constant associated with voltage-sensor activation while the channel is closed [&#x003c4;<sub>J</sub> = 1/(&#x003b1; + &#x003b2;)] and therefore constrains the rate constants associated with C&#x02013;C transitions. The equilibrium constant <italic>J</italic> and charge <italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> associated with voltage-sensor activation are mainly constrained by the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V and <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref> A shows that the allosteric scheme reproduces the initial time course of I<sub>K</sub> activation, and therefore the delay, at different voltages. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref> B compares the average &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V data to the predicted &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> (solid line) and &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub> (dashed line). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> predicts that the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V and &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>&#x02013;V relationships will be similar in shape but, in contrast to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>, their maxima will not be at the same voltage [V<sub>max</sub>(&#x00394;<italic>t</italic>) = 153 mV, V<sub>max</sub>(&#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>) = 145 mV]. This small difference, representing a voltage-dependent change in the relationship between &#x00394;t and &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>, reflects the ability of channels to open before all four voltage sensors are activated. The &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship was measured mainly at voltages more positive than V<sub>max</sub>(&#x00394;<italic>t</italic>), and therefore constrains the charge associated with voltage-sensor activation (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;</sub>) more tightly than that associated with deactivation (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>). For simplicity, &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V was fit with the assumption that &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub> is symmetrically voltage dependent, yielding <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> = &#x02212;<italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> = 0.275 <italic>e</italic>. Although the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V data do not require symmetry, values of <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> and <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> close to these estimates are necessary to assign a reasonable total charge [<italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> = (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> + <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;</sub>) = 0.55 <italic>e</italic>] to voltage-sensor activation. <italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> is constrained by the fit to the <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F) and is consistent with the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5B</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. C</xref>) and Cole-Moore shift (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref> C). The accompanying paper shows that this estimate of <italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub> is also consistent with gating current measurements (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Delay in I<sub>K</sub> Deactivation</title><p>One feature of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> that distinguishes it from models with a single open state is that it predicts a delay in I<sub>K</sub> deactivation because channels can pass through several open states before closing. Tail currents in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> C exhibit a slight delay, which is evident as a deviation from an exponential fit during the first 200 &#x003bc;s after a voltage pulse. Even at 5&#x000b0;C, this delay is brief and could be influenced by filter properties or series-resistance error. However, tail currents at more negative voltages in the same patch (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> D) did not show such a deviation from exponential decay, suggesting that the tail current delay is not an artifact. The allosteric model reproduces these tail current kinetics, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref> C. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref> D compares tail currents and simulations at &#x02212;40 and &#x02212;360 mV. The data and prediction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (solid lines) deviate from an exponential time course (dashed lines) at &#x02212;40 but not &#x02212;360 mV. The delay disappears at very negative voltages because the time constant associated with open-state transitions, representing voltage-sensor deactivation, decreases at negative voltages. It should be noted that, according to the allosteric model, the equilibrium constants for open-state transitions differ from those for closed state transitions by a factor <italic>D</italic>. Thus, open- and closed-state transitions are expected to be characterized by different time constants. We expressed this difference as an increase in the forward O&#x02013;O rate constants by <italic>D</italic> and a decrease in the backward rates by the same factor relative to the corresponding C&#x02013;C transitions.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Discussion</title><p>We have studied mSlo channel currents at very low [Ca<sup>2+</sup>]<sub>i</sub> to elucidate the mechanism of voltage-dependent gating. This procedure limits the number of accessible conformations to those without Ca<sup>2+</sup> bound. To a first approximation, the voltage response of mSlo channels appears simpler than that of many voltage-sensitive channels and can reasonably be described by a two-state gating scheme (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). For example, the time course of macroscopic I<sub>K</sub> activation is well fit by an exponential function after a brief delay, and the time constant of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation is much slower than the delay. At voltages where steady state <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is significant (&#x0003e;10<sup>&#x02212;3</sup>), the kinetics of both activation and deactivation exhibit an exponential voltage dependence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> A) consistent with the presence of voltage-dependent forward and backward transitions between a closed and an open state. Finally, when estimates of equivalent charge associated with these transitions are summed, they are similar to that obtained by fitting the steady state G<sub>K</sub>&#x02013;V relationship with a Boltzmann function (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>).</p><p>These characteristics of mSlo gating appear simple and self-consistent, but closer examination of I<sub>K</sub> kinetics and voltage dependence over a wider range of conditions reveals deviations from two-state behavior that imply a surprisingly complex underlying gating mechanism. An important conclusion of this study is that mSlo channel opening and voltage-sensor activation reflect distinct conformational events that occur on different time scales but are allosterically coupled. Based on the assumption that the channel has a voltage sensor in each of four identical subunits, this mechanism results in a 10-state gating scheme with five open and five closed states arranged in parallel. In this allosteric model, transitions among closed (C&#x02013;C) or open (O&#x02013;O) states are governed by rapid voltage sensor movements, while closed&#x02013;open (C&#x02013;O) transitions are weakly voltage dependent and rate limiting. Because voltage-sensor activation is assumed to be much faster than channel opening, this scheme predicts exponential relaxation kinetics and other &#x0201c;simple&#x0201d; behaviors that can be approximated by a two-state model or a sequential gating scheme. However, these properties change with voltage in a manner that reflects the complexity of the underlying mechanism. In particular, the kinetic and steady state properties of I<sub>K</sub> activation become weakly voltage dependent at negative voltages, suggesting that channel opening can occur in the absence of voltage-sensor activation.</p><p>The allosteric model of mSlo voltage gating has implications for understanding BK channel activation and voltage-dependent channel gating in general. First, the model establishes a framework for evaluating the effects of mutation on voltage-dependent BK channel gating. Second, the scheme forms a basis for understanding the effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on BK channel gating. The demonstrated complexity of mSlo voltage gating in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> greatly increases the minimum complexity of models that include Ca<sup>2+</sup>-bound states. The voltage-gating mechanism also raises the fundamental question whether Ca<sup>2+</sup> acts by modulating voltage-sensor movement, channel opening, or some combination of both of these processes. Finally, the allosteric scheme may apply to other voltage-dependent channels. The following discussion considers these implications of the model in detail.</p><sec><title>Allosteric Voltage Gating and the Effect of S4 Mutation</title><p>The allosteric gating scheme has implications for interpreting BK channel structure&#x02013;function studies because some apparently simple features of macroscopic I<sub>K</sub> kinetics and voltage dependence may be related in a complicated manner to elementary molecular events such as voltage-sensor movement and channel opening. This is illustrated by the example in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>.</p><p>Neutralization of a charged residue in the S4 segment of mSlo (R207Q) produces a marked decrease in the steepness of the G&#x02013;V relationship and a shift of almost &#x02212;100 mV in the half-activation voltage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref> A) (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Diazetal1998">Diaz et al. 1998</xref>; Cui, J., and R.W. Aldrich, manuscript in preparation). The S4 segment is thought to form part of the voltage sensor in voltage-gated channels and a reasonable hypothesis is that the mutation reduces the charge associated with voltage-sensor movement, thereby reducing the voltage dependence of channel activation. If mSlo channel voltage gating could be described by a two-state model, a decrease in gating charge would be required to account for a change in the steepness of the G&#x02013;V. However, the allosteric model suggests a different explanation.</p><p>The wild-type (WT) G&#x02013;V in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref> A was fitted by allosteric <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (solid line) using the same parameters as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F. The R207Q G&#x02013;V was then fit (solid line) by changing the half-activation voltage for the voltage sensor [V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>)] from +145 to &#x02212;100 mV and leaving all other parameters the same as for the WT. That is, the effect of the S4 mutation can be accounted for by increasing the equilibrium constant <italic>J</italic> 207-fold (&#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic> = 5.33 <italic>kT</italic>) without changing the voltage sensor charge (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub>), the allosteric factor (<italic>D</italic>), the C&#x02013;O equilibrium constant (<italic>L</italic>), or the charge associated with channel opening (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub>).</p><p>According to the allosteric model, the shape of the G&#x02013;V for R207Q mainly reflects the charge associated with the C<sub>4</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>4</sub> transition (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub>) because the voltage sensors are largely activated at voltages where <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is small. Thus the WT G&#x02013;V is steeper because voltage-sensor activation and channel opening occur over the same voltage range. To test this conclusion, R207Q activation was examined at low <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref> B). The voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> for the mutant increases at negative voltages to a maximum slope like that exhibited by the WT (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Diazetal1998">Diaz et al. 1998</xref>). This behavior is reproduced by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>, solid lines), reflecting the ability of mutant voltage sensors to become deactivated at negative voltages, and consistent with the idea that the total gating charge for the two channels are similar. Gating charge measurements for WT and mutant channels in the companion article (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>) support this conclusion.</p></sec><sec><title>Allosteric Voltage Gating and the Voltage Dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)</title><p>The voltage dependence of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation kinetics is another feature of mSlo gating that illustrates a complex relationship between molecular events and macroscopic behavior. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> C and previously reported by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>, the time constant of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation exhibits a bell-shaped voltage dependence over a 250-mV voltage range centered near the half-activation voltage for mSlo. The two regions of exponential voltage dependence might reasonably be interpreted as representing the voltage dependencies of rate limiting forward and backward transitions between single closed and open states. However, the allosteric scheme suggests that this apparently simple voltage dependence is an emergent feature of all transitions in the model and cannot be attributed to properties of individual rate constants.</p><p>According to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>, the horizontal C&#x02013;C and O&#x02013;O transitions will be so fast that they do not affect &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>). This point was confirmed in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref> A by showing that the values of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) measured from I<sub>K</sub> simulations (symbols) can be reproduced by an analytical approximation of the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship (solid line) that assumes horizontal transitions are equilibrated: <disp-formula id="FD18"><label>18</label><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{{\tau}}} \left \left({\mathrm{I}}_{{\mathrm{K}}}\right) \right = \left \left[{{\sum_{{\mathrm{i}}}}} \left \left({\mathrm{{\delta}}}_{{\mathrm{i}}}p{\mathrm{C}}_{{\mathrm{i}}}+{\mathrm{{\gamma}}}_{{\mathrm{i}}}p{\mathrm{O}}_{{\mathrm{i}}}\right) \right \right] \right ^{-1}{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> where &#x003b4;<sub>i</sub> and &#x003b3;<sub>i</sub> are rate constants for the C<sub>i</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>i</sub> transitions and <italic>p</italic>C<sub>i</sub> and <italic>p</italic>O<sub>i</sub> are conditional occupancies of the open and closed states [<italic>p</italic>C<sub>i</sub> = <italic>p</italic>(C<sub>i</sub>|C) and <italic>p</italic>O<sub>i</sub> = <italic>p</italic>(O<sub>i</sub>|O)].</p><p>The shape of the &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship can to some extent be explained by comparing it to the time constants of the individual C&#x02013;O transitions in the model [&#x003c4;<sub>i</sub> = (&#x003b4;<sub>i</sub> + &#x003b3;<sub>i</sub>)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref> A, &#x003c4;<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;&#x003c4;<sub>4</sub>, dashed lines). At limiting negative voltages, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) is determined by the time constant of the C<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>0</sub> transition (&#x003c4;<sub>0</sub>) and at positive voltages by the C<sub>4</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>4</sub> transition (&#x003c4;<sub>4</sub>). At intermediate voltages, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) represents a weighted sum of the rate constants for all C&#x02013;O transitions (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD18"/>), where the relative weighting depends on the equilibrium distributions of different closed and open states [<italic>p</italic>C<sub>i</sub>(V) and <italic>p</italic>O<sub>i</sub>(V)]. The time constants of individual C&#x02013;O transitions (&#x003c4;<sub>i</sub>) provide a rough indication of the range spanned by &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) at intermediate voltages. However, &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) measured from +30 to +240 mV in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> C reflects the voltage dependence of the horizontal equilibria in the model as well as the kinetics of the different C&#x02013;O transitions, and cannot be attributed to a particular rate-limiting step. Thus, the exponential voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) at intermediate voltages is coincidental and does not represent the voltage dependence of any one rate constant [although &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) can not be attributed to single rate constants, the rate-limiting transition always represent the C&#x02013;O conformational change].</p><p>The simulation in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref> A predicts that &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) will achieve a limiting voltage dependence, representing the charge associated with the C<sub>4</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>4</sub> transition (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub>), at voltages (&#x0003e;300 mV) that exceed our experimental range. Therefore, we used the exponential voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) between +180 and +280 mV (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>(180&#x02013;280)</sub> = 0.29 <italic>e</italic>) as an upper limit for <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub>. For parameters that describe our data, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> always predicted <italic>z</italic>
<sub>(180&#x02013;280)</sub> &#x02265; <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub>. This is not a general property of the model, however.</p><p>The allosteric model requires that the equilibrium constant for C&#x02013;O transitions increase <italic>D</italic>-fold for each voltage sensor that is activated. The forward and backward rate constants are not otherwise constrained. &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationships in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> were fit with the additional assumption that forward rates increase and backward rates decrease monotonically with each voltage sensor activated. A conclusion of this analysis is that voltage-sensor activation affects mainly the forward rate constants. Fits to the 5&#x000b0; or 20&#x000b0;C data in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> C required that the forward rates increase 11,500- or 6,700-fold when all four voltage sensors are activated, whereas the backward rates decrease only 7.3- or 12.5-fold, respectively. Indeed, the backward rates for the first three C&#x02013;O transitions were assumed to be identical such that &#x003c4;<sub>0</sub>, &#x003c4;<sub>1</sub>, and &#x003c4;<sub>2</sub> are identical at negative voltages as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref> A. This result suggests that voltage-sensor activation may destabilize the closed conformation with little effect on the free energy of the open conformation or the transition barrier between O and C.</p></sec><sec><title>Allosteric Versus Sequential Gating Schemes</title><p>An important feature of the mSlo data that is reproduced by the allosteric model is that many kinetic and steady state properties of I<sub>K</sub> can be approximated by a sequential gating scheme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>), except at extreme voltages. This is significant because many voltage-gated channels have been described by sequential models analogous to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>; it is possible that such channels also operate through an allosteric mechanism, but have not been studied under conditions that reveal such a mechanism.</p><p>The distinction between allosteric and sequential schemes is important because the models make different predictions concerning the possible molecular events that link voltage-sensor movement to channel opening (discussed below). In addition, the allosteric scheme provides a simple explanation for cooperative interaction of voltage-sensors in voltage-dependent gating. Many channels exhibit behaviors that deviate from the predictions of completely independent schemes such as the Hodgkin&#x02013;Huxley model (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HodgkinandHuxley1952">Hodgkin and Huxley 1952</xref>). Such results can be described by gating schemes in which the voltage sensors interact in a cooperative manner such that the activation of one affects the movement of the others (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="VandenbergandBezanilla1991">Vandenberg and Bezanilla 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Perozoetal1992">Perozo et al. 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="TytgatandHess1992">Tytgat and Hess 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Zagottaetal1994a">Zagotta et al. 1994a</xref>). We have used such a model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref>) to fit the delay in mSlo I<sub>K</sub> activation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref> implies that there is direct communication between voltage sensors in different subunits. The allosteric model (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>) can account for the delay kinetics, as well as other features that are not reproduced by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref>, using the simpler assumption that voltage sensors act independently while the channel is either closed or open. Cooperativity is embodied in the allosteric transition between these two conformations, a mechanism of subunit&#x02013;subunit communication that is known to exist in many proteins (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Perutz1989">Perutz 1989</xref>).</p><p>Given the ability of allosteric and sequential models to act similarly, it is important to define the conditions that allow them to be distinguished. The ability of the allosteric model to act like a sequential scheme was illustrated by the comparison of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F. The two predictions deviate significantly from each other only when <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is very small (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>); the two models cannot be distinguished based on conventional G&#x02013;V measurements. The allosteric model for mSlo behaves like a sequential scheme because the allosteric factor is large (<italic>D</italic> = 17), such that the equilibrium constant for the C&#x02013;O transition increases by a factor of 83,000 (<italic>D</italic>
<sup>4</sup>) when all voltage sensors are in the activated state. Channel opening is most likely to occur after all voltage sensors have been activated, as in a sequential scheme.</p><p>The conditions under which <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> converge can be defined by comparing the expression for <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD15"/>) with that for a version of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> (see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD19"/>), where the C<sub>4</sub>&#x02212;O<sub>4</sub> transition is assigned an equilibrium constant of <italic>LD</italic>
<sup>4</sup>, equivalent to the C<sub>4</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>4</sub> transition in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>.</p><p>
<disp-formula id="FD19"><label>19</label><tex-math id="M22">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}P_{{\mathrm{o}}}=\frac{1}{1+\displaystyle\frac{ \left \left(1+J\right) \right ^{4}}{L \left \left(DJ\right) \right ^{4}}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD15"/> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD19"/> are equivalent when <italic>DJ</italic> is large (&#x0003e;&#x0003e;1), so we can define a value of <italic>J</italic> (<italic>J</italic>
<sub>eq</sub>) such that <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> behave equivalently when <italic>J</italic> &#x02265; <italic>J</italic>
<sub>eq</sub>: <disp-formula id="FD20"><label>20</label><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}J_{{\mathrm{eq}}}{\gg}{1}/{D}{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>The value of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> where these two models converge (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>eq</sub>) is obtained by substituting <italic>J</italic>
<sub>eq</sub> into <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD19"/>: <disp-formula id="FD21"><label>21</label><tex-math id="M24">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}P_{{\mathrm{eq}}}=\frac{1}{1+\displaystyle\frac{ \left \left(1+J_{{\mathrm{eq}}}\right) \right ^{4}}{LD^{4} \left \left(J_{{\mathrm{eq}}}\right) \right ^{4}}}{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>For constant <italic>LD</italic>
<sup>4</sup>, <italic>P</italic>
<sub>eq</sub> will decrease when <italic>J</italic>
<sub>eq</sub> decreases (when <italic>D</italic> increases). For large <italic>D</italic>s, it is necessary to measure small <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> to observe a divergence between the predictions of the allosteric and sequential models. This is illustrated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref> B, which compares <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships predicted by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> for different values of <italic>D</italic> (5&#x02013;160). As <italic>D</italic> is increased, the predictions of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (solid lines) become increasingly difficult to distinguish from that of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref> B, dashed line).</p></sec><sec><title>Detection of Allosteric Voltage-gating Behavior</title><p>It is quite possible that a channel that activates through an allosteric voltage-gating mechanism mistakenly could be described by a sequential model if the allosteric factor (<italic>D</italic>) is large. The mSlo data was fit with <italic>D</italic> = 17, indicating that each activated voltage sensor changes the free energy difference between closed and open conformations by &#x00394;&#x00394;<italic>G</italic>
<sub>co</sub> = ln(<italic>D</italic>) = 2.83 <italic>kT</italic>. If this interaction energy were increased by only 55% such that <italic>D</italic> = 80, measurements at <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> &#x0003c; 10<sup>&#x02212;8</sup> would be required before deviations from a sequential scheme could be detected (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F10">Fig. 10</xref> B).</p><p>Additional factors could serve to prevent identification of an allosteric mechanism. Deviations from sequential gating behavior were only clearly demonstrated for mSlo by studying ionic currents at extreme negative voltages and very low <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>, where the voltage sensors are presumed to be in a resting state such that the kinetic and steady state properties of I<sub>K</sub> are determined by the C<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>0</sub> transition. In the case of mSlo, the equilibrium constant for this transition (<italic>L</italic>) is large enough that <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> can be measured when voltage sensors are not activated. Similarly, the kinetics and weak voltage dependence of the O<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>0</sub> transition allow us to resolve tail current kinetics at voltages as low as &#x02212;500 mV. In channels where the O<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;C<sub>0</sub> transition is faster or its equilibrium constant smaller than that of mSlo, measurement of ionic current properties may be impractical under conditions that distinguish allosteric and sequential schemes.</p><p>The voltages at which <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> can be measured may also limit the identification of an allosteric mechanism. This point is illustrated by the behavior of the mSlo R207Q mutant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>). In contrast to the wild type, the slope of the <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship for R207Q does not appear to decrease at negative voltages (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref> B), even though measurements were made down to &#x02212;180 mV where <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is very small (10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>). However, both WT and R207Q <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships are well fit by the allosteric model using identical values of <italic>D</italic>, <italic>L</italic>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>L</sub>, and <italic>z</italic>
<sub>J</sub>, and different values of V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref> B, solid lines). These fits imply that <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is more steeply voltage dependent for the mutant because the voltage sensors are significantly activated even at &#x02212;180 mV [V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>) = &#x02212;100 mV]. The model predicts that R207Q will achieve the same limiting slope as the WT, but only at voltages more negative than &#x02212;200 mV (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref> B). Thus, the identification of a weakly voltage-dependent limiting slope may be impossible if <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> cannot be measured at voltages sufficiently negative to force the voltage sensors into the resting state.</p></sec><sec><title>Previous Evidence for Allosteric Voltage Gating</title><p>Allosteric models analogous to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> have been proposed to describe the voltage-dependent activation of several channels, including L-type Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MarksandJones1992">Marks and Jones 1992</xref>), <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="McCormacketal1994">McCormack et al. 1994</xref>), and SR Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="N0x1e510b0N0x1e3fc30">R&#x000ed;os et al. 1993</xref>). These examples are relevant to the above discussion, present some interesting contrasts to mSlo, and illustrate an alternative approach to testing the allosteric model. In all three studies, it was the action of a ligand rather than the properties of gating under control (ligand-free) conditions that provided the most compelling evidence for an allosteric voltage-gating mechanism. In other words, gating properties in the absence of ligand were consistent with an allosteric model, but were also adequately described by sequential schemes analogous to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> or <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref>. Measurements were not performed at extreme voltages or low <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> to distinguish these possibilities. And the allosteric model parameters <italic>L</italic> and <italic>D</italic> that were used to describe these channels suggest that such measurements would be at least as difficult as they are for mSlo: <italic>L</italic> = 7.8 * 10<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>, <italic>D</italic> = 225 (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MarksandJones1992">Marks and Jones 1992</xref>); <italic>L</italic> = 1.7 * 10<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>, <italic>D</italic> = 49 (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="McCormacketal1994">McCormack et al. 1994</xref>); and <italic>L</italic> = 1.3 * 10<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>, <italic>D</italic> = 25 (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="N0x1e510b0N0x1e3fc30">R&#x000ed;os et al. 1993</xref>). However, upon ligand application, channel gating was altered in complex ways that were most simply explained in the context of an allosteric voltage-gating mechanism.</p><p>
<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MarksandJones1992">Marks and Jones 1992</xref> found that application of dihydropyridine agonists to Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels caused a decreased latency to first opening, an increase in the maximum <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>, and a slowing of I<sub>Ca</sub> tail currents. In addition, the <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship was shifted to more negative voltages and became steeper. These diverse effects cannot be accounted for by a sequential scheme without assuming that ligand binding has complex effects on multiple transitions. In contrast, an allosteric scheme reproduces all the results with the simple assumption that agonist-binding increases the equilibrium constant (<italic>L</italic>) for the allosteric C&#x02013;O transition. The decrease in first latency reflects that an increase in <italic>L</italic> will allow channels to open when fewer than four voltage sensors are activated. Consistent with this prediction, two open dwell-time components were detected in the presence of ligand, providing evidence for multiple open states. And the predictions of the allosteric model concerning first latency are analogous to those concerning the kinetics of the macroscopic delay in the present study.</p><p>R&#x000ed;os et. al. (1993) also concluded that multiple effects of an agonist (perchlorate) on SR Ca<sup>2+</sup>-release channel conductance and gating currents could be explained simply in terms of an allosteric model where agonist binding enhances the allosteric transition (increasing <italic>L</italic>). Conversely, <xref ref-type="bib" rid="McCormacketal1994">McCormack et al. 1994</xref> proposed that inhibitory effects of 4AP on ionic and gating currents in <italic>Shaker</italic> channels can be explained in terms of a decrease in <italic>L</italic> that favors the closed conformation.</p><p>In line with our results for mSlo, the three studies discussed above concluded that the allosteric transition between C and O was weakly voltage dependent or voltage independent. An important difference between these channels and mSlo is that their activation kinetics appear to be limited by voltage-sensor movement rather than channel opening. In the case of the Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="MarksandJones1992">Marks and Jones 1992</xref>), C&#x02013;O transitions are &#x0223c;100-fold faster than voltage-sensor activation, essentially opposite the relationship observed for mSlo. This difference results in activation kinetics for Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels and <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channels that are more sigmoidal than observed for mSlo (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Zagottaetal1994b">Zagotta et al. 1994b</xref>). Related differences in channel behavior are observed at the level of gating current kinetics (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>). The relative speed of voltage-sensor movement and channel opening for mSlo turn out to be advantageous for dissecting transitions in the allosteric scheme. For example, we are able to assume that the delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation mainly reflects voltage-sensor properties because channel opening is slow. Similarly, the I<sub>K</sub> relaxation time constant &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) was analyzed with the assumption that voltage sensors are equilibrated.</p></sec><sec><title>Limiting Slope of the P<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V Relationship and Multiple Open States</title><p>Measurements of the limiting voltage dependence or &#x0201c;limiting slope&#x0201d; of the G&#x02013;V relationship have been used extensively to estimate the total gating charge associated with activation of many voltage-gated channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Almers1978">Almers 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Zagottaetal1994b">Zagotta et al. 1994b</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Hirschbergetal1995">Hirschberg et al. 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Nocetietal1996">Noceti et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Seohetal1996">Seoh et al. 1996</xref>) including BK channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Diazetal1998">Diaz et al. 1998</xref>). <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Almers1978">Almers 1978</xref> showed that if channel gating can be described by a linear sequence of closed states followed by a single open state, then the voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> will be maximal at limiting negative voltages. <xref ref-type="bib" rid="SiggandBezanilla1997">Sigg and Bezanilla 1997</xref> generalized this conclusion to any model containing a single open state. For such schemes, the limiting voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> denotes the total gating charge moved during a transition from the resting closed state occupied at negative voltages (e.g., C<sub>0</sub> in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>) to the open state. In the few previous instances where single channel currents have been used to measure very low values of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>, the voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> appeared to achieve a maximum at negative voltages consistent with the presence of a single open state (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Hirschbergetal1995">Hirschberg et al. 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="IslasandSigworth1996">Islas and Sigworth 1996</xref>). However our results show that BK channel gating is not consistent with such a model since the voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> for mSlo decreases at negative voltages.</p><p>When the limiting and maximum voltage dependence of <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> are different, as for mSlo, then the channel must have multiple open states and there must be voltage-dependent pathways between the open states (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="SiggandBezanilla1997">Sigg and Bezanilla 1997</xref>). The allosteric voltage-gating scheme encompasses these general conclusions. A particular feature of this scheme is that the maximum slope of the <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship reflects the charge associated with a subset of transitions and therefore underestimates the total gating charge. For example, the maximum slope of the fit in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> F represents an equivalent charge of 1.74 <italic>e</italic>, underestimating the total charge (2.6 <italic>e</italic>) by 33%. In addition, the relationship between maximum slope and total charge may change when model parameters <italic>L</italic> or <italic>D</italic> are altered, and changes in maximum slope caused by channel mutations, such as those reported by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Diazetal1998">Diaz et al. 1998</xref>, cannot be unequivocally attributed to changes in total gating charge.</p></sec><sec><title>Molecular Mechanism of Allosteric Voltage Gating</title><p>Experiments in many voltage-gated channels suggest that the S4 transmembrane segment forms at least part of the voltage sensor (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="YangandHorn1995">Yang and Horn 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="AggarwalandMacKinnon1996">Aggarwal and MacKinnon 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Baoetal1999">Bao et al. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Larssonetal1996">Larsson et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Mannuzzuetal1996">Mannuzzu et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Seohetal1996">Seoh et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Yangetal1996">Yang et al. 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Yusafetal1996">Yusaf et al. 1996</xref>). Residues have also been identified that may form part of an activation gate that controls the flow of ions through the pore (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Liuetal1997">Liu et al. 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Holmgrenetal1998">Holmgren et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Perozoetal1998">Perozo et al. 1998</xref>). However, little is known about the molecular nature of the interaction between voltage sensors and the activation gates. Sequential models of voltage gating (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S3">Fig. 3</xref> or <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref>) suggest that voltage sensors form part of the activation gate or are directly linked to the gate in such a way that channel opening can only occur when all voltage sensors are in an activated conformation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref> A). In contrast, the allosteric voltage-gating model for mSlo implies a less direct interaction between voltage sensor and channel pore, which is more difficult to envisage in terms of a physical model.</p><p>Many allosteric proteins have been studied whose molecular structure is known in detail, such as hemoglobin, glycogen phosphorylase, phosphofructokinase, and aspartate transcarbamoylase (reviewed by <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Perutz1989">Perutz 1989</xref>). These studies provide guidelines concerning the molecular nature of allosteric interactions that could prove useful in understanding how voltage-sensor movement and channel opening might interact in mSlo. These examples are multimeric proteins with multiple ligand-binding sites. Cooperative ligand interactions with these proteins are well described by models analogous to the MWC scheme, where the protein can undergo an allosteric conformational change that in turn affects the affinity of ligand binding sites. In all cases, the high and low affinity conformations of these proteins have been determined by x-ray crystallography. Two important conclusions from these studies are that allosteric transitions generally involve a concerted quaternary conformational change, and that the interaction of ligand-binding sites with the allosteric transition is mediated through subunit interfaces. One explanation for these results is that molecular interactions between subunits are weaker than those within subunits. Thus, a change in the tertiary conformation of a subunit due to ligand binding is more likely to alter the relative position and bonds between subunits than it is to perturb the tertiary conformation of an adjacent subunit. Ligand-binding sites in allosteric proteins are linked to subunit interfaces in such a way that a change in quaternary conformation is translated into a change in the structure of the binding site. Quaternary conformational changes often preserve a symmetric arrangement of subunits and are therefore concerted.</p><p>By analogy with other allosteric proteins, it is reasonable to propose that mSlo channel opening involves a quaternary conformational change and that voltage sensors affect the interaction between subunits. Structural studies of gap&#x02013;junction channels and nicotinic Ach-receptor channels by Unwin and co-workers (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="UnwinandEnnis1984">Unwin and Ennis 1984</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Unwinetal1988">Unwin et al. 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Unwin1998">Unwin 1998</xref>) support the idea that channel opening involves a quaternary rearrangement of subunits. Experiments examining the accessibility of <italic>Shaker</italic> channels to cysteine-modifying reagents are also suggestive of such conformational changes in voltage-gated channels (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Holmgrenetal1998">Holmgren et al. 1998</xref>). Voltage sensors might then affect channel opening if their activation produces a change in the steric or binding interactions between subunits. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref> B illustrates how such a mechanism might work in the context of the allosteric voltage-gating scheme. In this cartoon, channel opening is depicted as a concerted rotation of four subunits and voltage-sensor activation is shown as a tertiary conformational change within each subunit. For simplicity, only the states with all four voltage sensors in the resting (&#x02212;) or activated (+) states are shown, and transitions involving independent voltage-sensor movement are abbreviated by dashed arrows. Shaded areas between subunits represent hypothetical regions of subunit&#x02013;subunit interaction. Voltage sensors are shown as interacting strongly with adjacent subunits only when they are in the resting conformation and when the channel is closed. Thus, voltage-sensor activation promotes channel opening by selectively destabilizing the closed conformation, as suggested by the kinetic data. Conversely, the equilibrium constant for voltage-sensor activation increases when the channel is open because the resting (&#x02212;) state is no longer stabilized via interaction with adjacent subunits. Although the details of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F11">Fig. 11</xref> B are speculative, they are consistent with our data and suggest a possible molecular mechanism for interaction between voltage sensors and channel opening that may guide future investigation.</p></sec><sec><title>The Voltage Dependence of Channel Opening</title><p>The idea that mSlo channel opening involves a quaternary conformational change is attractive not only because it is consistent with an allosteric mechanism, but also because it provides a possible explanation for the voltage dependence of channel opening. The allosteric model assumes that channel opening and voltage-sensor activation are distinct events. Yet the data suggest that C&#x02013;O transitions are voltage dependent and account for &#x0223c;15% of the total gating charge movement. This result may appear to contradict the assumption that the C&#x02013;O conformational change does not involve voltage-sensor activation. However, it is likely that channel opening could involve the movement of charged groups in the voltage sensor without requiring that voltage sensors &#x0201c;activate.&#x0201d; Quaternary conformational changes in proteins often involve rotations of subunits about an axis perpendicular to the axis of symmetry (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Perutz1989">Perutz 1989</xref>). In the case of ion channels, such a motion might allow voltage sensors to rotate within the membrane electric field. Thus, channel opening could involve a displacement of voltage-sensor charge without requiring that voltage sensors undergo a tertiary conformational change (from R to A). This mechanism suggests that an alteration in voltage-sensor charge could affect the charge movement associated with both voltage-sensor activation and channel opening. We did not test this prediction, but several investigations of <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channels have concluded that 10&#x02013;17% of the total gating charge (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>T</sub>) is associated with channel opening (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="McCormacketal1994">McCormack et al. 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Zagottaetal1994a">Zagotta et al. 1994a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Smith-Maxwelletal1998">Smith-Maxwell et al. 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="LedwellandAldrich1999">Ledwell and Aldrich 1999</xref>) or final cooperative transitions (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Schoppaetal1992">Schoppa et al. 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Sigworth1994">Sigworth 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="SchoppaandSigworth1998b">Schoppa and Sigworth 1998b</xref>). Thus, the fraction of <italic>z</italic>
<sub>T</sub> associated with channel opening is similar for <italic>Shaker</italic> and mSlo even though <italic>z</italic>
<sub>T</sub> is approximately fivefold greater for <italic>Shaker</italic> (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>). This is consistent with <italic>mSlo</italic> and <italic>Shaker</italic> undergoing similar conformational changes, with the difference that the <italic>Shaker</italic> voltage sensor is more highly charged. In addition, mutations to the <italic>Shaker</italic> S4 segment can almost eliminate the voltage dependence of channel gating (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Baoetal1999">Bao et al. 1999</xref>), consistent with a reduction of voltage-sensor charge contributing to a decrease in the voltage dependence of the channel opening transition.</p></sec><sec><title>Implications for Calcium-dependent Activation</title><p>The allosteric voltage-gating scheme has implications for understanding the effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on BK channel function. Many of the effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> on mSlo channel activation can be described by a voltage-dependent MWC scheme, which operates under the assumption that Ca<sup>2+</sup> allosterically modulates voltage-dependent channel activation (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>; <xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). This scheme further assumes that channel opening can be described by a single concerted voltage-dependent transition between a closed and open conformation. However, we have shown here that the voltage-dependent activation pathway is more complicated and can be separated into voltage-sensor movement and channel-opening steps. This description of voltage gating raises a question concerning the mechanism of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent action: Does Ca<sup>2+</sup> alter voltage-sensor movement or channel opening, or some combination of both? This question will be addressed in a subsequent article (Horrigan, F.T., and R.W. Aldrich, manuscript in preparation).</p><p>Regardless of the mechanism of Ca<sup>2+</sup> sensitivity, the complexity of the allosteric voltage-gating scheme greatly increases the minimal complexity of any model of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent activation. Previous work has demonstrated that mSlo exhibits a dose&#x02013;response relationship for Ca<sup>2+</sup> that is characterized by a Hill coefficient of &#x0223c;1&#x02013;3 (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Cuietal1997">Cui et al. 1997</xref>). Thus, the channel must have at least three Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites and it is reasonable to assume that there might four, one for each subunit. Given a 10-state model of voltage gating and four Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding sites, a complete model of mSlo gating must contain a minimum of 50 states (for each state in the voltage-gating scheme there will exist at least one state with 0&#x02013;4 Ca<sup>2+</sup> ions bound). If Ca<sup>2+</sup> binding affects voltage-sensor movement, a 70-state model is necessary. Even more states may be required if the relative position of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-bound subunits and activated voltage sensors within the channel homotetramer affect their interaction (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="Coxetal1997a">Cox et al. 1997a</xref>; Horrigan, F.T., and R.W. Aldrich, manuscript in preparation).</p></sec><sec><title>Limitations of the Data</title><p>According to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref>, measurements of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) and <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> at negative voltages provide direct information about the kinetics and voltage dependence of the C<sub>0</sub>&#x02013;O<sub>0</sub> transition. However, not all parameters in the allosteric model are as tightly constrained, and several simplifying assumptions have been made that require confirmation. For example, the properties of closed-state transitions (C&#x02013;C) were determined based upon analysis of the delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation as well as the voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) and <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>. These data are consistent with the assumption that horizontal transitions represent the activation of four independent and identical voltage sensors and that the forward and backward rate constants for these transitions are symmetrically voltage dependent. Similarly, the assumption that forward and backward rate constants for voltage-sensor activation are symmetrically affected by channel opening appears consistent with the presence of a brief delay in the decay of potassium tail currents. However, ionic current data provides only an indirect measurement of voltage-sensor movement, and deviations from these simple assumptions are possible.</p><p>It thus becomes important to characterize the properties of voltage-sensor movement. In the companion article (<xref ref-type="bib" rid="HorriganandAldrich1999">Horrigan and Aldrich 1999</xref>), gating current measurements were used to directly examine voltage-sensor movement. The results generally confirm the above assumptions and provide further support for the allosteric voltage-gating scheme.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Dan Cox and Gargi Talukder for helpful comments on the manuscript.</p><p>This work was supported by a grant from the National Institutes of Health (NS23294) and by a National Institute of Mental Health Silvio Conte Center for Neuroscience Research grant (MH48108). R.W. Aldrich is an investigator with the Howard Hughes Medical Institute.</p></ack><fn-group><fn><p>1used in this paper: BK channels, large conductance Ca2+-activated potassium channels; G&#x02013;V, conductance&#x02013;voltage relationship; MWC, Monod-Wyman-Changeux; WT, wild type</p></fn></fn-group><app-group><app id="APPAppendix"><p>To derive an expression for the delay duration (&#x00394;<italic>t</italic>), <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD4"/> is rewritten in terms of open-state occupancy: <disp-formula id="FD22"><label>22</label><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O}} \left \left(t\right) \right ={\mathrm{O}}_{{\mathrm{{\infty}}}} \left \left[1-e^{{ \left \left({\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t-t\right) \right }/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}\right] \right t{\geq}T{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> where <italic>T</italic> is the time where O(<italic>t</italic>) achieves an exponential time course, and &#x003c4; is the time constant of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation [&#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)]. <italic>d</italic>O/<italic>dt</italic> can then be defined after the delay: <disp-formula id="FD23"><label>23</label><tex-math id="M26">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right =\frac{{\mathrm{O}}_{{\mathrm{{\infty}}}}}{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}e^{{ \left \left({\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t-t\right) \right }/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}t{\geq}T{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD22"/> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD23"/> gives: <disp-formula id="FD24"><label>24</label><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*} \left \left[\frac{{\mathrm{{\tau}O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right }{{\mathrm{O}} \left \left(t\right) \right +{\mathrm{{\tau}O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right }\right] \right =e^{{ \left \left({\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t-t\right) \right }/{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}}{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD24"/> can be linearized when [(&#x00394;<italic>t</italic> &#x02212; <italic>t</italic>)/&#x003c4;] is small (when O &#x0003c;&#x0003c; &#x003c4;O&#x02032;). Such is the case for mSlo at <italic>t</italic> = T, when I<sub>K</sub> achieves an exponential time course: <disp-formula id="FD25"><label>25</label><tex-math id="M28">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*} \left \left[\frac{{\mathrm{{\tau}O^{\prime}}} \left \left(T\right) \right }{{\mathrm{O}} \left \left(T\right) \right +{\mathrm{{\tau}O^{\prime}}} \left \left(T\right) \right }\right] \right =1+\frac{ \left \left({\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t-T\right) \right }{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}}{\mathrm{;}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> hence <disp-formula id="FD26"><label>26</label><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t=T-\frac{{\mathrm{O}} \left \left(T\right) \right }{{\mathrm{O^{\prime}}} \left \left(T\right) \right }{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Because O(<italic>T</italic>) is small during the delay O&#x02032;(<italic>t</italic>) can be approximated by <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD10"/>: <disp-formula id="FD27"><label>27</label><tex-math id="M30">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right ={\mathrm{{\delta}C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}} \left \left(t\right) \right t{\leq}T{\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> and <disp-formula id="FD28"><label>28</label><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{O}} \left \left(T\right) \right ={\int _{0}^{T}}{\mathrm{O^{\prime}}} \left \left(t\right) \right dt={\mathrm{{\delta}}}{\int _{0}^{T}}{\mathrm{C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}} \left \left(t\right) \right dt{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD26"/>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD27"/>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD28"/> gives: <disp-formula id="FD29"><label>29</label><tex-math id="M32">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t=T-{\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{{\mathrm{C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}} \left \left(t\right) \right dt}{{\mathrm{C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}} \left \left(T\right) \right }{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Thus &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> is determined only by C<sub>L</sub>(<italic>t</italic>). If transitions among closed states are assumed to be fast relative to channel opening, as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">5</xref>, then the amplitude and time course of C<sub>L</sub> should be functions mainly of voltage-dependent rate constants that characterize closed-state transitions.</p><p>In <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">5</xref>, C<sub>L</sub> can be expressed as the product of a voltage-dependent amplitude function (F[v] = A<sub>&#x0221e;</sub>
<sup>4</sup>) and a time-dependent function of the voltage-sensor activation time constant &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>
<italic>G</italic>&#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>
<italic>v</italic>,<italic>t</italic>=1&#x02212;<italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;<italic>t</italic>&#x003c4;<sub>J</sub></sup>
<sup>4</sup>(see <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD2"/> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD8"/>): <disp-formula id="FD30"><label>30</label><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{C}}_{{\mathrm{L}}} \left \left[v,t\right] \right =F \left \left[v\right] \right G \left \left({\mathrm{{\tau}}}_{{\mathrm{J}}} \left \left[v\right] \right ,t\right) \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>For any model where C<sub>L</sub> can be expressed in terms of <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD30"/>, <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD29"/> can be expressed in terms of only <italic>G</italic>[&#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>[<italic>v</italic>], <italic>t</italic>]: <disp-formula id="FD31"><label>31</label><tex-math id="M34">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t \left \left({\mathrm{{\tau}}}_{{\mathrm{J}}} \left \left[v\right] \right \right) \right =T-{\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left({\mathrm{{\tau}}}_{{\mathrm{J}}} \left \left[v\right] \right ,t\right) \right dt}{G \left \left({\mathrm{{\tau}}}_{{\mathrm{J}}} \left \left[v\right] \right ,T\right) \right }{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Thus &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> is a function of &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>[v]. Now we determine the conditions under which &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> will be proportional to &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>[v] or, equivalently, <disp-formula id="FD32"><label>32</label><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{{\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t \left \left({\mathrm{{\tau}}}_{{\mathrm{J}}} \left \left[v_{2}\right] \right \right) \right }{{\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t \left \left({\mathrm{{\tau}}}_{{\mathrm{J}}} \left \left[v_{1}\right] \right \right) \right }=\frac{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}_{{\mathrm{J}}} \left \left[v_{2}\right] \right }{{\mathrm{{\tau}}}_{{\mathrm{J}}} \left \left[v_{1}\right] \right }=s\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> or <disp-formula id="FD33"><label>33</label><tex-math id="M36">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}}\right] \right =s{\mathrm{{\Delta}}}t \left \left[{\mathrm{{\tau}}}\right] \right {\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> where &#x003c4; = &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>[<italic>v</italic>
<sub>1</sub>] and <italic>s</italic>&#x003c4; = &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>[<italic>v</italic>
<sub>2</sub>]. If <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD33"/> is true, then, by combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD31"/> and <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD33"/>, <disp-formula id="FD34"><label>34</label><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}T-{\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},t\right] \right dt}{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }= \left \left(T-{\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left[{\mathrm{{\tau}}},t\right] \right dt}{G \left \left[{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }\right) \right {\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> where <disp-formula id="FD35"><label>35</label><tex-math id="M38">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},t\right] \right =G_{{\mathrm{{\infty}}}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> for <italic>t</italic> &#x02265; <italic>T</italic>. <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD34"/> is true if <disp-formula id="FD36"><label>36</label><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}G \left \left[{\mathrm{{\tau}}},t\right] \right =G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},st\right] \right \end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>(a condition that holds for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">5</xref>). <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD36"/> implies: <disp-formula id="FD37"><label>37</label><tex-math id="M40">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left[{\mathrm{{\tau}}},t\right] \right dt}{G \left \left[{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }\;={\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},st\right] \right dt}{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},sT\right] \right }{\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>By changing the variable of integration (<italic>r</italic> = <italic>st</italic>) this becomes: <disp-formula id="FD38"><label>38</label><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},st\right] \right dt}{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},sT\right] \right }=\frac{1}{s}{\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},r\right] \right dr}{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }=\frac{1}{s} \left \left({\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},r\right] \right dr}{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }+{\int _{T}^{sT}}\frac{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},r\right] \right dr}{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }\right) \right {\mathrm{.}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>
</p><p>Given <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD35"/> then: <disp-formula id="FD39"><label>39</label><tex-math id="M42">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}\frac{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},r\right] \right dr}{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }=1\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> for <italic>r</italic> &#x02265; <italic>T</italic>. Combining <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD37"/>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD38"/>
<xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD39"/> and replacing <italic>r</italic> with <italic>t</italic> yields: <disp-formula id="FD40"><label>40</label><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[10pt]{article}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{pmc}
\usepackage[Euler]{upgreek}
\pagestyle{empty}

\oddsidemargin -1.0in

\begin{document}
\begin{equation*}{\int _{0}^{T}}\frac{G \left \left[{\mathrm{{\tau}}},t\right] \right dt}{G \left \left[{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }\;=\frac{1}{s} \left {\int _{0}^{sT}}\frac{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},t\right] \right dt}{G \left \left[s{\mathrm{{\tau}}},T\right] \right }+T \left \left(s-1\right) \right  \right {\mathrm{,}}\end{equation*}\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula> which can be rearranged to yield <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="FD34"/>. Thus &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> is proportional to &#x003c4;<sub>J</sub>[<italic>v</italic>] for <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">5</xref> under the conditions that, first, I<sub>K</sub> achieves an exponential time course when <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> is small and, second, transitions among closed states are assumed to be fast relative to channel opening.</p></app></app-group><ref-list><ref id="AggarwalandMacKinnon1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aggarwal</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacKinnon</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Contribution of the S4 segment to gating charge in the <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channel</article-title>
<source>Neuron</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>1169</fpage>
<lpage>1177</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8663993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Almers1978"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almers</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Gating currents and charge movements in excitable membranes</article-title>
<source>Rev. Physiol. Biochem. Pharmacol.</source>
<volume>82</volume>
<year>1978</year>
<fpage>96</fpage>
<lpage>190</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">356157</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ArmstrongandBezanilla1974"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezanilla</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Charge movement associated with the opening and closing of the activation gates of the Na channels</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>63</volume>
<year>1974</year>
<fpage>533</fpage>
<lpage>552</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4824995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Baoetal1999"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bao</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hakeem</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Henteleff</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Starkus</surname><given-names>J.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rayner</surname><given-names>M.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Voltage-insensitive gating after charge-neutralizing mutations in the S4 segment of shaker channels</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>113</volume>
<year>1999</year>
<fpage>139</fpage>
<lpage>151</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9874694</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Barrettetal1982"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magleby</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallotta</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Properties of single calcium-activated potassium channels in cultured rat muscle</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>331</volume>
<year>1982</year>
<fpage>211</fpage>
<lpage>230</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6296366</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="BielefeldtandJackson1993"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bielefeldt</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>M.B.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A calcium-activated potassium channel causes frequency-dependent action-potential failures in a mammalian nerve terminal</article-title>
<source>J. Neurophysiol.</source>
<volume>70</volume>
<year>1993</year>
<fpage>284</fpage>
<lpage>298</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8395581</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="BraydenandNelson1992"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brayden</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Regulation of arterial tone by activation of calcium-dependent potassium channels</article-title>
<source>Science.</source>
<volume>256</volume>
<year>1992</year>
<fpage>532</fpage>
<lpage>535</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1373909</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ColeandMoore1960"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>J.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Potassium ion current in the squid giant axondynamic characteristic</article-title>
<source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<year>1960</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>14</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13694549</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ColquhounandHawkes1977"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colquhoun</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>A.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Relaxation and fluctuations of membrane currents that flow through drug-operated channels</article-title>
<source>Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci.</source>
<volume>199</volume>
<year>1977</year>
<fpage>231</fpage>
<lpage>262</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22856</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Coxetal1997a"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Allosteric gating of a large conductance Ca-activated K<sup>+</sup> channel</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>110</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>257</fpage>
<lpage>281</lpage>a
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9276753</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="Coxetal1997b"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Separation of gating properties from permeation and block in mslo large conductance Ca-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>109</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>633</fpage>
<lpage>646</lpage>b
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9154909</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CrestandGola1993"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crest</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gola</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Large conductance Ca<sup>(2+)</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels are involved in both spike shaping and firing regulation in helix neurones</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>465</volume>
<year>1993</year>
<fpage>265</fpage>
<lpage>287</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8229836</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Cuietal1997"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cui</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>D.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Intrinsic voltage dependence and Ca<sup>2+</sup> regulation of mslo large conductance Ca-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>109</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>647</fpage>
<lpage>673</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9154910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Diazetal1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Interaction of internal Ba<sup>2+</sup> with a cloned Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent K<sup>+</sup> (hslo) channel from smooth muscle</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>107</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>399</fpage>
<lpage>407</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8868050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Diazetal1998"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meera</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amigo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarez</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Role of the S4 segment in a voltage-dependent calcium-sensitive potassium (hSlo) channel</article-title>
<source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
<volume>273</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>32430</fpage>
<lpage>32436</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9829973</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DiChiaraandReinhart1995"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiChiara</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Distinct effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> and voltage on the activation and deactivation of cloned Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>489</volume>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>403</fpage>
<lpage>418</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8847636</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="DiChiaraandReinhart1997"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>DiChiara</surname><given-names>T.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinhart</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Redox modulation of hslo Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>
<source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>17</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>4942</fpage>
<lpage>4955</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9185532</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="GormanandThomas1980"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gorman</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>M.V.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Potassium conductance and internal calcium accumulation in a molluscan neurone</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>308</volume>
<year>1980</year>
<fpage>287</fpage>
<lpage>313</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7230018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Hamilletal1981"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamill</surname><given-names>O.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neher</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sakmann</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigworth</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Improved patch-clamp techniques for high-resolution current recording from cells and cell-free membrane patches</article-title>
<source>Pfl&#x000fc;gers Arch.</source>
<volume>391</volume>
<year>1981</year>
<fpage>85</fpage>
<lpage>100</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6270629</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="HerringtonandBookman1995"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herrington</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bookman</surname><given-names>R.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Pulse Control</source>
<year>1995</year>
<publisher-name>University of Miami Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Miami, FL</publisher-loc>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="Hirschbergetal1995"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirschberg</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rovner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lieberman</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patlak</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Transfer of twelve charges is needed to open skeletal muscle Na<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>106</volume>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>1053</fpage>
<lpage>1068</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8786350</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="HodgkinandHuxley1952"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hodgkin</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huxley</surname><given-names>A.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A quantitative description of membrane current and its application to conduction and excitation in muscle</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>117</volume>
<year>1952</year>
<fpage>500</fpage>
<lpage>544</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12991237</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Holmgrenetal1998"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yellen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The activation gate of a voltage-gated K<sup>+</sup> channel can be trapped in the open state by an intersubunit metal bridge</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>21</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>617</fpage>
<lpage>621</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9768847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="HorriganandAldrich1999"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Horrigan</surname><given-names>F.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Allosteric voltage-gating of potassium channels IImSlo channel gating charge movement in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup>
</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>114</volume>
<year>1999</year>
<fpage>305</fpage>
<lpage>336</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10436004</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="HudspethandLewis1988"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hudspeth</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Kinetic analysis of voltage- and ion-dependent conductances in saccular hair cells of the bull-frog, <italic>Rana catesbeiana</italic>
</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>400</volume>
<year>1988</year>
<fpage>237</fpage>
<lpage>274</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2458454</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="IslasandSigworth1996"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Islas</surname><given-names>L.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigworth</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The limiting slope of KV 2.1 channels shows a gating charge of about 12 e</article-title>
<source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>70</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>A190</fpage>(Abstr.)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="Lancasteretal1991"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lancaster</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicoll</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Perkel</surname><given-names>D.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium activates two types of potassium channels in rat hippocampal neurons in culture</article-title>
<source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<year>1991</year>
<fpage>23</fpage>
<lpage>30</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1986065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Larssonetal1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>H.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>O.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dhillon</surname><given-names>D.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>E.Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Transmembrane movement of the <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channel S4</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>387</fpage>
<lpage>397</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8789953</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Latorreetal1982"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hidalgo</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Reconstitution in planar lipid bilayers of a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent K<sup>+</sup> channel from transverse tubule membranes isolated from rabbit skeletal muscle</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>79</volume>
<year>1982</year>
<fpage>805</fpage>
<lpage>809</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6278496</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="LedwellandAldrich1999"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ledwell</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Mutations in the S4 region isolate the final voltage-dependent cooperative step in potassium channel activation</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>113</volume>
<year>1999</year>
<fpage>389</fpage>
<lpage>414</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10051516</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="LewisandHudspeth1983"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hudspeth</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Voltage- and ion-dependent conductances in solitary vertebrate hair cells</article-title>
<source>Nature.</source>
<volume>304</volume>
<year>1983</year>
<fpage>538</fpage>
<lpage>541</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6603579</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Liuetal1997"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holmgren</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jurman</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yellen</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Gated access to the pore of a voltage-dependent K<sup>+</sup> channel</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>175</fpage>
<lpage>184</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9247273</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="MaglebyandPallotta1983a"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magleby</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallotta</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Burst kinetics of single calcium-activated potassium channels in cultured rat muscle</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>344</volume>
<year>1983</year>
<fpage>605</fpage>
<lpage>623</lpage>a
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6317854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="MaglebyandPallotta1983b"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Magleby</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pallotta</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium dependence of open and shut interval distributions from calcium-activated potassium channels in cultured rat muscle</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>344</volume>
<year>1983</year>
<fpage>585</fpage>
<lpage>604</lpage>b
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6317853</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="Mannuzzuetal1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mannuzzu</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moronne</surname><given-names>M.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Isacoff</surname><given-names>E.Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Direct physical measure of conformational rearrangement underlying potassium channel gating</article-title>
<source>Science.</source>
<volume>271</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>213</fpage>
<lpage>216</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8539623</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="MarksandJones1992"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marks</surname><given-names>T.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>S.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium currents in the A7r5 smooth muscle&#x02013;derived cell line. An allosteric model for calcium channel activation and dihydropyridine agonist action</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>99</volume>
<year>1992</year>
<fpage>367</fpage>
<lpage>390</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1316936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="MarrionandTavalin1998"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marrion</surname><given-names>N.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavalin</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Selective activation of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels by co-localized Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels in hippocampal neurons</article-title>
<source>Nature.</source>
<volume>395</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>900</fpage>
<lpage>905</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9804423</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Marty1981"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marty</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ca-dependent K channels with large unitary conductance in chromaffin cell membranes</article-title>
<source>Nature.</source>
<volume>291</volume>
<year>1981</year>
<fpage>497</fpage>
<lpage>500</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6262657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="McCormacketal1994"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joiner</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinemann</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A characterization of the activating structural rearrangements in voltage-dependent <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channels. [Published erratum appears in <italic>Neuron</italic>. 1994. 12:706.]</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<year>1994</year>
<fpage>301</fpage>
<lpage>315</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8110460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="McManusandMagleby1991"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McManus</surname><given-names>O.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magleby</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Accounting for the Ca<sup>(2+)</sup>-dependent kinetics of single large-conductance Ca<sup>(2+)</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels in rat skeletal muscle</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>443</volume>
<year>1991</year>
<fpage>739</fpage>
<lpage>777</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1822543</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Meeraetal1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meera</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A calcium switch for the functional coupling between alpha (hslo) and beta subunits (KV,Ca beta) of maxi K channels</article-title>
<source>FEBS Lett.</source>
<volume>382</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>84</fpage>
<lpage>88</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8612769</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="MethfesselandBoheim1982"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Methfessel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boheim</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The gating of single calcium-dependent potassium channels is described by an activation/blockade mechanism</article-title>
<source>Biophys. Struct. Mech.</source>
<volume>9</volume>
<year>1982</year>
<fpage>35</fpage>
<lpage>60</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6293598</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="MoczydlowskiandLatorre1983"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moczydlowski</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Gating kinetics of Ca<sup>2</sup>+-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels from rat muscle incorporated into planar lipid bilayers. Evidence for two voltage-dependent Ca<sup>2</sup>+ binding reactions</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>82</volume>
<year>1983</year>
<fpage>511</fpage>
<lpage>542</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6315857</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Monodetal1965"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monod</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Changeux</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>On the nature of allosteric transitionsa plausible model</article-title>
<source>J. Mol. Biol.</source>
<volume>12</volume>
<year>1965</year>
<fpage>88</fpage>
<lpage>118</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14343300</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Nelsonetal1995"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>M.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rubart</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santana</surname><given-names>L.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonev</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knot</surname><given-names>H.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lederer</surname><given-names>W.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Relaxation of arterial smooth muscle by calcium sparks</article-title>
<source>Science.</source>
<volume>270</volume>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>633</fpage>
<lpage>637</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7570021</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Neyton1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neyton</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A Ba<sup>2+</sup> chelator suppresses long shut events in fully activated high-conductance Ca<sup>2+</sup>-dependent K<sup>+</sup> channels</article-title>
<source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>71</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>220</fpage>
<lpage>226</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8804605</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Nocetietal1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Noceti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldelli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Birnbaumer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Effective gating charges per channel in voltage-dependent K<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>108</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>143</fpage>
<lpage>155</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8882860</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Pallottaetal1981"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pallotta</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magleby</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrett</surname><given-names>J.N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Single channel recordings of Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> currents in rat muscle cell culture</article-title>
<source>Nature.</source>
<volume>293</volume>
<year>1981</year>
<fpage>471</fpage>
<lpage>474</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6273730</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Perozoetal1998"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perozo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cortes</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuello</surname><given-names>L.G.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Three-dimensional architecture and gating mechanism of a K<sup>+</sup> channel studied by EPR spectroscopy</article-title>
<source>Nat. Struct. Biol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>459</fpage>
<lpage>469</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9628484</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Perozoetal1992"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perozo</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papazian</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezanilla</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Gating currents in <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channels. Implications for activation and inactivation models</article-title>
<source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>62</volume>
<year>1992</year>
<fpage>160</fpage>
<lpage>168</lpage>Discussion: 169&#x02013;171.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1600094</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="Perutz1989"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perutz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Mechanisms of cooperativity and allosteric regulation in proteins</source>
<year>1989</year>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>New York. </publisher-loc>pp. 101</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="PetersenandMaruyama1984"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>O.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maruyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium-activated potassium channels and their role in secretion</article-title>
<source>Nature.</source>
<volume>307</volume>
<year>1984</year>
<fpage>693</fpage>
<lpage>696</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6321995</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Pressetal1992"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Press</surname><given-names>W.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Teukolsky</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vetterling</surname><given-names>W.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Flannery</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Numerical recipes in Cthe art of scientific computing, 2</source>
<year>1992</year>
<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>NY</publisher-loc>pp. 717&#x02013;722</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="N0x1e510b0N0x1e3fc30"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000ed;os</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karhanek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ma</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>An allosteric model of the molecular interactions of excitation&#x02013;contraction coupling in skeletal muscle</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>102</volume>
<year>1993</year>
<fpage>449</fpage>
<lpage>481</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8245819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Robitailleetal1993"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robitaille</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaczorowski</surname><given-names>G.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Charlton</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Functional colocalization of calcium and calcium-gated potassium channels in control of transmitter release</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>11</volume>
<year>1993</year>
<fpage>645</fpage>
<lpage>655</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7691106</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="RothbergandMagleby1998"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rothberg</surname><given-names>B.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magleby</surname><given-names>K.L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Kinetic structure of large-conductance Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels suggests that the gating includes transitions through intermediate or secondary states. A mechanism for flickers</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>111</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>751</fpage>
<lpage>780</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9607935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="SafronovandVogel1998"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Safronov</surname><given-names>B.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Large conductance Ca<sup>(2+)</sup>-activated K<sup>+</sup> channels in the soma of rat motoneurones</article-title>
<source>J. Membr. Biol.</source>
<volume>162</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>9</fpage>
<lpage>15</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9516233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Schoppaetal1992"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoppa</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCormack</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanouye</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigworth</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The size of gating charge in wild-type and mutant <italic>Shaker</italic> potassium channels</article-title>
<source>Science.</source>
<volume>255</volume>
<year>1992</year>
<fpage>1712</fpage>
<lpage>1715</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1553560</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="SchoppaandSigworth1998a"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoppa</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigworth</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Activation of <italic>Shaker</italic> potassium channels. I. Characterization of voltage-dependent transitions</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol</source>
<volume>111</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>271</fpage>
<lpage>294</lpage>a
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="SchoppaandSigworth1998b"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schoppa</surname><given-names>N.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigworth</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Activation of <italic>Shaker</italic> potassium channels. III. An activation gating model for wild-type and V2 mutant channels</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>111</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>313</fpage>
<lpage>342</lpage>b
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9450946</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="SchreiberandSalkoff1997"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salkoff</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A novel calcium-sensing domain in the BK channel</article-title>
<source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>73</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>1355</fpage>
<lpage>1363</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9284303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Schreiberetal1999"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schreiber</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yuan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salkoff</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Transplantable sites confer calcium sensitivity to BK channels</article-title>
<source>Nat. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>2</volume>
<year>1999</year>
<fpage>416</fpage>
<lpage>421</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10321244</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Seohetal1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seoh</surname><given-names>S.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sigg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Papazian</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezanilla</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Voltage-sensing residues in the S2 and S4 segments of the <italic>Shaker</italic> K<sup>+</sup> channel</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>1159</fpage>
<lpage>1167</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8663992</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Shenetal1994"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>K.Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagrutta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>N.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Standen</surname><given-names>N.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelman</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>North</surname><given-names>R.A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Tetraethylammonium block of Slowpoke calcium-activated potassium channels expressed in <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytesevidence for tetrameric channel formation</article-title>
<source>Pfl&#x000fc;gers Arch.</source>
<volume>426</volume>
<year>1994</year>
<fpage>440</fpage>
<lpage>445</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7517033</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="SiggandBezanilla1997"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sigg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezanilla</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Total charge movement per channel. The relation between gating charge displacement and the voltage sensitivity of activation</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>109</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>27</fpage>
<lpage>39</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8997663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Sigworth1994"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sigworth</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Voltage gating of ion channels</article-title>
<source>Q. Rev. Biophys</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<year>1994</year>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>40</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7520590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="SigworthandZhou1992"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sigworth</surname><given-names>F.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Ion channels. Analysis of nonstationary single-channel currents</article-title>
<source>Methods Enzymol.</source>
<volume>207</volume>
<year>1992</year>
<fpage>746</fpage>
<lpage>762</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1382211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Smith-Maxwelletal1998"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith-Maxwell</surname><given-names>C.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledwell</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Uncharged S4 residues and cooperativity in voltage-dependent potassium channel activation</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>111</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>421</fpage>
<lpage>439</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9482709</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Stefanietal1997"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stefani</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottolia</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Noceti</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Olcese</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallner</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toro</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Voltage-controlled gating in a large conductance Ca<sup>2+</sup>-sensitive K<sup>+</sup>channel (hslo)</article-title>
<source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA.</source>
<volume>94</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>5427</fpage>
<lpage>5431</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9144254</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Storm1987"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Storm</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Action potential repolarization and a fast after-hyperpolarization in rat hippocampal pyramidal cells</article-title>
<source>J. Physiol.</source>
<volume>385</volume>
<year>1987</year>
<fpage>733</fpage>
<lpage>759</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2443676</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="TytgatandHess1992"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tytgat</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evidence for cooperative interactions in potassium channel gating</article-title>
<source>Nature.</source>
<volume>359</volume>
<year>1992</year>
<fpage>420</fpage>
<lpage>423</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1406954</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Unwin1998"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unwin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The nicotinic acetylcholine receptor of the Torpedo electric ray</article-title>
<source>J. Struct. Biol.</source>
<volume>121</volume>
<year>1998</year>
<fpage>181</fpage>
<lpage>190</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9615437</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Unwinetal1988"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unwin</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Toyoshima</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kubalek</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Arrangement of the acetylcholine receptor subunits in the resting and desensitized states, determined by cryoelectron microscopy of crystallized <italic>Torpedo</italic> postsynaptic membranes</article-title>
<source>J. Cell Biol.</source>
<volume>107</volume>
<year>1988</year>
<fpage>1123</fpage>
<lpage>1138</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3417777</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="UnwinandEnnis1984"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Unwin</surname><given-names>P.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ennis</surname><given-names>P.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Two configurations of a channel-forming membrane protein</article-title>
<source>Nature.</source>
<volume>307</volume>
<year>1984</year>
<fpage>609</fpage>
<lpage>613</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6320017</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="VandenbergandBezanilla1991"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vandenberg</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bezanilla</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A sodium channel gating model based on single channel, macroscopic ionic, and gating currents in the squid giant axon</article-title>
<source>Biophys. J.</source>
<volume>60</volume>
<year>1991</year>
<fpage>1511</fpage>
<lpage>1533</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1663796</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Weietal1994"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Solaro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lingle</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salkoff</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Calcium sensitivity of BK-type K<sub>Ca</sub> channels determined by a separable domain</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>13</volume>
<year>1994</year>
<fpage>671</fpage>
<lpage>681</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7917297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="WymanandGill1990"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wyman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gill</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Binding and Linkagefunctional chemistry of biological macromolecules</source>
<year>1990</year>
<publisher-name>University Science Books</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Mill Valley, CA. </publisher-loc>pp. 330</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="Yangetal1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>A.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Molecular basis of charge movement in voltage-gated sodium channels</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>113</fpage>
<lpage>122</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8562074</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="YangandHorn1995"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Evidence for voltage-dependent S4 movement in sodium channels</article-title>
<source>Neuron.</source>
<volume>15</volume>
<year>1995</year>
<fpage>213</fpage>
<lpage>218</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7619524</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Yazejianetal1997"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yazejian</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>DiGregorio</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergara</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Poage</surname><given-names>R.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meriney</surname><given-names>S.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grinnell</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Direct measurements of presynaptic calcium and calcium-activated potassium currents regulating neurotransmitter release at cultured <italic>Xenopus</italic> nerve-muscle synapses</article-title>
<source>J. Neurosci.</source>
<volume>17</volume>
<year>1997</year>
<fpage>2990</fpage>
<lpage>3001</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9096135</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Yusafetal1996"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yusaf</surname><given-names>S.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sivaprasadarao</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Measurement of the movement of the S4 segment during the activation of a voltage-gated potassium channel</article-title>
<source>Pfl&#x000fc;gers Arch.</source>
<volume>433</volume>
<year>1996</year>
<fpage>91</fpage>
<lpage>97</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9019737</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="Zagottaetal1994a"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zagotta</surname><given-names>W.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoshi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>
<italic>Shaker</italic> potassium channel gating. IIIEvaluation of kinetic models for activation</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>103</volume>
<year>1994</year>
<fpage>321</fpage>
<lpage>362</lpage>a
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8189208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="Zagottaetal1994b"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zagotta</surname><given-names>W.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoshi</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dittman</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aldrich</surname><given-names>R.W.</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>
<italic>Shaker</italic> potassium channel gating. IITransitions in the activation pathway</article-title>
<source>J. Gen. Physiol.</source>
<volume>103</volume>
<year>1994</year>
<fpage>279</fpage>
<lpage>319</lpage>b
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8189207</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>
<xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> Kinetic Parameters</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr valign="bottom" align="center"><th colspan="5" rowspan="1">
<graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.t1"/>
</th></tr><tr valign="bottom"><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameters</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patch 1</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Patch 2</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average 5&#x000b0;C</th><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average 20&#x000b0;C</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>
</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b1;(0)*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">276</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">238</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1276</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b2;(0)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7650</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">7129</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6596</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">35370</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;<sub>0</sub>(0)*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00128</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00384</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00138</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0074</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;<sub>1</sub>(0)*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0218</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0653</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0235</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.126</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;<sub>2</sub>(0)*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.370</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.11</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.399</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;<sub>3</sub>(0)*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.27</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.99</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.51</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">25.7</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b4;<sub>4</sub>(0)*</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.4</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.0</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.3</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>0</sub>(0)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">640</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1923</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">690</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3700</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>1</sub>(0)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">640</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1923</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">690</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3700</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>2</sub>(0)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">640</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1923</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">690</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3700</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>3</sub>(0)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">269</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">712</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2612</td></tr><tr valign="bottom"><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003b3;<sub>4</sub>(0)</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.3</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">294</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.8</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">295</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>*These rate constants in combination with the following parameters are sufficient to define the kinetic behavior of the model (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> = +0.275 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> = &#x02212;0.275 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub> = +0.262 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> = &#x02212;0.138 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>D</italic> = 17, <italic>f</italic> = <italic>D</italic>,[&#x003b4;<sub>0</sub>(0)/&#x003b3;<sub>0</sub>(0)] = <italic>L</italic>(0) = 2 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>, &#x003b1;/&#x003b2; = <italic>J</italic> = 1 at +145 mV [V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>)].</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="S1" position="float"><label>Scheme S1</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s1"/></fig><fig id="S2" position="float"><label>Scheme S2</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s2"/></fig><fig id="S3" position="float"><label>Scheme S3</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s3"/></fig><fig id="S4" position="float"><label>Scheme S4</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s4"/></fig><fig id="S5" position="float"><label>Scheme S5</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s5"/></fig><fig id="S6" position="float"><label>Scheme S6</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s6"/></fig><fig id="S7" position="float"><label>Scheme S7</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s7"/></fig><fig id="S8" position="float"><label>Scheme S8</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s8"/></fig><fig id="S9" position="float"><label>Scheme S9</label><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.s9"/></fig><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Delay in I<sub>K</sub> activation. (A<sub>1</sub>) I<sub>K</sub> evoked by a voltage pulse to +160 mV from a holding potential of &#x02212;80 mV at 20&#x000b0;C, representing the average response to 110 pulses. The time course of activation and deactivation are fit by exponential functions (dashed lines). (A<sub>2</sub>) The record from A<sub>1</sub> is plotted on an expanded time scale, showing a delay before I<sub>K</sub> achieves an exponential time course (dashed line). The delay duration (&#x00394;<italic>t</italic>) is defined as the time where the exponential fit intersects the time axis, and was determined after shifting the I<sub>K</sub> trace along the time axis by &#x02212;25 &#x003bc;s to correct for instrumentation delay (see <sc>methods</sc>). (B<sub>1</sub>) A family of I<sub>K</sub> evoked at 5&#x000b0;C in response to 70-ms voltage pulses (+80 to +200 mV in 20-mV steps). Exponential fits (solid lines) are superimposed on the current traces. (B<sub>2</sub>) The initial activation of I<sub>K</sub> from B<sub>1</sub> exhibits a clear delay. An arrow indicates the start of the voltage pulse. A capacitive transient (control) evoked in response to a pulse to &#x02212;180 mV was recorded using fast capacity compensation, but no leak subtraction, demonstrating that membrane voltage settles rapidly.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f1"/></fig><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Kinetics of I<sub>K</sub> delay. (A<sub>1</sub>) I<sub>K</sub> evoked at +180 mV (7&#x000b0;C) is compared with the prediction of a Hodgkin-Huxley model (Scheme III: &#x003b1; = 375 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003b2; = 660 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) that approximates the delay in I<sub>K</sub> (A<sub>2</sub>), but does not reproduce the subsequent time course of activation. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> fits both the delay and activation time course (&#x003b1; = 2,018 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003b2; = 1,172 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003b4; = 341 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003b3; = 136 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Both models were constrained to reproduce the steady state open probability measured at the end of the pulse (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub> &#x02245; G<sub>K</sub>/G<sub>Kmax</sub> = 0.29) and assume channels occupy the first closed state (C<sub>0</sub>) at the start of the pulse. The derivative of the trace in A [<italic>d</italic>(I<sub>K</sub>)/<italic>dt</italic>] is plotted on linear (B<sub>1</sub>) and log&#x02013;log (B<sub>2</sub>) scales and is fit by a function (1 &#x02212; <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;</sup>
<italic>t</italic>
<sup>/&#x003c4;</sup>)<italic><sup>n</sup></italic>, where <italic>n</italic> = 4 and &#x003c4; = 270 &#x003bc;s (B<sub>1</sub> and B<sub>2</sub>, solid line). A better fit is obtained with <italic>n</italic> = 2.9 and &#x003c4; = 316 &#x003bc;s (B<sub>2</sub>, solid line). The predictions of sequential gating <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S6">Fig. 6</xref> are indicated by dashed lines. (Scheme VI: X = 3, &#x003b1; = 600 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003b2; = 349 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>,&#x003b4; = 341 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, &#x003b3; = 136 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). Current traces were shifted along the time axis by &#x02212;25 &#x003bc;s to correct for the instrumentation delay (see <sc>methods</sc>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f2"/></fig><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Voltage dependence of I<sub>K</sub> delay. (A) The initial time course of I<sub>K</sub> activation measured at +180 mV from the same patch as <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> shows a decreased delay following a 1-ms prepulse to various voltages (&#x02212;80, 0, 40, 80, 100, and 120 mV). To accurately represent the time course of channel opening, currents during the prepulse were scaled by a factor I<sub>K</sub>(+180)/I<sub>K</sub>(V<sub>pre</sub>) representing the ratio of single channel current amplitudes measured at the test and prepulse voltages. (B) A family of I<sub>K</sub> evoked at different voltages (+120 to +240 in 20-mV steps, holding potential = &#x02212;80) are fit with exponential functions (dashed lines), demonstrating a voltage-dependent change in delay. (C) Delay duration (&#x00394;<italic>t</italic>) is plotted versus pulse voltage for two experiments. The plots are fit by functions of the form &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> = 1/(<italic>a</italic> + <italic>b</italic>) with <italic>a</italic>=<italic>a</italic>
<sub>o</sub>*<italic>e</italic>
<sup><italic>z</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub><italic>e</italic><italic>kt</italic></sup>,<italic>b</italic>=<italic>b</italic>
<sub>o</sub>*<italic>e</italic>
<sup><italic>z</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub><italic>e</italic><italic>kt</italic></sup>(<italic>z</italic>
<sub>a</sub> = +0.28 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>b</sub> = &#x02212;0.28 <italic>e</italic> ; (&#x025b4;) <italic>a</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 124 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>b</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 4,767 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>; (&#x02022;) <italic>a</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 98 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>b</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 3,902 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The delay was not well determined at the lowest voltages; therefore, fits were constrained with the simplifying assumption <italic>z</italic>
<sub>a</sub> = <italic>z</italic>
<sub>b</sub>. (D) The average &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship (mean &#x000b1; SEM, <italic>n</italic> = 6), was obtained after first normalizing individual plots (see text) to mean &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> measured from +180 to +195 mV. The data are fit by the above function (solid line, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>a</sub> = +0.28 <italic>e</italic>; <italic>z</italic>
<sub>b</sub> = &#x02212;0.28 <italic>e</italic> ; <italic>a</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 119 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>b</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 4,240 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and reproduced by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> [dashed line: <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;</sub> = +0.28 <italic>e</italic>, &#x003b1;(0) = 244 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;</sub> = &#x02212;0.28 <italic>e</italic>, &#x003b2;(0) = 8,670 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub> = 0.155 <italic>e</italic>, &#x003b4;(0) = 49.4 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b3;</sub> = &#x02212;0.155 <italic>e</italic>, &#x003b3;(0) = 134 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>]. The rate constants in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> that describe voltage sensor movement (&#x003b1;, &#x003b2;) are 2.05-fold greater than (<italic>a</italic>, <italic>b</italic>) at all voltages. Thus &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> = 1/(<italic>a</italic> + <italic>b</italic>) is proportional the voltage-sensor time constant &#x003c4; = 1/(&#x003b1; + &#x003b2;). The parameters that describe the C&#x02013;O transition in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> (&#x003b4;, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b4;</sub>, &#x003b3;, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b3;</sub>), were adjusted to fit the <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> B) and to reproduce the time course of I<sub>K</sub> activation at the peak of the &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship (+153 mV).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f3"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The voltage-dependence of I<sub>K</sub> relaxation. (A) Activation and (B&#x02013;D) deactivation kinetics measured at 5&#x000b0;C are fit by exponential functions (solid lines). I<sub>K</sub> was activated in response to voltages from +100 to +240 mV. Deactivation was measured at the indicated voltages after a 50-ms depolarization to +120 mV.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f4"/></fig><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>The voltage dependence of &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>). (A) Time constants [&#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)] from the fits in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4A</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. B</xref>, are plotted versus voltage and fit (dashed line) by two exponential functions with the indicated equivalent charge (<italic>z</italic>). The prediction of a two-state model [&#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) = 1/(<italic>a</italic> + <italic>b</italic>), <italic>a</italic>=<italic>a</italic>
<sub>o</sub>*<italic>e</italic>
<sup><italic>z</italic><sub><italic>a</italic></sub><italic>e</italic><italic>kt</italic></sup>,<italic>b</italic>=<italic>b</italic>
<sub>o</sub>*<italic>e</italic>
<sup><italic>z</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub><italic>e</italic><italic>kt</italic></sup>] is indicated by a solid line (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>a</sub> = 0.37 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>b</sub> = 0.67 <italic>e</italic> ; <italic>a</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 4.86 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>b</italic>
<sub>o</sub> = 1,323 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). (B) &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) is plotted on a log scale versus voltage for all the records in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>. Data were shifted along the voltage axis by &#x00394;V<sub>h</sub> = +5.6 mV (see <sc>methods</sc>). Three regions of exponential voltage dependence are shown by dashed lines with the indicated equivalent charges (<italic>z</italic>). A solid curve indicates a fit to <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>, Patch 1). (C) &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V plots obtained from multiple experiments at 5&#x000b0; and 20&#x000b0;C (&#x025cb;) were normalized to mean &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>) at &#x02212;80 mV, and then averaged in 15-mV bins (&#x02022;). Solid curves indicate fits of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> to the averaged data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>: average 5&#x000b0; and 20&#x000b0;C). The dashed curve represents a fit of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S8">Fig. 8</xref> to the average 5&#x000b0;C data for V &#x0003c; +100 mV (<italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;1</sub> = &#x02212;0.45 <italic>e</italic>, &#x003b2;<sub>1</sub>(0) = 2,400 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b2;2</sub> = &#x02212;0.14 <italic>e</italic>, &#x003b2;<sub>2</sub>(0) = 700 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x003b1;2</sub> = &#x02212;0.26 <italic>e</italic>, &#x003b1;<sub>2</sub>(0) = 300 s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f5"/></fig><fig id="F6" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Steady state activation. (A) A family of I<sub>K</sub> evoked in response to 20-ms depolarizations (+80 to +280 in 20-mV steps, holding potential = &#x02212;80, 20&#x000b0;C). G<sub>K</sub>(V) was determined by measuring the tail current amplitude at &#x02212;80 mV immediately after each pulse. (B) The G<sub>K</sub>&#x02013;V relationships from 23 experiments (&#x025cb;) were normalized by G<sub>Kmax</sub> and shifted along the voltage axis to align half-activation voltages (see <sc>methods</sc>). The average G&#x02013;V (&#x02022;) represents the mean &#x000b1; SEM of the normalized-shifted data determined over 15-mV intervals. A Boltzmann function raised to a power of 3.2 (<italic>z</italic> = 0.69 <italic>e</italic>, solid line) represents the best fit to the individual data, excluding experiments where V<sub>max</sub> &#x0003c; 240 mV. G<sub>Kmax</sub> could not be directly determined for the excluded experiments; therefore, these data were normalized based on the Boltzmann<sup>3.2</sup> fit. Dashed lines indicate predictions of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> [&#x02208; = &#x003b4;/&#x003b3;, &#x02208;(0) = 0.367, <italic>z</italic>
<sub>&#x02208;</sub> = 0.295 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z<sub>J</sub></italic> = 0.55 <italic>e</italic>, V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>) = 145] and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> [<italic>L</italic>(0) = 2 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>, <italic>z<sub>L</sub></italic> = 0.4 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z<sub>J</sub></italic> = 0.55 <italic>e</italic>, V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>) = 145, <italic>D</italic> = 17]. (C) The data are replotted on a semi-log scale together with the Boltzmann<sup>3.2</sup> fit (solid line). The maximum voltage dependence of G&#x02013;V is indicated by a dashed line (<italic>z</italic> = 2.0 <italic>e</italic>). (D) Single channel currents were recorded at the indicated voltages and filtered at 20 kHz. The corresponding all-points histograms are plotted on a semi-log scale (points versus picoamperes). (E) Normalized open probability (<italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>/<italic>P</italic>
<sub>omax</sub>, see text) determined from single channel currents is plotted versus voltage for several experiments in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> (filled symbols) or 4.5 &#x003bc;M Ca<sup>2+</sup> (open symbols). The dashed line indicates the maximum voltage dependence of the macroscopic G&#x02013;V from C. (F) The normalized <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationship from &#x02212;120 to +300 mV combines the macroscopic and single channel data. Filled symbols indicate averages (mean &#x000b1; SEM, 15-mV bin width), while open symbols represent data from individual experiments. Predictions of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> (dashed line) and IX (solid line) are the same as in B.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f6"/></fig><fig id="F11" position="float"><label>Figure 11</label><caption><p>Interaction between voltage sensors and channel gating. Cartoons illustrate two hypothetical mechanisms of coupling between voltage-sensor movement and channel opening. Voltage sensors in each subunit are shown to undergo a transition between resting (&#x02212;) and activated (+) conformations. For simplicity, only states with all four voltage sensors in the same conformation are shown. The independent transitions of voltage sensors are abbreviated by dashed arrows. (A) A direct coupling mechanism assumes there exists a direct physical link between voltage sensor and a gate that controls the flow of ions through the pore. Such a mechanism does not allow channels to open unless voltage sensors are activated. (B) An allosteric mechanism assumes that channel opening involves a quaternary rearrangement of subunits that alters subunit&#x02013;subunit interactions (indicated by shaded areas between subunits). Voltage-sensor activation is also assumed to affect subunit&#x02013;subunit interaction, and is shown here as stabilizing the closed state when voltage sensors are in the (&#x02212;) conformation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f11"/></fig><fig id="F7" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Allosteric model: I<sub>K</sub> kinetics. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> was used to fit the time course of mSlo I<sub>K</sub> (solid lines; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>: Patch 2, &#x00394;V<sub>h</sub> = &#x02212;11.3 mV). (A<sub>1</sub> and A<sub>2</sub>) I<sub>K</sub> evoked at +180 mV at 7&#x000b0;C (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> A). (B) <italic>d</italic>(I<sub>K</sub>)/<italic>dt</italic> is plotted on a log&#x02013;log scale (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> B<sub>2</sub>). (C) The Cole-Moore shift (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> A).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f7"/></fig><fig id="F8" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Allosteric model: voltage dependence of I<sub>K</sub> kinetics. (A) The initial time course of I<sub>K</sub> activation at different voltages (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> B, 5&#x000b0;C) are fit by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>: Patch 1, &#x00394;V<sub>h</sub> = +5.6 mV). (B) The average &#x00394;<italic>t</italic>&#x02013;V relationship (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref> D) is compared with the prediction of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> for &#x00394;<italic>t</italic> (solid line) and the time constant of voltage-sensor movement &#x003c4;<italic><sub>J</sub></italic> = 1/(&#x003b1; + &#x003b2;) (dashed line). (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>: average 5&#x000b0;C). (C) <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (dashed lines; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>: Patch 1, &#x00394;V<sub>h</sub> = +5.6 mV) predicts a delay in tail currents measured from 0 to &#x02212;160 mV (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> C). (D) Tail currents and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> predictions (solid line) at &#x02212;40 and &#x02212;360 mV show initial deviation from an exponential fit (dashed lines, from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4C</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. D</xref>) at &#x02212;40 mV, but not at &#x02212;360 mV. Thus, a tail current delay is observed, but not at very negative voltages.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f8"/></fig><fig id="F9" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Effect of S4 mutation. G<sub>K</sub>&#x02013;V relationships for mSlo WT and S4 mutant R207Q in 0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> were obtained using both macroscopic and single channel currents as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> and are plotted on linear (A) and semi-log (B) scales. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> was used to fit both relationships (solid lines). Parameters are the same as in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref> [<italic>L</italic>(0) = 2 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>, <italic>z<sub>L</sub></italic> = 0.4 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z<sub>J</sub></italic> = 0.55 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>D</italic> = 17], except V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>) = &#x02212;100 mV for R207Q, while V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>) = 145 mV for WT.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f9"/></fig><fig id="F10" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Properties of the allosteric voltage-gating scheme. (A) The &#x003c4;(I<sub>K</sub>)&#x02013;V relationship determined by simulating <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (&#x02022;; <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table </xref>: average 5&#x000b0;C) can be reproduced by an analytical approximation (solid line) that assumes horizontal transitions are equilibrated. The voltage dependence of time constants for individual C&#x02013;O transitions are also plotted (&#x003c4;<sub>i</sub> = [&#x003b4;<sub>i</sub> + &#x003b3;<sub>i</sub>)<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>]. (B) <italic>P</italic>
<sub>o</sub>&#x02013;V relationships predicted by <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S9">Fig. 9</xref> (solid lines) are plotted on a semi-log scale as the allosteric factor <italic>D</italic> is adjusted [with <italic>z<sub>L</sub></italic> = 0.4 <italic>e</italic>, <italic>z<sub>J</sub></italic> = 0.55 <italic>e</italic>, V<sub>h</sub>(<italic>J</italic>) = 145]. The equilibrium constant <italic>L</italic> was adjusted together with <italic>D</italic> such that the half-activation voltage remained constant (for <italic>D</italic> = 5&#x02013;160: <italic>L</italic> = 2.18 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;4</sup>, 1.57 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;5</sup>, 1.05 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;6</sup>, 6.80 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;8</sup>, 4.33 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;9</sup>, and 2.72 <italic>e</italic>
<sup>&#x02212;10</sup>). A dashed line indicates the prediction of sequential <xref ref-type="fig" rid="S5">Fig. 5</xref> (from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JGP7962.f10"/></fig></floats-group></article>